Greetings everyone. Welcome to the fifth
applied active inference symposium. It's
November 12th, 2025.
Some brief introduction slides and then
to Carl Fristen for a keynote address
and discussion.
So, welcome to the Active Inference
Institute. We are a nonprofit
volunteer-run organization dedicated to
improving the rigor, accessibility, and
applicability of the active inference
framework.
Since 2021, we have hosted an annual
applied active inference symposium with
Carl as the as the first presenter back
in 2021,
which serves as an endofear celebration
and convening for our ecosystem. At the
link symposium.activeinference.institute
institute. You can look at all the
previous programs and proceedings.
We're here to highlight applied and
translational work in active inference
across domains and from groups around
the world. Meanwhile, we surface
opportunities and needs of our
ecosystem, get feedback and facilitate
connections among participants. That's
you. You can join the institute discord,
donate to support the work, stay tuned
via newsletter and actively infer on
about the program. There are three days
of programs and the bulk of the
proceedings will be livereamed to
YouTube at the three links that are
available at the program and you can
watch it live and rewatch it at the same
link and there may be some adjustment at
the fine scale with time zones and
pre-recorded and live and scheduling and
all fun kinds of things but big picture
there's going to be three live streams
that will consist the bulk of the
program.
In the participant registration, we
asked if people wanted their responses
to be public and for those who did, we
integrated their responses. So, you can
read the raw responses to people's qu to
questions that people were asked like
what would be interesting for them, what
would be useful, how can active
inference have a big impact in 2026. And
we also used LLM to integrate the
responses and do embeddings on the
responses. All kinds of cool stuff. So
you can check out that open source code.
A big thank you to our team of
co-organizers.
Alexandra Mava, Andrew Pasha, Bradley
Lucia, Christian Martin, Corey Slater,
Daniel Friedman, Maria Garcia, Maria
Louisa, Pablo FM, Sylvia Zang, and Zora
Ramaned. It was a great and streamlined
process with these co-organizers. So
absolutely was a team effort and I thank
them all again. If there's some kind of
session presenter or development that
you'd like to see in next year's
symposium, you would be welcome to
provide that feedback or even to step up
and be a co-organizer. It's a lot of
fun. Email us if you're interested.
Also, thank you to our sponsors. Our
first sponsor is Navigating Uncertainty,
a book bringing the science of active
inference and the free energy principle
to life through story, art, and human
experience by Anna Pereira with a
forward by Carl Fristen. And Anna will
have a presentation later in the
program. and also our sponsor for this
symposium, Upcycle Club, an independent
social initiative that actively supports
a select group of noteworthy
institutions and innovative projects
dedicated to fostering research,
education, and original thinking. So now
without further ado to Carl's keynote
and I thought how to introduce this
keynote and on this slide I have Carl
thinking of the 2012 paper the history
of the future of the basian brain where
there's a quote which was about the
neuroiming community but I believe it
applies to the active inference
community today as well and he wrote In
short, the futureing in short, the
future of imaging neuroscience is to
refine models of the brain to minimize
free energy where the brain refineses
models of the world to minimize free
energy. This endeavor itself minimizes
free energy because our community is
itself a self-organizing system. And so
here from the past to the predictive
future, we have generative AI and all
these different domains of application
for active inference. So hopefully a
fittingly aesthetic introduction to what
should be a very fascinating keynote
followed by a discussion.
So thank you Carl for joining and you
can share your screen and looking
forward to your keynote here.
Well, thank you for that lovely
introduction. Um, and just to say it's a
great pleasure uh to kick off uh this
symposium and I'd like also just to
reiterate um my thanks on behalf of the
the audience and the viewers to the
co-organizers and particularly you
Daniel for uh stewarding us all uh in
this community direction. It is uh it is
a great endeavor and I just want to
again thank you for that. Um so I'm
going to start um with a slightly
retrospective feel. Um I'm mindful that
now we're in almost the sort of second
generation of people um applying or
interested in the free energy principle
and in particular active inference. So
I'm going to stand back a bit and this
presentation is going to have a certain
retrospective
global take on the foundations and the
principles upon which active inference
is based and in particular it's based
upon a presentation given to the neuroai
workshop at last year's Europe and also
the um international active inference
workshop uh earlier this year in
Montreal.
However, this presentation's got a twist
because I know people always like to
know what the latest thing is. So, at
the end of this presentation, I'm hoping
just to foreground
um a domain of questions and challenges
that face artificial general
intelligence research. um the kinds of
um problem solving abstractions and
reasoning that we uh that are
characteristic of natural intelligence
that uh now have become a goal or a
target for certain sections of the
machine learning uh community. So um
what I'm going to do in order to sort of
look at how one could deploy or apply
active inference to understand formalize
and simulate logical reasoning and
abstraction. I'm going to refer back to
a rather old paradigm now, the three
ball paradigm, just to revisit that um
and look at how we can use active
inference in its most general sense to
underpin the sample efficiency that we
bring to the world when looking for
evidence for the way that we understand
the world. So, that's where we're going
to start. Um, in fact, I'm going to
cheat and um
we'll get Jeffrey Hinton to actually
start for us. Now, I'm not sure whether
this is going to um be audible on the
live stream. Uh, so Daniel, could if I
could um um ask you uh I'm just going to
play a few seconds and if you can hear
it, then we'll just continue. And if you
can't, I'll actually read out what Jeff
what Jeff actually said. Um, so let me
just start this.
>> I would like to meet Cal Bolts.
>> Was that audible? Excellent. Okay. So,
let me just put this in context. Um,
Jeff was being presented with the UCD
Ulyses Medal uh a year or so ago. Um,
and right at the end of his presentation
and indeed right at the end of the
question and answer um session from the
audience, he was asked the following
question. if you could go back in time
and meet your hero, academic hero, who
would you like to meet? And his response
was, I'd like to meet Helm Holtz. So,
let's just listen to his explanation for
that. And I'd like to meet Helm Holtz
believed in unconscious perceptual
inference. He basically thought that
when you're doing vision, you're doing
lots of inference, but it's not kind of
conscious deliberate inference. you're
inferring from the distal from the
proximal stimulus you're inferring what
the state of the world is that gave rise
to that and he was clearly right about
that so that was one branch of Helmz's
work a different branch of Helmz's work
was um free energy there's something
called Helmhold's free energy and what
Helmholds didn't realize was that if
you're trying to do inference in a
complicated model with complicated lat
variables a statistician would tell you
to do inference by given the current
parameters of your model, take the data
and figure out the best way for your
model to explain the data. And there
might be several ways for your model to
explain the data. But you have to figure
out the probability of each of those
ways in which your model could explain
the data in order to adjust the
parameter of your model. And what
variational inference says is actually
you don't have to get that probability
right. You can approximate that
probability and still guarantee you'll
learn a better model. or rather than
some band that'll improve. And so the
two completely different bits of
Helmos's career, the work on free energy
and the work on perceptual inference
were actually very closely related. And
free energy is the key to being able to
do perceptual inference tractably. And
I'd love to tell Helmans that
lovely. Uh so I'm basically going to uh
just try and unpack uh what Jeff was
intimating there and do so with
reference to three of the great um
intellectual architects of the physics
from my point of view at least um of
artificial intelligence. uh clearly
Helmholtz uh whose contributions come at
many many different levels also a nod to
Feman uh in the sense it wasn't quite
Helmholtz free energy um that um
underwrites variational inference the
free energy in question um is actually
due to uh Richard Feman but I also want
to acknowledge um the sort of physics of
measurement and observation and
certainly the perspective uh afforded by
Edwin gains in the context of things
like the uh maximum entropy or caliber
principles. Um so
Helm Holtz, where do we start with Helm
Holtz's contributions? Uh my favorite
point is a slide which I've shown many
many times. Um summarized by this
beautiful quote, objects are always
imagined as being present in the field
of vision as would have to be there in
order to produce the same impression on
the nervous system. So this is his
notion of unconscious imperence. This is
his notion that the brain is a
constructive organ generating
explanations in an inside out kind of
way that provide an accurate and as
we'll see simple account of sensory
impressions on the nervous system. And
clearly this is very closely related to
the notions of uh perception as
hypothesis testing by people like
Richard Gregory. ideas that were taken
with great effect and deployed in
machine learning uh by people like
Jeffrey Hinton and Peter Diane uh who
actually built a Helmholtz machine um as
a metaphor for the basian brain lending
or borrowing from u probability theory
in the sense of basian statistics and of
course the work of Richard Fineman um on
his work on the pathogal formulation of
quantum electronamics.
So what's this notion of um
unconscious inference? Um one could
argue it goes right back to the students
of Plato. I'm looking it back to the
16th century. This um I think um
beautifully illustrates the notion of
unconscious inference or perhaps even
conscious inference in this instance.
Um, so this is a painting by a 16th
century oil painter famed for painting
still lives that when viewed from
another perspective give you a very
different kind of visual impression. So
if previously you saw a bowl of fruit
but now you see a face, the point being
made here is that you made that face.
This is something that you brought to
the table as an explanation, a
hypothesis, a model, um a fantasy
literally uh making the brain a
fantastic organ, a purveyor of
explanations and fantasies that best uh
explain our sensory input. I think that
perspective lends um a a a a certain um
gravity to um Fineman's meme uh which we
all uh quote um um regularly. um what I
cannot create I do not understand and
you know that acquires I think a very
concrete me uh meaning um when read in
light of Helmholtz's notion of
unconscious inference if you can't
create it on the inside you have no
understanding knowledge belief no real
um ability to recognize what what it is
so I'm here reading the creation again
in this sort of constructive perspective
on the brain in as a statistical organ
creating explanations for its sensorium.
Um how can one formalize that? Well, we
can uh again appeal to uh Fman's um free
pathological formulation and free energy
or use of variational um calculus of
variations to elaborate the right kind
of objective functions that allow you to
solve very difficult inference problems.
um they are difficult because they
entail marginalization or impossible
integration problems but they can be
rendered tractable and converted into
optimization problems through these
variational bounds and in particular the
uh variational free energy as a bound on
log evidence. So what do I mean by that?
Well, um, if we just think carefully
about the nature of things that could
possibly, um, hold beliefs or, um, have
beliefs or make inferences about other
things. Then immediately we have to
introduce a distinction between the
thing that is observing, inferring,
measuring and the thing that is
observed, measured or we are making
inferences about. And statistically uh
this is the marov blanket due to jude
pearl um and simply separates the world
into the self or the observer and the
non-self or the observed and the
birectional exchange between these two
systems here cast in terms of a mark of
blanket comprising sensory states and
active states. The sensory states are
mediating the effects of the world on
the inside. Whereas the active states
are reciprocally mediating the effects
of the inside on the world through some
kind of action autonomic reflexes or uh
uh actually acting um with by say mus uh
muscles or motor system. Um and this um
this construction um this sort of
partition separation disambiguation
between the observed and the observer um
enables one to apply fman's path
integral formulation to the dynamics of
any system that yields to this kind of
separation between self and non-self and
I've just summarized this here in terms
of uh the free energy principle where we
can associate how or we can um describe
and demonstrate that the dynamics the
rate of change of my internal states so
my neural activity and my active states
together sometimes referred to as
autonomous states why well because they
don't depend upon the external states by
construction by this separation of the
self from the non-self um and if we can
do that we can um now just write down uh
the dynamics of of those autonomous
states I repeat my internal states and
my active states as a gradient flow or a
process that looks as if it is
minimizing in the sense of optimization
this variational function um of my
sensory input and the beliefs about the
outside that are parameterized
by my internal states. And here's the
familiar expression or one uh way of
writing down that expression. Um this
has been used to great effect in terms
of understanding uh things like
predictive coding with reflexes which
we'll uh cover briefly later. Um and
sort of
simple um from the point of view for
example of um control theory sort of
control as inference. And I I just
wanted to sort of draw a bright line
between two kinds of um application of
active inference that rests upon the
notion of beliefs about what I am doing.
Um that takes us from control as
inference into planning as inference
where I now have in mind a a probabistic
representation of what I am going to do
uh and certainly what I'm going to do
into the future. Um, interestingly,
if one traces back the origins of that
particular move, it just rests upon um
considering big things possibly with a
sort of deep or hierarchical structure
on the inside where one now um where the
active states no longer have direct
access to the internal states deep
inside um some uh internal structure. So
if I just remove that, something really
interesting happens. Um what happens is
we can now regard the active states
which were previously real variables
that had direct access to the internal
states as various causes of the sensory
states. But if we're now reading the
dynamics of my internal states as making
inferences about the causes of my
sensations, having beliefs about what is
out there, then now I am licensed to
describe my internal states as including
beliefs about my own action. And this
now um leads to the notion of planning
as inference and introduces something
called expected free energy. Why
expected? Well, if I've got beliefs
about my future and in particular the
consequences of my actions in the
future, those observations, those
sensations, those data are now no longer
real variables. They now become random
variables because they haven't yet
occurred. And now that means if I want
to evaluate the free energy, I now have
to take an expectation over the
posterior predictive density over the
sensations that I would cause in the
future if I committed to this particular
action. Um so you could say that this is
a more if you like authentic kind of
active inference in the sense that it
could be applied to things like you and
me. Um basically um using the path
integral formulation to link us uh link
the markoff blanket to full active
inference where we have paths of least
action that are determined by the free
energy for my internal states my belief
updating and for my action the expected
free energy. So let's just visit those
two sort of um aspects of free energy
minimization sometimes cast I repeat as
a path of least a principle of least
action. Let's just look at the sort of
the internal states minimizing
variational free energy. Um and this is
where the second foundational
contribution of helmhotes comes into
play. Um what we can do is if we now
interpret the internal states as
parameterizing some beliefs about the
external states uh in this example
parameterized in terms of a Gaussian
distribution or Gaussian belief um then
because we know the expression for the
dynamics of the internal states um we
can use the help of decomposition to
split the dynamics into two parts.
And what I've done here is um associate
those two parts for those people who are
interesting that those two parts are
effectively a dissipative flow that
descends free energy gradients and a
non-dissipative or conservative flow
that um circulates in a certain fashion
on the iso contours of uh of the free
energy. I can associate this
non-disipative and dissipative part with
the prediction and update of a calman
filter which would be one very simple
example of um um inference under a very
simple uh generative model and uh the
basis of control is inference things
like linear quadratic control. But the
story I want to tell here really is that
we can associate if I knew the state of
the world or had an expectation about
the state of the world. I also know how
it's going to change. I can predict how
it's going to change the mu dot up here.
But I also and that would be associated
with the solenoidal the non-disiplined
part. I you know I have not been
informed by any sensory information at
this stage. But when I do have access to
sensory information, I can now evaluate
the free energy gradient and update my
expectation in the light of the sensory
evidence and in particular um the uh
prediction error that is effectively the
free energy gradient. So what's a
prediction error? Well, imagine we had
this impression on our um sensory
epithelia and I had in mind
an internal state that represented the
belief that this particular impression
was caused by a howling dog. And if I
had a generative model that could
generate the consequences, the sensory
consequences of a howling dog causing my
sensory input, I could take the
prediction, subtract it from the actual
sensation and produce a prediction
error, a mismatch. And then all this
equation is saying, all the Helmholds
decomposition is saying is it will look
as if this prediction error is driving
my beliefs in order to minimize the
prediction error where when the
prediction error is um um minimized, I'm
minimizing my free energy gradients and
I found a free energy minima.
So this um provides I think a really
nice perspective on filtering on data
evidence accumulation uh that is can be
interpreted directly in terms of Helm
Holtz's uh decomposition. Um notice that
all that this is saying is that you're
minimizing your prediction error as a
proxy for a variational free energy.
You're never going to actually know uh
what's out there. In this instance, it
was actually a cat. Um so what about
James? What's another way of looking at
this sort of uh free energy minimizing
um description of self-organization
where the self is distinguished via
markoff blanket from non-self. I put
this up here um because I think that you
know it does provide a really
interesting uh dual perspective on the
problem of in or the description
afforded by inference measurement and
observation in general and I've just
expressed the free energy now in terms
of um a an energy um and an entropy an
expected energy or a potential uh and an
entropy here And this um this entropy
here um we can see if we want to
minimize a free energy we need to
maximize the entropy of our beliefs. And
of course this is exactly what James was
saying in terms of the measurements that
we do in physics um but crucially under
constraints. So what are the
constraints? Well, they're just the
constraints that are supplied by a
generative model. Um for us you're
affording an accurate explanation of
some data um under a generative model uh
where the generative model is usually
expressed in terms of some likelihood
and prior the probability of some
outcomes or observations given the
hidden states that are hidden behind the
markoff blanket and some prior beliefs
that characterize my model namely the
probability of those latent or hidden
states.
I put this up because it there's a um
there's often um a degree of confusion
when talking about the um the
thermodynamics of inference. Um so you
know if I want to maximize um my uh the
entropy of my beliefs why is it that
often the free energy principle is cast
as an account of or a description of
things that sustain themselves by
minimizing the dispersion or the
dissipation of their say sensory states
or observational states. Um the paradox
is very easily resolved in this instance
by noting that when people talk about
entropy the you have to specify the
particular probability density or
distribution to which that entropy
applies and in this particular instance
um the maximum entropy uh principle
applies to the entropy of the beliefs
and this entails a minimum entropy
production uh principle. um and that I
think can be rendered very very um
obvious in the sense if I now just take
the time average of the free energy we
can see immediately that as the path
entropy goes down the uh goes uh in one
direction um the entropy uh goes in the
other direction. And so if I maximize my
path integral by minimizing my free
energy or my expected free energy
then I'm implicitly minimizing the
dispersion or dissipation of my uh
exchanges with the environment through
the outcomes or observations supplied by
that environment.
So maximum path entropy is basically
equal to or equivalent to a minimum
entropy production principle very much
in the spirit of um the theory of
dissipative structures. uh due to pri
um another way of re um of um
understanding or intuiting um the
characteristic uh or the implications of
free energy is just to re express it to
somebody machine learning would express
it u or possibly even um basic
statistics.
So I've just rearranged the terms and
I've just arranged them um in terms of
the accuracy, the expected probability
of some outcomes um under some beliefs
about what caused those outcomes, the
latent states um minus a complexity. So
what's the complexity? Well, it's just
the divergence between my posterior
beliefs, my um um the beliefs encoded by
my internal states and prior beliefs. So
that scores the divergence
between what I believe now a priori
before seeing some data and after seeing
some observations a postiori it
literally scores the degree to which I
change my mind in order to provide an
accurate account of the data. uh and of
course that's just an expression of
principles of indifference or Okam's uh
uh principle but interestingly it also
has thermodynamic uh coralates um by
appeal to things like the Jazinski
equality and Landau's principle
you can now say that if I want to change
my mind if I want to pay a complexity
cost in accounting for my observations
my measurement um in a way that provides
an accurate account of that measurement
or observation. Um then I'm going to
have to spend energy. It costs some
work, some thermodynamic work to erase
bits and to move on some statistical
manifold or to induce a divergence
between my prior and my post area. Which
means that in minimizing free energy
equivalently in machine learning in
maximizing the EV the negative free
energy or the um the evidence lower
bound
I'm implicitly trying to minimize my
computational cost and that um also
impacts in a thermodynamic uh context
that I'm going to do it as
thermodynamically if as efficiently as
possible. Um and of course this is just
one aspect of biometic and or biotic
self-organization
um right through to uh kind of influence
that Helm Holtz had in mind. So that
perspective allows us to sort of look at
the sort of what some people call merely
reflexive active inference because we
haven't as yet got to planning as
inference um through a number of
different lenses and I've just
summarized these here in a slide which
I'm sure many of you have seen before.
Um so at the moment we're just talking
about um the notion of describing
ourselves as minimizing free energy or
trying to maximize this um evidence
bound or maximize the model evidence the
evidence through our generative models
through updating our beliefs um and
noting that our actions should also
minimize exactly this quantity. So our
actions are just going to fulfill our
predictions
formally. Then um what does this mean or
how could one interpret this? Well, we
know that uh first of all the free
energy is a bounded approximation to the
log evidence um the log uh probability
of some outcomes uh given me um as a um
you know the self in question. Um and
what that basically means is I can
interpret this log probability as the
kind of outcomes that are characteristic
of the kind of thing that I am. So they
have meaning for me. They characterize
me. Uh you know I am um have a certain
temperature. I have a certain status. I
have all sorts of exchanges with the
environment and all of those
environments are characteristic or
typical or define the kind of thing that
I am. And from this that interpretation
um of free energy um leads to things
like reinforcement learning. If I was a
control theorist, it could be cast in
terms of optimal control theory. Or if I
was an economist, it would be expected
utility theory. If I was an information
theorist, the negative of of this log
marginal likelihood or log model
evidence is known as selfinformation.
Um also known as surprisal, more simply
surprise. And it just scores the
improbability how uncharacteristic this
exchange with the environment would be
if I am me. Um and that reading of this
quantity here uh the free energy in and
of itself um can then um forge links
with information theory the infamax
principle the principle of maximum
mutual information or equivalently
minimum redundancy principles due to
barlow and of course the free energy
principle itself.
That's good. If I now take the time
expectation or average of
self-information or surprise, I now get
entropy. So now we come back to the
minimum entropy production principle
that James was considering from the
point of view of maxent or max caliber
uh principles. Um and what does that
mean? Well, it just means that it will
look as if my autonomous states, my
sensory states and my control states or
active states um are those that on
average try to minimize the dispersion
of my exchanges with the environment. Of
course, this is the holy grail of
self-organization as exemplified in
synergetics uh due to Haken. And if I
was a physiologist, it's just a
statement of homeostasis that I am the
kind of thing that keeps my essential
variables within viable bounds and
ensures that they they do not dissipate
um uh beyond those uh characteristic
values. The final interpretation which
of course is the one we're familiar with
is that this probability of some
outcomes given me um can also be
described as um model evidence if I
associate me as a generative model of
the world in which I am immersed. And
this basically says that free energy
minimizing is just maximizing model
evidence um sometimes referred to as uh
self-evidencing. And this is a provides
a sort of formal account to the basian
brain evidence accumulation and
particular implementations such as
predictive coding that rest upon the um
the isomorphism between free energy
gradients and uh precision weighted
prediction error.
So that's um from free energy to um
self-evidencing. Um what about this sort
of second kind of active inference where
we now um instead of just picking those
actions that minimize free um
variational free energy. What if we now
make inferences and now describe our
internal states as holding beliefs about
what we are doing uh and possibly what
we are doing into the future. sometimes
referred to as policies pi here that now
will minimize the expected free energy
under some um I repeat posterior
predictive density of the consequences
the outcomes that ensue if I committed
to a particular sequence of actions or
combination of actions known as a policy
and this is where we move from the free
energy to the expected free energy and
I've just written this out in full
because you know even if you don't like
equations I think there's a a lovely
iconic symmetry here um which is um um
tells you a lot about ways in which you
can understand the motivations
for behavior um and the implicit um
intentional aspects of the behaviors
that I infer myself committing to. Um so
I've just written out the free energy in
terms of a mixture of complexity and
accuracy. um and um rewrite just moved
terms around to uh foreground the fact
that we can also express this as a KL
bound or divergence um um or a band on
the log evidence um and it's a band
simply because the KL divergence between
my beliefs about latent states and the
true posterior can never be less than
zero by construction.
So if I now take the expectation of
these quantities um under some
consequences conditioned upon a policy
what happens? Well the complexity
becomes risk the inaccuracy becomes
ambiguity and the divergence and log
evidence become expected information
gain and expected value. So just to
unpack that just let us just sort of
look at these terms and see how we can
interpret them very much in the spirit
of the uh the previous slide looking at
merely um reflexive active inference. So
let's assume that first of all I don't
have any prior preferences. I don't have
any probabilistic description of the
characteristic outcomes um that I would
expect given me or given my generative
model. What are we left with?
Well, we're left with another KL
divergence, but this one is an
interesting one um in the sense that
it's um it is going to be maximized
simply because now the outcomes are in
the future and they now become random
variables. Uh and what is it a um um an
information gain or a pay divergence or
um um an on average a mutual
information? What is it between? Well,
it's basically between
the beliefs I would have about the
states of affairs in the world out there
in the future if I were able to see the
consequences or observe the consequences
of those states relative to if I did
not. In other words, it's scoring the
information that is obtained by acting
in this way. It basically scores the
epistemic value or the epistemic
affordance.
um it scores the degree to which I'm
going to resolve my uncertainty about
states of affairs in the future if I did
this. Uh in the BA in the visual search
literature, this is often referred to as
basing surprise. um is also
mathematically equivalent to maximizing
mutual information between cause and
consequence where cause are my hidden or
latent states and the consequence are
the observable outcomes or consequences
of those states conditioned upon some
policy or active intervention um on the
world under my generative model.
Let's take a particular kind of
uncertainty off the table. Let's assume
for simplicity that we can see every
state of the world directly. So now my
observations
become the states of the world and the
states of the world become the
observations. So there's no ambiguity
about what um about the states or the
causes of the observed consequences. If
I remove the ambiguity, I'm le left with
another cha divergence. This time we
want to minimize it.
And what are we minimizing? Well,
effectively, we're just minimizing the
divergence between what I believe will
happen if I commit to this policy
relative to my prior preferences that
characterize the outcomes that are
characteristic of me. Um, and that
basically um scores my policies in terms
of how close can I keep myself to my
pride preferences. Um in engineering
this would be known as um pathog kl uh
control. Uh you could also substitute
model predictive control uh and some
kinds um of basian rl um under this uh
under this formalism. If you're an
economist this would be um risks
sensitive control.
Let's now make a final move and remove
all reducible uncertainty from the
problem. So now there is no more
information to be gained from this
environment. I'm now completely familiar
with this environment and I cannot
resolve my uncertainty anymore. What am
I left with? Well, I'm just left with
this um uh quantity which we have
previously associated with value. Um the
expected value. Uh so from the point of
view of economics, this would just be uh
expected utility theory. the value I
expect given my beliefs about the future
under a particular under a particular
policy.
So notice what we've done here. We've
we've actually derived a number of
really important um characterizations or
descriptions of motivated behavior or
optimal behavior in some sort um um
simply by selectively removing different
sources of uncertainty. But the most
general case um is this decision-m under
uncertainty that um entails a principled
approach to information gathering or
uncertainty reduction and I've tried to
illustrate that here just by appealing
to the dual aspects of baze optimal
action or decision-m um so it has two
aspects um the first is nicely captured
by the ability of the expected value to
score the probability that I'm likely to
to uh pursue this pro uh this policy and
of course that's exactly what you'll
find if you read books on basin decision
theory. So um this would be if you like
the part of the bay optimality that
rests upon uh optimal basin decision
theory. But there's another way of being
baze optimal and that's um often cast in
terms of ba uh the principles of optimal
bay optimal experimental designing your
experiment to elicit those data that
resolve the greatest amount of
uncertainty about your hypotheses u the
uh pertaining to the way that those data
were generated or caused. Um, and this
goes right back to the 1950s with people
like Dennis Lindley looking at the
information theoretic criteria which of
course adjusts the expected information
gain or the ex epistemic affordance that
we've just described um that underwrites
exploratory behavior designing the right
kind of experiments uh in order to
resolve uncertainty so that you can
become exploitative uh in accord with
BA's optimal decision theory. Um
together expected value and information
gain just mean a negative expected free
energy. Um um and you know one would
could argue this is the essence of
active inference beyond a merely
reflexive active inference. Um what I
want to do now is just sort of return to
these three um three sort of
perspectives uh or contributions uh to
the free energy but from now a much more
technical um uh perspective or a formal
perspective. And what I've done here is
write out the free energy as an accuracy
term and then all the different bits of
complexity
that are contributed by the various sets
of unknowns in my generative model and
every set usually brings along uh a mean
field factor or partition of the
unknowns the random variables of
different kinds. Um so I picked out here
the unknown states the random variables
that are the latent or the hidden states
behind the markoff blanket that change
from moment to moment. Uh we don't know
um we don't know our policies. Um this
is another random variable that I'm
making inferences over and then
selecting the from the uh selecting the
most likely policy. Um but also I have
um model parameters. I have parameters
of a model. Here I'm summarizing the
parameters in terms of a likelihood
tensor. um which we'll come back to
later um um a um uh that has in terms of
the deployment of the of the parameters
within say a tensor, it also has a
particular structure. So we not only do
we have um beliefs about states of the
affairs, the ways in which we're going
to interrogate or act upon the world,
but also we have beliefs about the
contingencies, the laws um the
parameterizations, the associations that
underwrite the cause effect structure um
that are installed in our generative
models. Now the key observation here is
that if I can be described as a free
energy minimizing thing then there are a
number of ways in which I can minimize
my free energy. I can change my beliefs.
I can change my mind about states of the
world and we could call that perception
um by changing Q through my internal
states to minimize uh the uh the
variational free energy or the negative
free energy in this instance. um but I
can also
change my posterior beliefs about the
parameters of my generative model. So we
have a nice distinction now between sort
of inference and learning and I'm using
active learning in the sort of
traditional sense um certainly promoted
by people like David McKay in the in the
1980s and '9s. Um
and the difference here is it's exactly
the same maths. It's just it usually
unfolds over progressively longer uh
time scales. So I I have to do lots of
evidence accumulation or information
gathering to resolve uncertainty about
states of the worlds and how they
change. And then on the basis of those
beliefs, I accumulate those beliefs and
um assimilate that into um optimizing my
beliefs about the parameters, say the
connection weights in a uh in a neural
network um or the dish counts in a uh in
a tensor network. um um that would
correspond to this slow process of free
energy minimization. Um that basically
is minimizing the complexity of my model
of the world, maximizing its
compressibility, maximizing mutualation.
All of these being equivalent
perspectives on the same imperative u to
minimize to maximize the um the marginal
likelihood or the model evidence. The
final um thing though is that not only
can we change our posterior beliefs
encoded by the the the you know our um
internal states, we can also minimize
the free energy by changing our prior
beliefs. Now we're familiar with that in
terms of um predicating our prior over
what to do next, our policies on
expected free energy, but we can also do
the same with respect to a prize over
the latent states and crucially the very
model itself. And that's what I want to
pursue in the final part um of the of
this uh of this presentation. Um so what
we're we're talking about now is that
that there are lots of opportunities um
to minimize free energy. Um and if we're
all free energy minimizing things, it's
likely that we are will show evidence of
these kinds of minimization processes
such that minimizing um changing our
prior to minimize free energy could be
regarded as a description of attentional
selection.
>> We're talking about now is that that
there are lots of opportunities
Sorry, continue. Carl,
>> right, I'm talking to myself. Um,
uh, and the pri um, sorry, policy
selection would be um, you know, a neat
description of, um, optimizing my prior
beliefs about what I'm going to do next.
Um and that leads to if with this sort
of use of a selection word um
appropriate to the kinds of unknowns
that constitute my generator model leads
to the notion that um we can also
minimize free energy um through model
selection uh through a process akin to
structure learning. Um so I'm going to
close with an example and then just show
you um sort of the kind of things that
we've we've been um certainly with
colleagues at versus recently focusing
on in terms of generalizing this notion
of optimizing our priors over different
aspects of the generative models. This
is a paradigm which I'm sure most of you
have seen before and if you haven't the
purpose I'm of showing it again is just
to enable you to think about the way
that you
abstract the way that you reason about
the cause effect structure and in
particular how do you test hypotheses
about the mappings from states of play
states of affairs in the world and some
correct response response the rule that
underlies um a reward or some feedback
that you are correct. So what we're
talking about here is sort of a a
calculus of abstraction, a calculus of
reasoning and a calculus of rule
discovery where the rule can stand in
for some kind of symmetry, some kind of
equivariance, um some structure that
explains when you are right, when you've
got the right answer. Um, and this um
this is a the three ball paradigm.
Daniel, do you want to play this? Have
you forgotten the rule?
>> Go for it.
>> Okay. Well, let's Yeah, if you haven't
forgotten the rule, that's good because
we can get through this more quickly,
but I normally I would play this game
with the audience uh just to get them
into the spirit of introspecting. How do
we solve these kinds of abstraction
problems or rule discovery uh problems?
Um, so the game normally is is presented
as follows. You um you're going to be
presented uh with three colored balls
and you're going to choose or your game
or your job is to choose the correct
color based upon the arrangement of the
three large circles. Um, and the um
location of the correct color depends
upon the color of the upper circle,
which in this instance is blue. And then
what I'm going to do um is give you the
correct answer um and just leave that on
the screen so that you can remember past
instances, past trials so that you can
start accumulating evidence for against
different hypotheses or rules that could
be brought to the table to explain
what's the correct color. So that's all
you know. That's your prior beliefs. Uh
and then we normally play with the
audience a game. Uh and here there are
um you know a series of games starting
with uh the one that we saw previously
and then a series of of examples. And
what we're going to do or what I'm going
to ask Daniel to do is to guess until he
thinks he's discovered the rule and then
tell us if he's got the right rule. And
I'm interested in how sample efficient
he is. I'm interested in how many
exposures does he have to um entertain
before he suddenly gains insight into
the rule, before he has that aha moment.
Um and indeed, if you're watching this
um now or later, um you know, the the
the just think about the uh the
experience of this kind of rule
discovery. You know, is it a gradual
thing? Does it happen all of a sudden?
Are you able to um mentalize it? Is it a
propositional thing? Are you arguing in
words? Or does it just come into pop
into mind? These are all really
interesting aspects of this how one
would formulate or formalize um this
kind of abstract reasoning or logical
induction. Um right. So let's start.
Daniel, what we start with this um this
little game here, this epoch here. Uh
what color do you think is the correct
color?
>> Green.
Excellent. And for those of you um who
might not have noticed, this is exactly
the same as the example on the previous
slide. So I I'm assuming that Daniel was
>> That was training data. That was
training data.
>> Ah, right. So what you what are you
going to go for this time?
>> Red.
>> I'm sorry it was green. And of course
there is not sufficient evidence at this
stage for you to possibly guess any kind
of rule. Um, how have another go. Let's
go to this one.
>> Blue,
>> right? Well, think again. If if the
correct color is is is on is in a
particular location, um, can it be blue
if there's no blue uh on the screen?
>> I I'm open to some very creative rules.
>> Okay, we'll go with red.
>> Okay, then let's do that. Bye, Joe.
You're correct, sir. And how about this
one?
>> Blue.
>> You're going for blue. I'm afraid it was
green.
>> Okay,
>> this is this is this is desperately
unfair. So, when I normally do this with
an audience, we give people about 20 or
30 seconds between each example so they
can mull through alternative hypotheses
and suddenly spot the one that's uh
explained the data before. My uh at this
stage I I no one in the audience will
will have caught it. Uh D, let's give a
bit more information. What do you
think's the correct answer here?
>> Green.
>> Well done. Do you have an idea as to
what might be the rule?
Always green unless otherwise absent.
That's close. It's not quite the rule.
Uh but that's that's certainly close.
Do you want to think about it just a
little bit longer? This is relevant
because um what when I'm going to
simulate when I simulate this game um
there is a process of offline
introspection that requires you to spend
some time rifling through different um
hypotheses or explanations for this
particular rule or cause effect
structure. So, I'm deliberately witting
to give Danielle some time to to spot
any rules that he he might um bring to
the table to make the next predictions.
What are you going to predict for this
one? You you've already got this one, so
this is easy.
>> Blue.
>> Um, you've just told me the
>> or green on top. Oh, it depends on the
color of the upper circle. It doesn't
say it doesn't depend on other things.
Yeah, the all the information you need
is in the the arrangement of of these of
these three balls. And what you've told
me so far is when um the uh and all all
you the sort of the the cue if you like
is the color of the central ball. So
when you've already told it when the
central ball is green uh the is green.
>> Yeah, you've already told me that. And
>> when the central ball is blue, it's also
green.
Yeah. Well, you don't know that. Oh, uh,
well, that that was certainly one
instance, but it could have been this
one here.
>> Fair enough.
Perhaps have another choice.
>> Blue.
Ah,
>> it's red.
>> Okay, then red.
Correct.
>> Then green.
>> Correct.
>> Red.
>> Green.
>> Green. Green.
>> Oh. Oh, you
>> blue. If it's blue.
>> Green.
blue.
>> It can't It can't be green because
there's no there's no green on the uh on
on the
I'm teasing you and it's very unfair to
te I should uh the correct answer was in
this instance blue. Um so the the
solution now unfortunately we we don't
have access to the audience but some of
you um what normally happens is um after
a couple of um trials following the
point at which Daniel spotted the sort
of first element of of the rule um um
people suddenly get the insight with
very very sparse information but so
usually by about sort of uh uh between
five and eight uh trials And the the
correct answer was exactly as Daniel um
realized even by the fifth one I think
um that when the center is green the
correct color is always green. When the
center is red the correct color is on
the left and when the center is blue the
correct color is on the right.
Um so discounting the first one you
would not have known that until you now
got to the 1 2 3 4 5 6 7. Um so this
illustrates you know not a desperately
complicated rule but certainly has a
certain context sensitivity. Um and the
question I want to ask now is why is it
that Daniel partially was able to do
this um um or was able to infer this on
the basis of um well certainly part of
the rule after 1 2 3 4 5 um given um he
hadn't even seen a blue a Q apart from
the training uh trial um before. So in
principle this is quite remarkable that
you he was able to make some inference
to have a hypothesis in the absence of
any definitive data which is um which
you know is the kind of abstraction and
our remarkable efficiency to discover
latent structure in the world even
before we've actually seen it. Um but
let's just see if we can actually um get
a baze optimal agent to um match that
kind of performance. Um there's
something which I have to implement in
the simulations uh which was not made
explicit in the task instructions. Um
that the simulated agent has to actually
look at each of the location from a
start location and thereby has to choose
where to look as well as whether to
select a particular color um prior to
it. uh um um uh after it's decided what
color to choose. Um so there are two
kinds of actions in this particular um
example. It's where am I going to look
and what am I going to choose? What
would I need? What latent states would I
need to generate um the outcomes? Well,
the outcomes are basically what color am
I seeing? Um and where am I looking? um
and what kind of feedback am I getting?
Is it sort of have I yet to make a
choice or if I have made a choice is it
right or is it uh is it wrong? So to
generate these what where feedback
outcomes I need to
um I need to know what the latent states
of the world are and the latent states
are basically a sort of context that
establishes the rules. So for example,
if the correct color is on the right um
then uh well what is the correct color?
say it's red. Um, and if I know that the
correct color is on the on the right and
I know that the correct color is red and
I know where I am looking and I know
whether I have chosen or not, I can
generate all of these things. And how do
I generate these things? Well, I I do so
through a likelihood mapping technically
a likelihood tensor that goes from these
um latent states and probabilistically
maps to the outcomes. So what I've done
here is just show the rule that we used
in the previous example in the form of
an unfolded um likelihood tensor um
which is fairly simple to read. All it's
saying is that you know if um the rule
uh the current rule context is that the
correct color is on the left then
there's a lawful mapping between what I
am seeing
um and what the correct color is uh
provided I am looking at the left. But
if I'm looking at the center then I'll
just see red. And hence that was the
rule that whenever the center was red I
would should look to the left. When I
look to the left I can now identify the
correct color because of this isomorphic
mapping between the two. If I'm looking
anywhere looking to right that doesn't
count. Um so what we're doing is
basically visualizing the the nature of
a rule in terms of these sparse
isomorphisms these sparse mappings in a
likelihood um mapping um between cause
and consequence. And of course you
didn't know that you did know that if um
the the color um of the uh center square
so I'm looking at the center there's a
unique color to one of three rules
because there are three colors but you
don't know what the rule is. So you
started off with this uh and you were
hoping to gather enough uh information
or evidence to eventually disclose this
structured um likelihood mapping. So we
could actually simulate that and this is
what's um been done here. I'm just
showing um the results of simulating a
base optimal agent um with those
ignorant prior as naive prior um and
looking at its performance um over 32
games each game comprising sort of uh
four sorry four moves five exposures or
or uh to the same stimuli. Um we don't
need to go into any detail here what's
going on. This just shows you the the
policies about where to look and whether
to select something um that are selected
given all the cues um um the central
cues at the top here. Um what we what we
will notice though is that after about
um um 13 uh or 14 um observations,
the agent is continually correct, makes
no mistakes. Um which is um roughly the
same as as Daniel's performance even
though he half got the rule. Um at that
point the free energy reduces on average
and the confidence namely the uh the
precision or the negentropy of the
belief distribution over what to do next
what policies to engage in uh suddenly
um remains quite high. So there seems to
be a sort of a reasonably abrupt change
um after about the 15th um uh the 15th
exposure uh to a low free energy
confident correct kind of behavior. Um
and um the question is um you know what
what underlines what underwrites this
this qualitative um uh sorry
quantitative uh change in in behavior.
Um what we can get an idea just by
contrasting the belief updating um
before and after learning sufficient
amount of contingencies to have an
insight into the rule. Um and what I'm
showing here is just the simulated
belief updating and image format but
also the simulated local field
potentials or if you do
electrophysiology uh event related
potentials um associated with looking at
the different cues before and after
acquiring some knowledge through
parameter learning. So updating my
beliefs about the likelihood mapping um
uh denoted by a and the thing I just
wanted to highlight it's really
interesting that you know when I've
learned what the meaning of these
instructional clues are when I have some
understanding of the cause effect
structure then that meaning is actually
reflected in belief updating. So
suddenly certain cues um suddenly evoke
belief updating and simulated neural
responses in those representations of
the context. So suddenly I can recognize
I'm in one context simply because I and
it's me and its implications simply
because I've now learned the
implications. I've learned the rules. Um
but one has to ask well why look
anywhere? There's no reward in this
paradigm. um you know what why would you
um what what what drives what motivates
um scanning around in the first place?
Well, of course, we know what the answer
to that is. It's it's basically um the
expected information gain but in this
instance not over the normal kind that
is associated with basin surprise namely
resolving uncertainty about states of
the world but using exactly the same
construct but resolving uncertainty
about the actual contingencies the rules
the parameters of my generative model.
And in some literature's this
distinction um between information gain
over states and information gain over
parameters is known as novelty and
salience. And all we're saying is that
generalizing expected information gain
to cover the parameters of a generative
model um equips you with a kind of
curiosity that can be described in terms
of what happens if I do that uh what
will happen. So it's not what is behind
this door but can I open this door? um
and we are motivated to be curious in
this kind of way. So our intentional
behavior is now motivated by this um by
responding to epistemic affordances in
the environment that allows us to slowly
unear the contingencies and the
parameterizations
um in our generative model. Um so is
that a sufficient explanation of what's
been going on? Well, not quite. remember
that Daniel was able to um partially
discover the rule after um six um uh
present 1 2 3 4 5 five presentations.
How did he do that? Because he'd never
seen some of the information necessary
to be confident that this was a rule in
play.
Yeah. At this point, I would you know,
I'm tempted to ask Daniel, but I think I
think that would be unfair. Um so I I
asked the audience I said think about
how on earth what did what did you know
if you had discovered that rule before
the uh the full 32 exposures
how did you or how what what did what
did you know that the moral didn't know
and of course the normal response um
which is completely correct is well I
knew there was a rule I knew there was
some kind of symmetry there was some
kind of constraint some lawful relation
ationship um which constrained my
hypothesis space um which meant that I
could actually rifle through different
explanations that all had a rule-like uh
structure um I may have done that
serially or I may have done that well I
don't know how I could because it's
likely that I uh I was doing this
unconsciously um but from the point of
view of um how one might simulate the
fact that you knew knew that there was a
rule.
How could one install that prior into
this kind of active inference? And the
idea is really just to focus again on
optimizing the prior optimizing the
prior via a process of structure
learning. And basically what we're
saying is that if this agent was
equipped with an a priority set of
rules, hypotheses
um uh laws um that are going to be
embodied or represented by a whole range
a whole set of different kind of
likelihood mappings or uh likelihood
tenses here different models. Then um
this puts constraints on the belief
updating and it enables the agent to
accumulate evidence for each of these
models. And when the agent is
sufficiently um confident that the one
model is the best explanation what's
going on, she can then commit to that
particular model. So this is a process
known as basin model selection. Um and
we can formalize that just by looking at
the sort of the maths of basin model
selection. Uh and the picture that
emerges is that you know we spend a lot
of time um gathering information
foraging the the environment in a way
that allows us to build up associations
and contingencies and correlations
um as parameters in our generative
model. And then the idea now is that
we're going to go back and find a
simpler model that has a greater
evidence that still complies with the
particular model by removing certain
parameters and scoring the whether the
uh the free energy bound on the model
evidence goes up or down. If I remove
something from my model, if I reduce my
model in some way uh and the evidence
goes up, that means that that model was
just contributing the complexity, not
the accuracy. So I'm fully licensed to
remove it and to reduce that model. And
furthermore, if I have a space of
hypothesis, all of which are reduced
forms of some full model, I can go
through evaluating the reduced free
energy or the reduced evidence and score
all my models in terms of how uh how
much um how likely they are in relation
to each other. And if there's a winning
one, I can pick out that and I can uh
use this bas model reduction in order to
um very quickly and efficiently says no,
this model is the best explanation for
the data I have seen. So far, of course,
this is very reminiscent of what we're
doing in sleep um in terms of synaptic
regression just by removing um redundant
parameters crucially um minimizing free
energy but in the absence of any sensory
data. So there's no accuracy at all. So
the free energy just reduces to
complexity. I minimize my complexity
just by removing um removing any um
parameters um that have a substantive
change in the free energy and that's
relatively trivial to um evaluate um
under these discrete state space models
or likelihood tenses. So what we're
saying is basically we go around with
our eyes open accumulating all sorts of
potentially um redundant associations
and then we we just think about things.
We close our eyes. we introspect offline
um just to u make sure that we and just
retain those uh parameters that are
necessary to explain the data that we've
just seen so that we can now maximize
our model evidence and then open our
eyes again uh and start uh start start
again. And when we implement that in
this agent um we can massively increase
the um the sample efficiency um through
this period of periodic introspection or
having little naps between each of the
trials which is why I was trying to give
Daniel a break but didn't actually allow
him a proper break uh to think about
things um
and um increase so increase the
efficiency with which we can build our
beliefs about the structure and the
parameterization of our generative
model. So here's the true rule. This is
what um Daniel started with after about
12 trials. This is probably what he was
representing if he didn't know that
there was a rule there. If he'd had time
or indeed did have time to a certain
extent um to now look at this uh through
the lens of all possible rules, he could
have identified this particular
combination of subtenses or uh this rule
here after the 12th observation. And
indeed um when we simulate this um um we
can show a marked reduction in the
discovery time and the associated um uh
performance that can be scored in terms
of the average confidence um and the uh
free energy bound on model evidence. Uh
this is probably the most interesting uh
kind of result. It basically shows how
long it was until the model had a na
moment. how long it was until one of its
hypotheses, one of its rules um became
substantially more likely than any other
to the extent that they could then
confidently commit to that particular
rule. Um and in some instances it can it
can actually with the right kind of
information. Um it can actually be uh
very very uh you know be done after just
three exposures. Um but you have to have
the right kind of information. Uh this
is the the top line is the first one. Um
showing that uh to be to be confident
about the best drill you you should have
been about sort of eight uh observations
which is roughly what um uh which is
roughly what gen people do uh generally
um um uh however notice the blue squares
are when people jump to the wrong
conclusion. So there is a possibility of
prematurely committing to a particular
model on the basis of what you've seen
so far, but um um it's not going to be
the best explanation for what you're
going to see in the future. So that
occasionally you get this sort of um
jumping to conclusion effect, but on
average for this particular game with
random ordering of stimuli, we're
looking at u you know the the aha moment
emerging after about five to six um
exposures which is uh exactly the same
that um Daniel um evinced when uh
getting the partial rule. The final the
final thing I just wanted to um um speak
to is the last generalization
um from
expected information gain over
parameters
to expected information gain over the
model in of itself. So this is new. This
has never been written up or um or
described anywhere. But it it it's a
natural extension that rests upon um
basin model reduction and takes us now
into the world of true epistemic
foraging as a scientist would do when
she is gathering data for or against
disambiguate between a null and altered
hypothesis but generalized to
potentially hundreds of hypotheses. So
now we're addressing the question um
let's assume we are going to do some
basis uh reduction. What's the best way
to gather data that will disambiguate,
maximize the information gain, maximally
resolve the uncertainty about this
hypothesis space? So I can remove one
set of hypotheses successively and
winnow down my hypothesis space until
the last man is standing and I can
commit to this particular explanation.
And I would submit that this is if you
like um active reasoning. It's it's sort
of actively having in mind explanations
for your world and then designing
experiments in a way that is the most
efficient in terms of resolving
uncertainty about your hypothesis. And
that just basically requires um adding
an extra term to the expected free
energy. Um that just scores the
difference between my posterior over
models uh with the outcomes relative to
without the outcomes. And when we do
that um we get sort of you know very
interesting uh behaviors um and you can
actually score or plot the posterior
probability over different models or
hypothesis. Here this is the same
paradigm but made slightly different. So
we didn't tell the agent which of the um
locations of the colored ball uh colored
balls signified um which the um the
criterion ball that was the contained
the correct color. Uh so um in this in
the game we just played that was a
center ball but the this agent didn't
know that. So it it has to acquire a lot
more information before it can commit to
a particular hypothesis. That hypothesis
um well the correct um the correct rule
is the one that we just um um
entertained which the center is read
that the left state is the correct
choice and so forth. Um that's rule
number 65. that there are 81 other rules
that all have to be um eliminated before
we before we can get to the correct
rule. And this is a process of
elimination here starting off with
rather uninformative posterior beliefs
about the particular rule or model in
play. And when we um are confident by
applying uh Okam's razor um to this
distribution of posteriors of hypotheses
or beliefs or models um we can suddenly
commit to this model and then we can
identify the true likelihood mapping um
for subsequently and basically come very
confident um in terms of what we're what
we're doing uh and perform perfectly um
under the constraints in the game uh
with a minimum divergence between the
posterior the true uh true likelihoods.
Um just for those people who are
interested um it's interesting to think
about well how much does this um
expected information gain over models
contribute to the expected information
gain over other things and how do they
interact with each other and and just to
speak to that it's um what we've done
here is to simulate that game again um
but using all the different kinds of um
components of the expected free energy
the expected information gainer over
models states
um parameters and states and the
expected value which in this instance we
can be ignored. Um and then remove the
various sources of or kinds of expected
information gained to see what would
happen. And interestingly what happens
if we remove this um this scientific or
um um information gain over hypothesis
or models. um we can still do quite a
lot lot of um resolving uncertainty
about um models just by um resolving
uncertainty about the parameters that
constitute those models. But we have
real difficulties when it comes to two
equally plausible explanations because
um this agent is actually deliberately
sampling the world in order to maximally
disambiguate between the two uh the two
last hypotheses. And when we remove
everything we we we we still there is
information there but it can take a very
long time before we actually commit to
any particular hypothesis. So in summary
um uncertainty can be you know thought
of in terms of expected surprise namely
entropy um and we can think of different
sources of uncertainty and their
resolution in the following way that
latent states parameters and structure
all um offer different sources of
uncertainty that can be resolved through
free energy minimizing processes of
inference learning and selection of
different kinds uh leading to um uh one
way of reading artic artificial
curiosity in terms of succumbing to or
finding affordances that can be
described as salience, novelty and uh
knowledge. Um and just to reiterate the
importance of sleep. Um in the words of
Einstein, the merely reflexive act of
inference is just basically appealing to
the best explanations for the world. Put
very simply, everything should be made
as simple as possible but not simpler.
Um when we move to um playing as
inference and the importance of expected
information gain that is constrained by
expected value. Uh the important thing
is to not stop is to not to stop
questioning. Curiosity has its own
reason for existing. And on this
analysis, you probably invert that that
if you exist, you have to be curious in
the special condition that you don't
have direct access to your own actions
upon the world. And with that, it just
remains for me to thank those people
whose ideas I've been talking about and
of course to thank you for your
attention. Thank you very much.
>> Thank you, Carl. Awesome.
All right.
Great.
I will now pass to Michael Garfield who
will facilitate this next section. There
will be some roundt discussion and thank
you Michael. Take it away.
Yeah, wonderful.
Uh that was a bracing
way to wake up immediately jump into
your lecture and and uh begin one's day.
Um,
I guess the first question I have for
you and then I I think this touches
directly on Hungju's work and uh I would
love to solicit input from other people
on this as well, but Carl, let's let's
have you go first
has to do with the
surprise
of advanced meditators or psychonauts
in and you know non-ordinary states of
consciousness and like the the the loss
of the distinction between self and
other
and um
there's a what Eric Davis calls a kind
of a metabolic ontology
that um there's a threshold
beyond which the uh these like diatic
distinctions no longer uh seem to
pertain. pain and you end up with like a
kind of co-imcation of self and
environment
or a uh like an n-dimensional
figuration of of these relationships.
So, I'm I'm I'm curious to hear folks on
this panel wax on
uh phenomenology
of non-ordinary
self- other relationships
in the in light of this framing that you
just laid out for us.
I I'll start that because I'm the
oldest. Um and
I I get the impression it's very early
in the morning for you. So So I'm
assuming you're in California, which of
course
>> Santa Fe. Yeah,
>> Santa Fe.
Okay, that's still that's still about
sort of 11 hours I thought 8 hours. Uh
so it must be very early in the morning.
My apologies for that. For me, it's
getting getting into mid-after
afternoon. uh in relation to your
question and I'll try and set up the the
the other uh panelists for this um a
very sort of uh technical view of this.
I guess what you're talking about is
sort of non-dual states the the
distinction between self and others
certainly the the narrative self or
indeed the sort of sematic self just
disappears. Um I think that that again
I'm answering you know if I had to
simulate this how would I sim what kind
of generative model would I have to put
in play in order to plausibly simulate
this kind of phenomenology and the first
thing that I would have to do is to
actually write down a generative model
that actually had a distinction between
self and non-self um and um or self in
different uh in different contexts. So
uh that would be quite a sophisticated
generative model, very expressive
generative model that naturally now have
discovered the rule or the hypothesis
that it is actually an entity and that
many things can be explained by this
particular entity that is me being in
one of a small number of states sort of
carving subjective selfhood into into um
some plausible set of states that can
now very efficiently recognize I'm in
this state and therefore should attend
to this and should attend to that and
then what I would do to dissolve um that
confident commitment I am in this state
and and implicitly I am me um would be
to look at those situations under which
there's a loss of um precision over the
self other or self in other contexts um
distribution how would I do that well
operationally that would require um
decreasing this deep precision at um via
increasing the precision of lower level
processing. Um what would that look
like? Well, it would look like I was
attending to something that was um um
closer to the sensorium. Um so you you
you you you could sort of say this was
some aspect of meditation for example
that you know I am deliberately
attending to assigning much greater
precision to the um to you know to the
sensorium um possibly a very limited
part of the sensorium and that
implicitly dissolves any conviction it
doesn't I don't need to explain the
world now in terms of I cause this and I
cause that there is no need for any
highness uh uh you know it it is not
necessary in this particular instance
simply because I I've been able to and
of course we aren't generally able to do
this but if you become a skilled
practitioner doing this some people can
um you know redeploy
their precision their entropy their
their um their attention however you
want to articulate this away from this
very high level self kind of model of
minimal selfhood at least that would be
my That's how I would approach this.
>> Oops. Now I'm unmuted. All right. Sure.
Thanks. Um, thank you. Thank you for
inviting me in this panel talk is really
great honor. um before. So um well I
would say from you know from a more I
would say phnological perspective
phenomenologistish
perspective I would say um so it is also
important to distinguish
uh intentional intentional uh quality
versus intentional the entity the was it
the um
so if say conscious conscious uh
conscious lana or qualia the qualia uh
comes to to me like if we if I am
observing a red apple then red apple can
be also the qualia but but in the but in
terms of perspective or the orientation
subjective orientation that if I would
like like um be be um open to um
approach I would say open to approach to
the redness of the of the apple or am I
close to like am I deliberately
uh thinking that red apple is something
bad or something something um harmful to
to um my individual. Um so so those that
kind of uh that kind of was it uh um
type of I would say type of
consciousness is well the questions are
referred in general as intentional
quality and um I would say much the
easier easier way to describe this would
be um having certain perspective toward
some some kind of matter some kind of um
conscious matter. So um I would say also
modeling not just only the red apple the
redness of the apple and the roundness
of apple but also what uh what what
exact perspective does the um an
individual
is oriented oriented toward um having
having which which perspective is very
important I would say when we try to
model the consciousness
and um in terms of in terms of how so
how can the active inference framework
can uh can play in in terms of modeling
this perspective I would say um let's
start from
uh let's start from the very uh very
basics of
let's say um free energy principle the
the physics principle
um that the individual
uh individual turns out to have certain
certain kind of veilance or certain kind
kind of feeling or orientation towards
the uh toward the certain OB objects and
that also
might be uh might be self-organized
within the within the um agent uh within
the agent or conscious being. Um so what
I would suggest would be um if we can if
we can deliver this perspective system
as something um something in in the
active emperence model uh something that
um makes makes the agent to infer or um
so as a as a different inference layer
um or
so Sorry. Um as a as a inference
different inference layer different
dimension of inference layer that is uh
that can be uh uh described in as
a um a certain form of information I
would say. Um
so that would be one uh one meaningful
path that we could model the perspective
structure or the consciousness
certain parts of consciousness. I would
say
Adam and Alex. I don't know if either of
you want to
Alex seems to be getting the
the ball from Adam here. Uh well, my
computer crashed in the middle of this,
so I think I'm not 100% sure what we're
talking about. Hi, Carl. Uh so uh I'm
not exactly sure what we're discussing.
I think I got a little bit of what
Hungju was saying, but uh maybe remind
me of the prompt. Yeah, the the the
prompt has to do with uh like this like
the self as
a uh something that is is not
necessarily persistent
in
you know it's an output of inference and
there there are you know uh many well
doumented
states in which
self other relationships are not
uh
in which we have a different syntax
you know where like non-dual
consciousness being one of them
uh
how do we you know how do we think about
all of that within an active inference
framework
>> so are you saying the output of
inference is oneself just to make sure I
got it
>> yeah it was a Yeah. It's like that the
idea of like a like there being a a self
other relationship.
>> Uhhuh.
>> Is it
>> with other as in like other entities
outside of like outside blanket? Right.
>> Okay.
>> Well, this might not be the most
appropriate answer, but I I tend to
think of it as maybe a different
direction. So, this is something Carl
didn't also mention in his talk. Uh, but
he and I have worked on this concept. So
another corollary of the free energy
principle is mortal computation. Um and
you and I have written at length about
that. Uh the audience can just type
Google and it'll come up. And um so then
that's a little bit about talking about
embodiment and inactivism and
embeddedness and extended theory of
mind. And then Carl and added a fifth E
to the five four E cognitive theory. So
it's 5E cognitive theory elementary or
basil cognition in reference to our
friend Michael 11. Um, and so like these
this like a whole framework for
discussing like sentience. Uh, I I tend
to avoid discussions of consciousness a
little bit. Carl is far more braver and
more equipped to address these things.
So I usually stay away from that. I like
to look at like a low level. But when
you say the self, um, I think at least I
haven't thought of active inference is
outputting something. It's rather active
inference is like a a reference to like
the dynamics and mechanics of something
that is embodied. So you need to talk
about like a substrate and so we need to
talk about well what platform are we
building on like is it a robot and that
is the self. So we have kind of this
like entity and again it could be like
nested markoff blankets and we could
talk about lots of jargon but the idea
is that you have some kind of object and
it's uh its primary directive is it
doesn't want to die or rather it is
trying to preserve its non-equilibrium
steady state its nest um because it
doesn't want to disintegrate in its heat
bath. So the whole point is it like
moves through uh the universe and trying
to collect resources. It does the
epistemic foraging that active inference
is all about uh because again that's
critical to maintaining its nest. That's
it's prime directive. Um and so like the
self the identity you have to like touch
on the notion of embodiment and you need
to have like a body to talk about and so
active inference is performed within the
context of that body again can be
described as a marov blanket and so that
is the self I mean of course it can be
destroyed it can disappear uh if of
course it fails to maintain its nez um
but the idea is like that's how I think
of the self and then you can use the
idea that that's the immortal computer I
underneath all of this is the FEP is
saying we're all mortal computers and we
live in a collective of mortal computers
and so that's the other right so there's
other mortal computers so I think I kind
of touch on that and that's kind of the
way I think of it rather the self is
kind of like inherent to the fact we
have to start talking about an entity a
substrate something physical and we also
need an environment of course because
activism is critical so you need some
way to describe the body it's
interactions. It's thermodynamic
coupling to some niche. Uh and then of
course we need other other bodies that
also interact with that niche and
interact with that body. Uh and then of
course you get embeddedness which is
then how you get society and culture.
And then we can start working our way up
the the big hierarchies that Carl often
likes to talk about. Not to speak about
you when you're here but as we work up
to bigger and bigger self-organizing
systems. So that's my perspective. I
might be misunderstanding, but that's
how I see self is it's kind of like,
well, you got to be able to talk about
now a platform, a substrate, a body,
whatever it is. It could be E.coli. Uh,
and that could be fine. That's a a
wonderful example of the most element,
one of the more simpler mortal
computers. So, it rather than an output.
So, I don't know if maybe I
misunderstood, but that's how I think of
it. And so, I kind of like to touch on
that is sentience. I don't know about
the consciousness part. I very careful
with that. So,
>> Sure. Sure. Sure. I I I I think that uh
you know just to qualify that uh a lot
of meditative traditions
see uh like laughter as like a
an observation of surprise at realizing
that
you one is not other than
uh figures into this that I I'm Adam, I
want to hear you speak to this.
the part about laughter in particular or
>> well no just
broadly
>> um well what just came to mind with the
part about um laughter also would be um
some of the work Carl's done with um
artificial curiosity and insight and
some of um Schmidt Hoover's uh uh
framings of uh humor in terms of like
rapid compression of um uh sudden uh
I guess a sudden arrival at an
increasingly elegant models. But um in
terms of I guess what's come up is um I
was uh wondering about um in the process
of um self-evidencing
whether the most robust self-evidencing
involves um having a certain porousness
to the self. Uh there's um uh some work
that's been uh called under uh different
names such as uh psychotic mark
psychotic marov blankets or like you can
have marov blankets that that aren't
well tuned enough that might be like
overly rigid and um they don't um uh
adjust to the multiscale competences
they ought to be a part of um and the
co-construct
niches well and they can become like um
pathological or um maybe like
parasitical or like or cancerous in
their in their nature. So any but the uh
uh guess the thing I'm thinking of is um
uh the the importance of maintaining
metastability
uh or or for um ongoing I guess um uh
chaotic uh itinerency or ability to
adapt or evolve like uh if if in the in
the process of uh preserving the self in
a given form
The best way to do that would be have a
grip that's not too tight or not too
loose um on the self. So those are some
things that came to mind. I don't know
if that's made any sense whatsoever,
but I I put some uh uh some of the
thoughts in the chat and some papers. Um
uh there's a interesting one by um my
friend um Goku um um how higher goals
are construct and collapse under stress
where he'll actually talk about how
systems um uh uh when they they're put
under allic load they can basically um
their clarical structure can unravel a
bit as like the deeper um
nodes or predictions the ones related to
things like self and world um uh
potentially become overloaded and
destabilized and this having a certain
adaptive function. So
those are things that came to mind when
uh from from your prompt. But
>> all right. Yeah. I had another question
on uh
this this Carl's
talking about sleep and scaling. You
know, I was I was uh just watching a
a stream of octopus documentaries
talking about the the development of the
octopus brain and how rapidly these
animals have to grow and learn and and
uh how therefore so much of their life
is spent in sleep.
And uh I'm trying to like think about
that in terms of um like
what we have going on with uh AI
which you know by contrast seems to uh
you know we we don't we don't have uh
at least in any way that we think about
it like a like a dreaming like a sleeper
dreaming
for the models that that we're put that
we're using in AI systems. Although I I
have seen some research sort of
simulated
dreaming in in an an effort to like uh
create geospatial
world models in in AI. Um,
so I'm curious about like the
relationship between these things and
and uh how
uh energy inefficient
our AI systems are
and uh the possibility that like
human input might be able to function as
a sort of proxy of of dreaming
or sleep in AI systems. Um, that's a big
kind of wide ambit question, but I'll
kick it off there that like, you know,
how how do we how do we let the machines
sleep and dream?
Um, you know, what what might that look
like technically? Uh, what role does uh?
>> Yeah, I'll just I'll stop there, Carl.
>> No, that's a great question. I' I've
been making notes about sort of key
words that people have brought to the
table which I think sort of deserve
deserve a little bit of a comment.
That's just picking up on um that
particular question. Um
it is interesting that um from the point
of view of people like Jeffrey Hinton um
building the Helmhill's machine um sleep
played a really important part um and if
you go back and Google the weak the wake
sleep algorithm um you'll see the first
forerunners of the kind of mortal
computation that Alex was talking about.
And interestingly, what this basically
entails is that you're um you're
basically building machine that can
learn to infer. And the way that you do
it is you expose it to data um and then
you learn the parameters of um a neural
network that maps to posterior beliefs.
And then you let it sleep. You take away
the data and you let it have a little
little period to sleep. And during the
sleep you actually generate from the
learned representations
ficted data dreaming data and that
allows you now to learn the parameters
of the mapping from the latent
representations of the latent causes to
the actual content or the outcome. So
this is very very similar to um in fact
almost isomeorphic to the original
introduction the free energy principle
that was cast really in terms of
learning to infer um but um the ultimate
objective is an inference machine
exactly along the lines of the helm
machine or or um you know the way that I
introduced the sort of helm hulks in
perspective. So I think your notion that
you know sleep um
is is important is absolutely right. It
was there at the foundation of all um
certainly the the useful um um
engineering endeavors in machine
learning and artificial intelligence
research. It's lost its way a little bit
with uh current transformer
architectures and um um uh DRL um um
however I think it's coming back again
in one sort of um muted sense. If you
just look at the um what reasoning means
in the generative AI literature,
reasoning means trying to suppress
hallucinations which you could call a
kind of dreaming um but it's all mind
reading that the user could actually see
but trying to resolve um um mistakes or
you know false predictions or you know
implausible predictions um by um
recursively
um um you know in the background um
generating its prompts and or multiple
prompts and then selecting. So reasoning
as read in the generative AI literature
which has nothing to do with reasoning
in the vernacular or cognitive science
or indeed in what I was talking about uh
or indeed in terms of probabistic um uh
induction uh you know logical induction
of the kind that Josh Tenbar might be uh
you know might be interested in. Uh but
reasoning in this particular popular
literature in machine learning um large
language model literature does actually
uh come back to this notion of just
taking you know stopping worrying about
the content and then just turning things
over in your mind which has some
similarity to the kind of um um um basic
model comparison and uh uh and and
reduction that um was um in my
presentation. So I think that yeah it's
a really important thing to think about
and you know again I come back to the
fact that you're you should be asleep
now if you're in California. So I'm
sorry about that sleep's really
important. Uh but can I just comment
upon some of the really just very
quickly on on some words that were came
up dur during during the panel
discussion which I think um would be
really usefully formalized within an
active inference uh setting. So I I'm
thinking about you know um initially
we're talking about veilance. Uh I think
veence is really important. Um so the
most technical and simplest explanation
of veilance I think would be come under
the rubric of a effective inference and
in this very simple view veilance just
is the precision or it's the negative
uncertainty. So things are negatively
veanced when you're uncertain
specifically when you're uncertain about
what to do and that's sometimes
associated with anxiety um sometimes in
a biological context uh stress uh and
chron and chronic stress. So just
knowing not knowing what to do because
you've got a very low precision belief
belief over your policies uh can be read
as and of course you have to recognize
that and now you have if you like a
generative model that can recognize oh I
am uh in a state of imprecision uh
pertaining to my policies and therefore
I must feel bad. um uh and you can now
um sort of unpack the implications and
the virtual and or possibly vicious
circles in terms of interacting with the
world. Um that um that I think um is one
part of the story. It's not emotional
inference though and I'm now speaking to
Alex's focus on mortal computation. Of
course, as soon as you talk about mortal
computation and things like you and me,
you now have to move to intraceptive
inference that the actual body matters.
So the vastness the the biggest sensory
organ I have is my body. Uh and I have
to make sense of my body. Uh and you
know I have to infer the state of my
body. And of course as soon as you do
that you've got some sort of minimal
kind of selfmodeling inferring my state
of self because I have to insta infer it
could be completely pre subconscious or
subpersonal you know in the sense of
homeostasis. But when we move to
allostasis then I think that the lines
get a bit you know
the lines are not so distinct and you
could argue that that intraception in
the spirit of mortal computation has to
be an aspect of emotional inference and
of course only you can own an emotion.
So I think that's important. Um I've
also got down here self versus other. Um
you know I think that's a really
important observation. So there's a
whole other argument uh which actually
came under Adam's nod to co-construction
of our niches. Um so one thing if we
co-construct a niche together is that we
our world now becomes populated by other
things like us which suddenly calls upon
generative models to disambiguate did I
cause that or did you cause that because
we are co-constructing and that may be
if you like a really simple-minded
explanation as to why we need a notion
of self simply to disambiguate between
self or the consequences of the action
of self versus other and of course
that's a you know a deep issue when it
comes to um attachment theory or
mergence of theory of mind, you know, in
a developmental context for the baby to
recognize that it's a self and it may
actually have to first recognize that
the mother is an autonomous self and
then recognize perhaps I am similar to
mom and therefore perhaps I'm a thing as
well and suddenly you get this this this
sort of distinction between self and
other. So I just wanted to really
endorse that that point uh I think that
Michael was making that you know the the
other hood uh is probably more important
for selfhood than anything else. You
don't need it uh if you didn't actually
co-construct your niches. Um the
dimension um the the dimensionality in
terms of quality of experience and
quailia um that you'll be searching for
in um active inference schemes formally
I would read as the order. So first
order inference is basically inferring
the content of what's going on. Second
order inference is inferring the
uncertainty or the precision of that. So
it's not about the content but it's the
precision you're inferring. As a
psychologist you would read that as
attention for example. Um and I think
that that the um some people would argue
to have a qualitative experience you
have to have some um agentic control
over the attention to the redness of the
apple. um which just means you've now
got to have a sort of deep generative
model of a particular kind where um the
depth is not now in terms of the sort of
composition of content but the uh the
depth in terms of parameterizing the
quality of your beliefs about the
content. Sometimes you can describe this
as sort of metacognitive aspect. So I
think that that that that would be a
really interesting line of inquiry to
explain and people do explain this um
you know the distinction say between
something that's normally transparent
and opaque uh being defined by the
ability to mentally act upon that
representation on the inside through
affording it greater or lesser precision
but of course to do that you have to
have a representation that I want to
afford this to. So again it it induces a
dependency on on self-representation and
there are all sorts of um ways that you
you know one can impact that in terms of
I repeat phenomenal transparency and
mental action. So I just wanted to say
all of all of those perspectives I think
speak to really exciting opportunities
to formalize them in terms of relative
straightforward generative models but
perhaps not too straightforward because
they do involve sort of higher order
aspects of of of of inference that uh
that we are particularly skilled at
skilled at solving. So then I want to
add to Carl if you don't mind I want to
extend because Carl brought up really
interesting the Helmholtz machine and
the wake sleep algorithm. Uh we also you
were to Michael's point about generative
models like again that's been around the
dreaming concept like Boltzman machines
also used to be called by Terry
Sajjinowski and Jeff uh harmoniums uh
the idea with that learning like wake
sleep got generalized to contrastive
divergence. Another way that dreaming
kind of looked like was you have what
Carl was mentioning like data dependent
inference and then you had uh
independent or let's say decoupled kind
of like exploring trajectories that are
confabulations as Jeff would call them
and then you kind of like push them away
uh from what's reality which is data
driven. So that's kind of been I just
kind of wanted to highlight that sleep
has kind of been at least through the
view of like oh we have negative and
positive data and then today another
kind of branch of research that I think
dreaming has sort of kind of lived uh is
in that contrastive paradigm we see a
lot of self-supervised learning in the
neuroai machine learning communities um
and again that's kind of like pushing
away outofdistribution data from
indistribution data uh and again I Carl
and I have also done some of that too
with like meta representational
predictive coding. Um so I kind of and I
think the dreaming another way that it
kind of lives on is in the concept of
catastrophic forgetting. Uh because no
matter how much transformers are
heralded as wonderful and the solution
to everything uh they still forget. Deep
neural networks have not really address
this issue. Uh and so uh you can see
even like predictive coding literature
from my groups like my own and others
where you use like the generative model
that's being learned in this
neurosircuitry. You sample from it and
then you kind of use that as a a refresh
mechanism to try to improve your longer
term memory. And that could be viewed as
like a dreaming state or little uh let's
say daydreaming phases. Uh and that goes
back to also classical literature like
Robert French and those that tried to
work on catastrophic forgetting like the
80s and the '9s. Uh in another place too
I just want to highlight is let's not
forget that active inference which
shares a lot of connections to
reinforcement learning we have
experience replay which is again another
way where we kind of replay a lot of
data in a buffer um and trying to kind
of uh improve the learning mechanism of
a policy uh so we that kind of mimics
episodic memory kind of sort of so
that's another place where I think it it
lives so I just wanted to highlight that
and then to you asked Michael very brief
briefly you snuck in there about like
energy efficient AI and how energy
efficient it is. Obviously it is
completely opposite of what we want.
Transformers are again Carl and I have
argued this they have carbon footprints
of literally cities uh to run a you know
chat GBT and LLM. So I think like to get
to that energy efficiency that we want
and I think also Carl highlighted in his
uh mention of interosceptive inference
uh I think the answers again we go back
to the idea of a body uh you need an
embodiment system they need a mortal
substrate uh and then I think that kind
of begins to answer where dreaming uh
and this consolidation of information
that again Carl mentioned in his talk
which is the structural selection. I
think you need a body because then it
kind of motivates things like rest. Uh
because again if your body is fatiguing
and you need to kind of go into a state
of like oh I need to repair because you
guys have mentioned we've mentioned
homeostasis you guys have mentioned
alostasis we should not me forget
autopsis uh the idea that we also need
to repair and construct and deal with
damage and so I think that that's where
you need a motivation for the dream
state and the rest state. And I think
that that's where the body sort of
answers it because again that comes from
the interceptive inference. I need to
understand my own internal states and
then I am driven to preserve them and
again go back to our directive. So I
think that's where dreaming the future
of dreaming comes into play because I
think with a body and its own
limitations and its own needs and
requirements and then how you interact
with the niche to get those resources uh
motivates things like rest repair uh and
again so we and not to keep saying the
same thing but Carl and I highlighted
all the levels right you have to start
with like horioesis or homeostasis
allostasis on top of that you need to
you need to describe autopsis
you kind of need to go all the way. You
have to explain all the levels to build
like a complete mortal computer that you
know is again an embodiment of the free
energy principle. And I think then that
starts to motivate things like why you
would dream. Uh and so I think that's
kind of where the future might lie even
though we see it embedded like you know
Carl and I pointed out some examples uh
where dreaming is kind of used as a
mechanism to repair learning uh or to
for example learn to contrast
confabulations from real world data. So
it's just like a little thing I wanted
to make a comment or long comment on.
And then if I'd I'll just add quickly I
know we don't have too much a question
for Carl. just wanted to ask him based
on the talk and he mentions like a bunch
of these different things about active
inference and I love the formulation but
something that he knows that I'm
obsessed with is the role and Carl you
mentioned neuroai neurobiological
learning and I know from your group and
a lot of those that work on it back
propagation of errors is used often to
train the deep neural network forms of
active inference or you do things like
probabilistic graphical models that are
discreet which are kind of hard to scale
up to very big systems. What do you
think is the role of getting the
learning rules right like Hebian
plasticity and you know because again
predictive coding has local learning
rules uh I often see like my group tries
to show you how you can do active
inference with that but I don't see a
lot of that what do you think is the
role and the importance of getting that
right that neuratomical description like
synaptic plasticity correct and not
using like the chain rule of calculus
which is convenient but isn't really
what our brains are doing I mean the
neuroscience still has not confirm that
we are just a chain rule system back
propagating along the same synapses that
we do forward transmission. So curious
to know your thoughts on the role of
that if you don't mind commenting if we
have some time Daniel
do we have time now? Yeah, go for it,
Carl. And then any last comments from
others?
>> Right. I very Yeah, really excellent
point. Excellent. I think at two levels
just that sort of um the importance of
mortal computation for the way that our
tech industry is developing and the
impact upon our lived world. I think
that's a really important uh
consideration which speaks to you know
quite substantive issues uh in the way
that we deal with big tech and the
direction of travel in machine learning
research and investment and building
power stations in Virginia for example.
Um uh so you know much of the motivation
for biometric or neuromorphic uh mortal
computation um inherits from that and
from the the the physics of information
uh sometimes cast in terms of say
thermodynamic computing if you like but
also the importance of neuromorphic. So
that's I think a really important issue
beyond academia. Um the second issue is
a specific question about the particular
algorithms that are used and and when
they diverge from a neuromorphic or um
um biometic um principle or when they
diverge from the principles of least
action um evidenced in biological and
real world self-organization you know
that's trouble ahead um and one example
of that is back propagation of errors
and of course the whole point of the
freeji principle is it is a local free
is
you're an extensive property which means
if you minimize it here and just here
you're minimizing it everywhere if
you're repeating that local um update
road. So in answer to your specific
question about the update rules I think
they're vitally important um is there a
right one or a wrong one? I according to
the complete class theorem no um there
isn't. What you would say is what is the
implicit generative model that explains
this particular functional form for for
the uh um the um belief update uh rule
for the parameters or the learning rule
in machine learning talk. So there will
be a generative model implicit in the
functional form of your learning rule.
Um and that has to have the form exactly
of that hamph
decomposition. So there has to be a sort
of a solenoidal term. There has to be,
you know, an update an update term and
and a prediction term in it. Um there's
also going to be some sort of volatility
terms. There's going to be a decay term
in it. Um so um but the key point is it
has to be local because we know that the
paths of least action um are defined by
action which is a time integral of an
energy potential and that enab potential
is an extensive function. So it has to
be local. So you know from the start
that back propagation of errors is not
the right way to do it. Um that would be
my brief answer to to your question.
Thanks Carl. Appreciate it.
>> All the panelists now have to to say
something very wise in their concluding
comments. I think that's that's the
pressure upon you now.
>> Yeah. any short closing comments and
then we'll go to the next session.
>> Well then I'll just knock myself out
quickly. Uh thank you Carl for again
answering my question. I mean I
obviously have argued for like a better
part of a decade that back prop is not
the right way to go. So uh and uh I
think again through the passive lease
action that kind of motivates why we
should care about like local biological
plasticity as kind of our guiding way of
designing for example predictive coding
active inference systems. So uh maybe to
try to say something wise in the spirit
of what you were just saying to the
audience I think that uh yeah we should
probably if you are interested in this
like idea of neuroi Carl and I call it
biomimetic intelligence uh but they're
all kind of the same thing I think then
we should be pu making a bigger push uh
towards biological plausible forms of
learning and rules uh and I think that
that's kind of a key idea and then just
remember that when you're constructing
these As Carl has aptly pointed out,
there is like an implicit generative
model. Uh what you might not be able to
do with an implicit generative model,
I'll just briefly comment, is you might
not be easily able to sample from it.
Sometimes it's better to have the
explicit model. Uh but again, uh it's
kind of like a trade-off in what kind of
scientific question you want to answer
and what type of model you want to
build. So, uh, yeah, that's my minor
comment, but I do think that there
should be a lot a bigger push, uh,
towards, uh, biologically plausible
credit assignment learning, uh, in
support of things like an active
inference framework. And so maybe that's
a call to the community to the active
inference symposium. I know my students
who will be presenting later uh, these
coming days and today, they know that
role, but I think more people need to do
it. So, we need a bigger push for that,
but maybe that's over like the next 10
years or so. So, thanks for that.
Does anyone else
>> You'll have to hand the baton by calling
upon the
>> Okay. Okay. Then I'll give it to uh
Michael since it looked like you uh
opened up your mic. Your turn. Say
something wise in in the spirit.
>> I have no wisdom here.
I'll just say that uh
this has been a a delight. I think you
know it's it has prompted me to think
about
the the way that uh like why is it that
the production of
v like deep fake video has become so
prominent for both open AI and for meta
in their in you know public facing
products
and that it may that that like
the insane uh finance like economics of
these organizations
is actually like leveraging humans
trying to
like uh dissipate
out into
like all of the possible
fantasy worlds that we can imagine. and
with these tools and and that that's
somehow going to like hold this thing
up. I mean, I'm sitt sitting here
thinking about the AI bubble that we're
in right now. And uh whether whether
it's a bubble that's going to pop or
whether whether it's actually like a a
cell membrane now being held together by
all of this this sort of uh collective
fantasy.
I'll leave it there.
>> All right. Thank you everyone.
We will be back soon.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Good talking to you,
Carl.
All right, welcome back. This next
session is going to be facilitated by
Ian Tennant. So Ian to you and
you have an hour and 15 minutes. So
thank you. Go for it.
Wait, I don't hear your audio. Yeah.
All right. Apologies for that delay
there.
Um,
all right. The next video that is going
to be played, sorry for the
little bit of scheduling changes. This
is Bradley Alisia, neurosimulation of
spatial intelligence. It's going to be a
63minute recorded video.
Hello, my name is Bradley Alisa and I'll
be presenting today on the
interdisciplinary underpinnings of the
neurosimulation of spatial intelligence.
Uh this work is in conjunction with the
orthogonal research and education lab
and particularly our cybernetic interest
group.
So an overview of where we'll be going
today. Uh this is I'm going to sketch
out a route to the neuros simulation of
spatial intelligence. So we haven't done
anything
uh in detail but this is just a route to
getting there. Uh the first and and a
lot of these different topics are kind
of related and so I have this nested
diagram. The first thing we'll talk
about is vertebrate neuro anatomy. So
thinking about the origins and coralates
of spatial cognition and vertebrates.
The next is ecological psychology and
biocybernetics. So thinking about the
brain as this sort of ecological
ecologically influenced structure uh but
also thinking about it as a circuit in
terms of how biocyroneticists would
think about the brain.
The next is uh path integration and
taxis. So we'll talk a little bit about
path integration or root finding and
then taxis which are movements towards
different stimuli and movements among
gradients and how those generate
intelligent behavior.
The fourth area is neuroethology. So
we'll talk a little bit about
neuroethology and how the brain
interacts with sensory modalities to
produce uh spatial cognition. And then
finally we'll talk about embodiment in
GS slam. So embodiment of course is very
important for any sort of model of
intelligence as well as this notion of
GS slam which engineers use to build
control systems that are spatially
embedded in embodied models. So when we
talk about neurosimulation we're talking
about simulating the conditions of
behavioral outputs. And so the neuro
component refers to development,
embodiment, sensory world, amplification
and evolution.
Development often is associated with
generativity, amplification with
something called good regulation and
evolution is roughly corresponding to
shared derived traits. The simulation
part then replicates components of a
system under plausible conditions. So to
take all the aspects of the neuro and
then simulate it in different ways. So
developmental neurosimulation which is
something our group has worked on is
simulating the construction and
expansion of the embodied nervous
system. It allows us to ask what could
happen in terms of morphology and
behavior. From our work we might aim to
model something like simple connetos
self assembled and an embodied context.
So our first stop is to consider the
vertebrate neuroanatomical view. So
spatial navigation in vertebrates is
typically thought of as a learning
memory and representational phenomena
based on a process of consolidating
episodic memory. And so in mammals
specifically, but in other vertebrates
as well, spatially explicit behaviors
have been tied to place in grid cells in
the inter rhinal cortex, which is mammal
specific and their analogous structures
in other vertebrates, but which provide
a geometric representation or an
abstract map of alocentric space that
space outside of the body frame. So if
you go back to 2014, the Nobel Prize in
physiology and medicine was awarded for
the brain's navigational place and grid
cell system. And this was awarded to two
groups. Uh one headed by Dr. John M.
O'Keefe and the other headed by doctors
Mabbrit and Edward I Moser for their
discoveries of nerve cells in the brain
that enable a sense of place and
navigation. So you see the difference
between play cells and grid cells. Grid
cells set up sort of a coordinate system
where you can have these periodic
episodes take place and then play cells
represent specific discrete objects in
the environment. These are the two
papers that we'll be talking about here.
The hippocampus is a cognitive map which
is actually a book and then the Moser's
grid cell and cortical representation.
So the cognitive map is a system which
generates an absolute reference of
ukitian space and it's located in the
hippocampus. This is from John O'Keefe's
work and so it's kind of thinking about
spatial cognition being located in a
cognitive map. This approach was based
on years of neuroanatomical
investigation. So before the the late
'7s there were a lot of lesions studies,
behavioral experiments and neuroiming
that had been done that had basically
been confirmed by Ke's team's work. So
this work hypothesized place and
misplace cells. So place cells are
information about the environment and
misplaced cells are displacement and
exploration of the environment. So you
have two different cell types and
they're working together in the same
network to predict spatial locations and
drive spatial behavior.
Now of course we can look across
uh m we can look across vertebrates to
see how diverse the hippocampus is. So
the hippocampus is actually a homologous
structure across
uh vertebrates and you see this in
humans of course uh which is in D down
at the upper right hand side of the
slide. You also see it in opossums uh
and that's of course also a mammal. Then
teu lizards and petrois uh pet promis
which is a fish. And you see those they
look a little bit more they look a
little bit different than the
hippocampus that you see in the human
opossum cate
an analogous function. And so we can
predict that there's a basal capability
for hippocample spatial processing. And
this is like sort of the acquisition of
it in the hip in the last common
ancestor that had a hippocampus.
And so we'll talk about two more papers.
So the reason I showed you the fogyny is
because we're going to be talking about
the zebra fish to see and then talking
about maze studies which you can uh
investigate from rodents which is this
paper that's cited here to fishes. One
thing we can learn from the zebra fish
larvae is that place cell analoges are
found in the fish toenphylon. And this
is showing how player come online in
laral development. Place cells in the
fish and toenphilin are enriched in
telenphalic development which happens
during this laral period and it forms a
spatial population code in the adult. So
here we have these play cells that are
sort of forming uh in the uh early you
know it we see like learning in the
telenphylon during this laral
development and they go on to form the
spatial population code which we see we
also have these maze learning paradigms.
So one of the things we want to work
think about is we want to think about
embodiment and how organisms with bodies
kind of explore their space. So it's not
just with the brain but space. And so
there are these maze learning paradigms
where learning utilizes place
information and builds a representation
of space. And we'll talk later about how
space itself is represented through a
sensory information.
Um but you know then we have to think
about how spatial navigation and
learning is is is acquired and is it
generally learned this way. So we might
actually use these maze learning
paradigms to train an agent or to train
an animal and that gives us interesting
results. But in a naturalistic context,
these mazes may be just kind of an
artificial thing. And so the learning
that we acquire might be an artifact of
that. So what do you do if you do not
have a hippocampus? So a whole lot of
non-vertebrate animals where single
cells conduct spatial navigation but
they don't have a hippocampus and they
don't have that kind of a learning
structure. So what other anatomical
mechanisms and functions are involved in
spatial navigation? If we're interested
in the simulation part and even in the
neuro part we want to know if there are
other mechanisms that are plausible.
So this brings us to the ecological
psychology and biocybernetics view. And
in this part of the talk, we're going to
look at this paper common and specific
activation supporting optic flow
processing and navigation in neuroiming
studies. And so we find that functional
segregation between optic flow
processing which is in the dorsal
pathway which sometimes is called the
what visual pathway
is separate from spatial navigation
which occurs in the vententral visual
pathway or the wear pathway. So we have
optic flow processing and spatial
navigation happening in the visual
system and those are two they're
basically the visual system is providing
information of those two types of
information to the hippocampus or to
other spatial processing centers. And so
uh one thing from the optic flow
literature that's interesting is this
idea of flow parsing mechanisms. and
flow parsing mechanisms or have been
identified that extract object motion
from middle temporal units in primates.
So there's this spatial uh processing
mechanism that is uh used to extract
object motion from visual information
and this allows us to parse naturalistic
flows. Uh spatial spatially tuned units
identify both object borders and
relative or egocentric motion. So you
have a lot of at least you have at least
two mechanisms within the visual system
that allow us to sort of parse
information relevant to spatial
cognition.
And then of course we also have optic
flow and alocentric navigation.
And this is also another thing that
happens to visual information to extract
the spatially explicit information that
can drive spatial navigation.
And so if we look at a primate ccentric
model, remember this is just in
primates. We have different types of
cells. Now we have our place cells of
course, but we also have our head
direction cells and we have a
representation of speed
which in so we have our play cells of
course. Then we have head direction
cells and speed cells and those form
this sort of network. And then you have
vestibular and optic flow information.
So the optic flow and vestibular
information is integrated by head
direction cells. So you see those two
inputs to head direction cells and head
direction and speed cells iteratively
update play cells. So play cells sit at
the top of this hierarchy. Head
direction and speed feed into it these
cells their states and determine the uh
state of the play cell. And then
vestibular and optic flow information
are going into head direction which
completes the network. And so we're
getting sensory information and
ultimately it's driving the behavior of
place cells. If we think a little bit
about these head direction cells,
they're very interesting. And so maybe
we can follow more up on that. So we
have two papers here. A bio inpired 3D
neural compass based on head direction
cells. This is an engineering take on
this uh where we're looking at this
model of of bat head direction cells.
And then this more biological paper
where they look at three-dimensional
head direction coding in the bat brain
and it's based on this model of the bat.
So the bat uses echolocation
and vision to sort of tune their spatial
navigation.
They have this flight room setup where
the bat is flying around the room.
They're taking pictures of the bat and
they're looking at their brain. They're
looking at the um HD cells, their tuning
width and their firing rate, and they're
looking at it for different behaviors.
They're looking at the tuning width in
percent. And then they're looking at the
peak firing rate in hertz. So this shows
that there's this response of head
direction cells for different types of
behaviors.
And in flight, there are different types
of neural responses.
And so if we put this into a phoggenetic
perspective, we have primates, corrupt
and rodents. These are all mammals, but
they're of course have different ways in
which they treat optic flow. So in
primates, we have optic flow
contributing to a view representation.
And this results in visual
specializations and primates, but it has
this view. This is why I showed the
image of that network with the uh place
cells and the visual information.
So that's in primates. But in corrupt
optic flow contributes to a view
representation as well. But this is due
to visual and auditory specialization.
So they have this view representation
and and corruptor is a sister out group
of primates. So that makes sense. But
they have this extra set of
specializations. And then rodents being
kind of distant from corruptor and
primates optic flow contributes to a
place representation where somata
sensory and old factory specializations
dominate. And so you can see that
there's this relationship between how
information like optic flow goes into
the brain and depending on how the brain
is adapted to different types of
environments, different types of
lifestyles, spatial cognition can occur
in different ways but kind of rely on
the same substrate. And so this is just
a little uh at the lower right there's
just this little visualization of how in
flies visual motor transformations
um
basically stabilize flight through this
optic flow mechanism. So this is
actually quite a bit different than the
mamalian last common ancestor and
this is quite different than the last
common ancestor for mamalians.
But you see that uh
you see that flies are also using uh
optic flow to stabilize their movements
and then that translates into how they
can navigate through space. O'Keefe and
Nato actually had a lot to say about
Gibson. And they quote is, "Spatial
cognition is a set of transformations
acting on sensory input and variance in
the form of things like ambient optic
arrays are extracted from multiple sets
of alternative viewpoints or
experiences.
And so this paper below on the ambient
optic array and eye perception kind of
shows what this looks like. So basically
uh you have all of these possible
sensory transformations from the sensory
world. We have this physical set of
transformations and this visual set of
transformations and spatial cognition is
basically acting upon these
transformations
finding specific pathways forward. So
you have all the sensory information
which gives you a lot of possible places
to explore. brain and spatial cognition
filter out and leave you with a small
set of alternatives that you can then
explore. So sensory transformations can
disambiguate objective or alocentric and
subject ego subjective egocentric
movement. These trajectories are the
consequence of the sensory environment
but also the way the agent moves through
the sensory environment and it can kind
of put things into different frames. And
so of course then observers or agents
being observers move to different
locations relative to their target and
they have to be able to track that
target as they move even though the
perspective changes and the object
changes its kind of size and shape in
the alocentric space. So this little set
of pipes here is, you know, if you have
this agent here and it's moving in sort
of a an arc, it's going to take
different viewpoints of this set of
pipes and it's going to look at it in
different ways and it's going to get
different information, but it can always
tell that it's looking at an arc.
Furthermore, it can remember all those
positions and it can use those to
navigate through these pipes knowing
relative information, relative
alocentric information about the object
in the environment. And so this paper by
Rushton and Warren is moving observers
relative retinal motion and the
detection of object movement talks a
little bit about this in terms of your
agent moving over time at a certain
angle and then having these points of
reference where their uh frame of
reference shifts and then they have to
use their memory system to sort of align
everything later when they go back to
navigate it. And of course we can look
at very small connetos to think about
different types of plausible visual
pathways. So what I showed you in the
last slide was this image of all these
plausible visual pathways where we kind
of the brain filters out all of the
implausible ones and leaves us with the
most likely visual pathways. But in a in
an anoid conneto which is very small um
it's less than 100 neurons uh we get
this we can do these experiments where
we can look at all the plausible visual
pathways available to the anoid and so
we can look at this in terms of a two
pixel system which is this sensory motor
photo receptor uh that can spatially
resolve light stimuli and then the
information is sent to the aector on
each side and it drives behavior. here.
And then over time you get these
different nerves that are ipsolateral
and you know they cross the midline and
then you have these uh more evolved eyes
you know with lenses and eye spots and
things like that. And then so you build
up from that simple model to these more
complex models and you can get these
more complex behaviors like mutual
inhibition, bilateral divergence, signal
delays and all this. And so the reason
I'm showing you this is to show you that
uh spatial perception and spatial
cognition can be relatively easy. You
don't need to have a a representational
system. You don't even need to have that
many cells. And but this is also it's a
hypothesized precursor to visual system.
So if this looks familiar this is
because it is the sort of biocybernetic
approach and it's similar to
Brightenberg's approach to
biocybernetics with vehicles and
building vehicles that uh approximate
small connetos nervous systems things
like that. We can also look at spatially
distributed light sources which require
sensory arrays internal pathways and
viewpoints on the light sources. So
things now you get embodiment involved
and body location and posture become
important. And we actually had an
interesting discussion at one of our
Saturday morning neurosim meetings on
Brightenberg's neuroanatomy and
synthetic biology work. Bradenberg
actually did a lot of neuroanatomy
before he proposed the vehicles work and
he built these he investigated fly
connetos quite extensively looking at
their neuroanatomy looking at their uh
their output behavior and this is kind
of what led him to the vehicles Oh,
So you know there's a lot of kind of uh
space between fly connetos and braenberg
vehicles. It's really interesting
biocybernetics and I think has a lot of
relevance to this topic. So go back to
our July 19th, 2025
meeting for more. And we have this new
paper out called a brief history of
cybernetic imperatives. This is on the
SI archive. This is uh thinking about
how we model plausible movements. So so
far we've talked a lot about uh vision
and visual information and then spatial
cognition as sort of a neural circuit or
a set of neural mechanisms.
And so that's all well and good, but
then you have this behavior and this
behavioral output is related to that
processing and how much information
specifically how much regulation goes
into those movements. So this again is
kind of thinking about simplistic
movements that result from maybe like a
small agent like a small conneto or a
vehicle. And so we have these different
types of movements going from random and
brownie in motion to levy flights where
you kind of move around randomly but
visit specific locations. And then you
have ballistic movements which are just
kind of like um sort of moving in a
certain direction and then moving again
in a certain direction which is moving
directionally but uncontrolled. And then
four you have first order prediction and
dynamics. So once you enter prediction
in the mix, you bring in feedback, you
bring in this sort of these dynamics
that are smoother. You know, you can
explore areas that are sort of
controlled in a curved manner. And then
finally, five, you have higher order
prediction and dynamics where you can
smooth out your curve and you can
actually make these very intentional,
very controlled movements. Maybe you're
trying to uh reach a prey or something
like that. And there are a lot of
different uh behaviors in insects which
are very interesting in terms of prey
capture as bats as well where they kind
of uh move towards their prey. They kind
of move past the prey and then back
towards the prey. And that's all based
on their ability to get sensory
information to update their spatial map
and then capture the prey successfully.
So this sort of typology of behaviors is
something we're kind of working on as
well and we want to fit this into this
model of spatial intelligence. So next
is the path integration and taxis view
and I say photo chemother
taxis that we want to talk about here.
So photoaxis are light signals.
Chemotaxis are chemical signals.
Thermotaxis are uh thermal signals and
thigotaxis are touch signals. And taxis
refers to when you have a an
environmental signal in that form and
then it forms a gradient in the
environment and the agent or the
organism will follow that gradient from
where they are to the highest
concentration of that gradient. So the
toxic movements are organized not by
some great regulatory mechanism but just
kind of following the gradient to the
next highest concentration. So this kind
of relates to path integration. So I'm
going to talk a little bit about path
integration which is sort of um
wayfinding or u homing if you are
familiar with like ants or something
like that where or insects where they
use path integration quite extensively
and it's kind of remembering space and
remembering sort of the map of the space
around you and then kind of going from a
home location knowing how space is
transformed and then moving back to the
original home location. So you explore
space a while and then you can always
find your way back home. And so that's
path integration. It has an interesting
relationship with toxic behavior and
we'll get into what that is. So we have
these two papers, possible uses of path
integration and animal navigation and
then principles of insect path
integration.
And so this is path integration in ants.
So you can see it's a very complex set
of behaviors. It almost looks like our
second phase of behavior is the uh levy
flights where they kind of move in a
certain direction but they make these
leaps and uh this is kind of you know
what what happens in ants where they
leave home. They they forage in the
environment and then they have to return
to the nest. And so they're using their
ability uh they're using pherommones.
They're using their ability to navigate
and remember space and remember how it
transforms when they turn their bodies
and then make it back home. So path
integration is the basis for cognitive
mapping. Path integration will happen in
other organisms as well, including
mammals. So this isn't just a thing that
you find in insects, but insects make
great use of this. Uh so this is the
basis for cognitive mapping. there's a
limited use of landmarks and resetting
processes. So they use landmarks but not
exclusively. They also reset their uh
their calibration tool. So usually they
measure footfall or something like that
and they use that as a heristic. Uh they
also reset their footfall information
sometimes. So this there are all sorts
of mechanisms involved in this. So the
information needed to compute a
trajectory involves a limited
approximation of distance when the
target is close. But when the uh target
is farther away, you need to have a
little bit different strategy. Sometimes
you can use the direction to goal which
is fixing and resetting your position
and then matching behavior or having a
coordinate system on top of a map and
having that coordinate system be the
guide to getting back to home base. And
so there these different ways in which
information can compute a trajectory and
perform this path integration. Now
there's some very interesting
connections with taxis because like with
path integration, taxis are cases where
the organism goes out explores their
environment. Maybe they're foraging or
maybe they're doing something else
trying to find some delicious uh meal of
some chemical chemicals or something
like that and then return home or return
to some other place. And so instead of
sort of these other mechanisms that we
think about, we actually have these
gradients that one can follow. You
follow the gradient to its source and
you then find your reward. So there's
this very clear signal, environmental
signal of where to go. But nevertheless,
you have to it's not a straight line.
It's not a straight shot to the source.
There's a lot of exploration and there
are mechanisms you need to use to
compare two different places where you
visited so you know where the greater
concentration of this thing is. So we
can actually build this interesting
table which is to generate a sort of a
contingency table for any one position
as you're tracking or um whatever it is
towards the source. So there are three
different behaviors. You can go towards
the source which is positive. You can
partially go towards the source which is
angular or you can be negative and move
away from the source. And so this is all
based on local information comparing two
different places revisited and moving in
that direction. And as you noticed with
path integration, the path is wavy and
it's curvy and and it doesn't it isn't a
straight line. And then we can use
different types of information in
sensory information. So we can use
light, photo, we can use chemistry,
chemo, we can use touch, thigma,
temperature, thermo, hardness, duro and
electricity or electro. So these are all
known taxes. And sometimes you can use
more than one taxis. You could use
photoaxis and chemotaxis or photoaxis
and thermotaxis and integrate them in a
way that helps you to improve your
performance. So for each of these then
you can say if you're at a photoaxis you
can move towards the photoaxis or
towards the thermoaxis or you might move
towards the photoaxis and partially
towards the thermmoexus
and this is all based on local
information. So over time it'll average
out to this path towards the source but
it does produce some interesting
dynamics especially when you have
multiple modalities. And so that relates
to path integration of course because
the source might often be some sort of
you know uh food source and then being
able to return home from there is also a
function of uh sort of following the
outbound signal or maybe following sort
of the decreasing gradient. These are in
mechanisms that don't involve the type
of hippocample spatial cognition we
talked about earlier but is nonetheless
part of the spatial intelligence. We can
also look at agents and and we did this
interesting work with agents where we
were doing this sort of dendritic
computing with agents. So we had these
Bradenberg vehicles with antennas and
the antennas had these different sensory
uh sensors on them and they take in
environmental information in this
spatial array. So you have sort of this
beam form of spatial information going
from left to right and it comes into
this uh antenna or this array and then
it encounters these transformation
points before it goes in the nervous
system. So the way dendritic computing
works is you have sort of the analogy of
dendrites in the brain where you have
these uh these treelike structures where
environmental information hits the
treelike structure and all of these sort
of uh parts of the array interact with
one another or you know maybe the ones
to the left take in more information the
ones to the right given the sort of the
direction of the source of the
information and then that influences how
it's processed by maybe like the logic
gate or some sort of transformational
process before it gets into the into the
nervous system. And so this is a
interesting sort of paradigm because you
can do a lot of interesting things with
spatial processing. You can have
environmental information that is
directional. It could be far to your
left or far to your right or it could be
right in front of you and that
information is processed differently
even though it's the same source. So if
you think of taxes, of course your taxes
are going to be different. Your
information is going to be maybe refined
or maybe it'll be obscured by this kind
of paradigm. Um but you know it's it's
going to influence how things happen.
And of course this is sort of how you
know if we have if we care about
embodiment, we're going to have this
sort of array of sensors on the outside
of the organism. It could be a visual
system. It could be other sensors. And
so we need to consider how those are
processed spatially and how that
influences behavior. This is another
example of sort of linking phenotype to
the sort of processing where the surface
perimeter is very curved and you have
these these uh dendritic trees or these
arrays that uh sort of conform to the
shape of the the body of the agent. You
have what we call sensory beam forming.
This is a an idea from engineering where
you take the different orientations of
sensory information and process it based
on its spatial location or its spatial
orientation to the sensor and then to
the organism as a whole. So this is very
different from the way we kind of
usually think about spatial processing
as sort of like this undifferentiated
signal that then gets processed in the
brain. This is actually what's processed
in these placement of the sensors on the
body. We also have sensory modality
specific gradients. This is from another
paper I published. So in this case each
sensory modality forms an input vector
and these are doesn't necessarily need
to be an embodied agent but this is like
uh where we have different sensory
modalities and the agent is sensing the
modalities and the modalities form a
gradient in the environment. So each
sensory modality forms an input vector
to the agent. A directed vector
describes the direction of exploration
along the sensory gradient for each
vector. So each of these vectors
describes a certain modality. It
describes a direction in which it's it's
located and the direction of exploration
that's expected. And so you can have
these different vectors um that are
aligned or they're misaligned. And so
sometimes visual information is in a
different place in the environment than
auditory information or touch
information. And those all have to get
integrated. Uh either you know sometimes
you'll have an angular displacement,
sometimes they're all coming from the
same direction. And so that's easy to
determine the the sort of the direction
of behavior, expected behavior. And so
this fits into this model of openloop
intelligence augmentation where we can
have this model of intelligence as an
openloop amplifier. to something like
what W or Ashb predicted in uh his
cybernetics work but instead of having
uh this sort of model of the environment
and sort of like an intelligence or an
internal model we have an intelligent
agent with a world model and then we
have this uh formulation of intelligence
which is sort of the uh sensory
information that's incoming feed forward
behavior the behavior that's generated
And then the selection mechanism on that
uh sensory pro sensory information. So
sensory processing is incoming sensory
information with selection that
determines your initial sort of
intelligence and then there's some model
of the world that you refer to to refine
that. And so thinking about spatial
navigation in a mathematical framework,
we're interested in spatial navigation
as this continuous set of dynamics. So
we can use a labbrian to describe this.
We can draw this from the equations of
motion. So we're interested in spatial
navigation, not necessarily as an agent
that's visiting a number of locations
and looking at the pretty uh squiggly
lines that it generates, but we really
want to know what the equations of
motion are because the equations of
motion can tell us something about the
behavior of the agent and in turn what
they're doing to process information to
produce this trajectory. So this is a
kinetic description and navigation where
the segments of motion or output of
place in grids rep representations for
example where other types of spatial
representations are put into the
environment as behavior and this is an
active process. So as representation
changes so too do the equations of
motion. This is a sketch of maybe what
this looks like in terms of the uh
taxis. So we have an agent Bradenberg
vehicle. It's integrating taxis from
multiple sensory sources and produces
this grandian description or this
trajectory that goes through space. You
start near sort of a thermal thermal
gradient. So you get these thermal taxis
and then you leave the thermal gradient
and you go to the chemical gradient and
you venture through the chemical
gradient. You come back out to the uh pH
gradient and then you venture through
that. come back to the sigma taxic
gradient and then out. So you you
explore these different gradients as you
encounter them. Sometimes the gradients
overlap but it basically describes sort
of the spatial behavior in terms of
these guiding cues and then the internal
mechanisms. You know that's something in
this model it's a black box but we can
think back to some of the potential
mechanisms that we might use to produce
this behavior. So I want to go back to
sort of the internal aspect of
intelligence and talk about the
neuroethological view. Neuroethology
being sort of the study of the brain in
naturalistic contexts. So again we
revisit this idea of spatial congruence.
We saw that back a few slides back that
we had those uh sensory vectors that
were maybe they were aligned and maybe
there was some displacement. In this
case, you can see kind of what that
looks like. They train these cats to
respond to signals that are both
congruent, meaning that a visual signal
and an auditory signal are coming from
the same place, and signals that are in
congruent. So, if the auditory signal
and the visual system or visual signal
are coming from different places and
then the food reward is where you get
the food, right? So, you know, it has if
the signal is coming from the same
place, the cat goes to that food tray,
gets the reward. If the signal is coming
from two different places, the cat has
to sort of figure out where the food
reward is. Is it the auditory signal or
the vis uh visual signal and they have
to disambiguate the two signals to get
the food reward. So, disongruous sensory
cues are feel spatial biases.
Not all locations or orientations are
equivalent. So it has to sort of sort
through even though it has all these
orientations and rotations spatial
rotations and spatial location
information stored in its internal model
of the environment. It still has to
disambiguate a lot of information to
make decisions to make the right
decisions without error. We you know we
have this model of coincidence detection
spatial coincidence detection is rooted
in the superior caliculus. You can see a
model of superior caliculus at the lower
right. And so these experiments are very
famous for revealing yet another place
where spatial processing happens. Uh
related to this is the chemo affinity
hypothesis. This is another famous
experiment where it's more about spatial
framing. So the idea is that you have
well in the Spir uh experiments on this
he took a frog and he cut the eye out
and he rotated at 180°. So when the eye
is in its normal position, the frog can
shoot out its tongue at like a a fly and
capture pretty quickly and do this
pretty accurately. But when he moves the
eye 180°, he rotates it in its socket.
The tongue goes in the opposite
direction of the fly almost
consistently. And so the idea there is
that you have this spatial frame that's
based on the eye and and the way it
develops. that spatial frame is put into
place and then when you rotate the eye
you're basically shifting that spatial
frame 180° off the spatial represent
representation of the optic tectum is
established in development and it stays
like that throughout adulthood. When you
shift the sensory array the
corresponding reference frame is shift.
So again we have these two cases of
spatial inongruity. one where you have
two senses that are uh decoupled, the
other where you decouple the sensory
array from the target in the
environment.
And so that leads us to this
neurosimulated Morris water maze. And so
this is interesting because you have
visual and auditory sources and they're
decoupled from each other. Not only are
they decoupled, but you have multiple
sources around the arena. The idea is
these vehicles will travel and try to
find the corresponding visual and
auditory sources. So they there's kind
of like this
uh this are a great this spatial
gradient of visual information and
auditory information. And in some places
it's mixing in some places it's
independent. And so these vehicles are
kind of exploring their space trying to
fix on some source and exploring its
space. And so this is kind of a
continuous maze. If we think back to the
mazes that we used for uh you know
hippocample learning, this is a
continuous maze and this is something
that will you know maybe tell us
something about how we can process
spatial inongruous spatial information
in very simple nervous systems. And one
more detail about this is that sometimes
these sensors are all located sort of in
the same direction. you have on this
vehicle here, you have three sensors all
pointed forward, but on this vehicle,
but on this vehicle, you have sensors
that are pointed in all different
directions. You basically mutated them
so that they're on different sides of
the body. And so that affects
processing. Sometimes that leads to a
periodic orbit, sometimes it leads to
something else. And we don't know, we
haven't run these experiments, but this
is just kind of a thought experiment uh
where, you know, we're kind of thinking
about varying the sensor uh location,
varying the sensory source location, and
then having this naturalistic behavior
where we can observe gradient following
and behave output behaviors that are
spatially interesting. So if we have
this spatially incoherent framing plus
spatially in in congruent multiensory
information it can lead to release
interesting dynamics. So then the next
two papers are the brain stem integrator
for self-location and memory and
positional homeostasis and zebra fish
and topographic maps of visual space in
the human cerebellum.
So this starts with a a quote from this
Vaness paper from 2019. That's the
second one. Topographic maps of visual
space in the human cerebellum.
And this is uh as follows. Retinotopic
mapping under fixation precludes a
distinction between purely retinopic or
eye-c centered, craniotopic or
head-entered, spatiootopic or world
center and other spatial encoding
schemes. This is in line with what we've
been talking about. We've been talking
about different types of sensory
centered uh processing, head centered
processing, head direction cells, etc.
And then this aloscentric view of the
world where things are spatiical.
We have this uh retinopic mapping that
in humans at least or in mammals is
precludes these distinctions. And so
this actually points to the cerebellum
is another site of spatial processing.
The cerebellum encodes multiple polar
coordinate maps of visual information
that provides information to the
aectors. So now we're not talking about
the sensors, we're talking about the
aectors. So now this is the outbound
information and the cerebellum encodes
these maps for that outbound information
to be transformed. Okay. So now we're
dealing with embodiment. We're dealing
with the consequences of embodiment. The
cerebellum is known for producing smooth
movements. It's involved in motor
control. It's involved in smoothing out
motor control and and having these
predictive models is very unique
architecture allows you to do that. And
O'Keefe and Nadal of course also had
something to say about embodiment which
is that the movement of an observer's
body changes position but does not alter
the position of objects. This is
distinct from relative position. The
body changes position of course as you
move. It doesn't alter the position of
objects though because you have sort of
a framework for thinking about different
transformational views on objects. So if
you're looking at an object from the
front or from the back or from the side,
you can put that together and know that
that's the same object. This is a
graphical abstract from this Yang paper
and cell. This is a zebra fish. It shows
that the cerebellum and the inferior
olive are involved in this location
error signal and then it's also involved
in determining velocity and also then
you know the zebra fish is moving with a
change in position. So it's locating the
error signal. It's correcting the error
signal and generating a certain velocity
that changes the position in an adaptive
manner. And we can think of this as a
control system where we have this input
that leads to swimming behavior. So we
have the neural coding, the behavior and
these brainwide circuits that control
this centered on the cerebellum, the
inferior olive. And so we can think
about this in terms of a map. So we have
our cell cerebellar map. It's taking in
information from different parts of this
organism. So we have the a lot of things
in the head that are mapped to things in
the hippocampus and then those are
produce outputs for those things. So we
have output behaviors
uh being uh mapped from the hippocampus
to output behaviors. Um and this is very
much like sort of a homunculus map that
you see in the neoortex.
Um and so you know we can actually
replicate this in a vehicle. We can have
this little area here where it maps
sensors from different places to these
maps and then an output to theseectors.
So you have inputs and they get mapped
to different cell populations which have
uh sort of a mapping to a specific
output. So in this case in vehicles or
wheels and you have these uh sensors
they could be light sensors or vibration
sensors bringing in information.
And so you know we can kind of classify
our different uh inputs and our
different outputs. And this is kind of
what you see with the topographic
distribution of output neurons and the
cerebellar nuclei and cortex to
smattopic maps and primary motor cortex.
So this just shows for different uh
aectors like hind limb or proximal
forlim or distal forlim there's a
different distribution of cells for each
of those types of output in the
cerebellum.
And so looking at this more closely you
can build a start to build a network
from these different uh cell types. It
adds self, it adds a functional layer to
these cell types in vehicles and it
gives us this ability to map things
outward as well as from the sensory
system inward. There's this core sensor
factor mapping where you get spatial
biases biases in these inter neuronal
networks. You get information exchange
among spatially sensitive inter neurons
and then peripheral processing networks
which are shown in the different colors
here are specialized subn networks for
timing differentiating and integration
of activity. So what we're trying to do
is build a very small nervous system
that replicates some of these findings.
But next I'd like to talk about these
two papers. The first is omnidirectional
sensory and motor volumes and electric
fish and then spatial planning with long
visual range benefits. escape from
visual predators in complex naturalistic
environments.
So, this first example shows the weekly
electric fish. The weekly electric fish
are interesting because they send out
this electrical signal around their body
and they sense prey in an environment
where they can't really see anything.
It's a very murky aquatic environment
and they have this is what they call
active sensation. So the electrical
signal that's sent around their body
from the electric organ near the head to
the tail where there's a receptor is
this electrical field this volume. And
so uh in the first paper that I talked
about this they've uh reconstructed
these sensory volumes around the fish at
different orientations. And then these
dots involve sort of prey that are in
the electrical field so that the fish
can sense the location of the prey so it
can move towards those prey and capture
them. So you can see that the prey are
spatially located spatially uh
segregated within this volume. um and
then the fish have to make a movement
towards that. And of course there are
different perspectives on this volume.
So if you look at the side view or the
back view, you can see that there's a
different distribution of things. And so
one of the thing other things that they
explored was this habit-based versus
plan-based action selection. So once the
electric fish senses that they're prey
within the volume, they can go and
capture the prey. But they have these
two strategies called habit-based and
plan-based action action selection.
Basically, they've did these uh
simulations uh where you could look at,
you know, what was involved in this. And
and I'll just tell you right now that
habit-based is not predictive and
plan-based is more predictive.
And so habit is based on a model free
approach. So habit is where behaviors
generated by state action values are not
related to immediate outcomes. They're
not adaptive. They're just state action
values. and there's no real prediction
there. Um, and then planning is a
model-based approach where behaviors are
best based on action outcome knowledge
structure. So, a knowledge structure
that helps prediction. Future states and
expected outcomes are modeled and this
is very adaptive. So, you know, you know
kind of what you're you what future
states to expect. You know what outcomes
to expect and it's much more predictive
than the habit model which is kind of
just output of behavior. And so these
are interesting because we talked about
in last year's talk by our group about
the role of habit in planning in sort of
agents and and thinking about uh
cybernetics what they call goal-
directed behavior. And so this is an
important distinction that is also
important in the spatial intelligence
paradigm. Finally we want to talk about
the view from embodiment in GSLAM. GSLAM
stands for generalized simultaneous
localization and mapping. So again we've
talked about embodiment we haven't
talked about GSL slam and so we'll talk
about two paper GS slam papers one is by
Adam Saffron and colleagues generalized
simultaneous localization and mapping GS
slam as unification framework for
natural and artificial intelligences and
then this other review on a visual slam
for robotics evolution properties and
future applications. So in these papers
basically they think about um spatial
processing as the sort of control
system. You have a control mechanism U
subP discrete time steps T subi then
sensor observations O subt. So you have
these three components. Then it leads to
an agent state X of T environmental map
M subt and that leads to spatial
representation and behavior. So it kind
of looks almost like a reinforcement
learning model with input from previous
states the environment and then it gives
you the spatiotemporal representation.
But of course there is this aspect of
the classic Sydney Harris cartoon where
he has he's very vague in step two and
he says then a miracle occurs. And so we
don't necessarily know what the filler
is in this between agent state the
environmental map and then defining
those and then what what leads to
spatial representation and
spatiotemporal representation and
behavior. It's a it's a hazy box. It
maybe can see somewhat inside of it and
I think things I've talked about in this
talk at least from the bio biological
standpoint can help. But we can also
think about saffron's idea of latent
slam. And this is a basis for map
updating. So we're not totally lost here
in slam. We can use these kind of latent
spaces to help us simulate spatial
behavior and then things beyond that.
But uh latent slam is an evaluation
between currently represented and novel
experiences. There's what they call view
pose matching based on place cell and
grid cells. So they use the place cell
grid cell model. So when current
observations match information then loop
closure in the representation happens
and that's confirmation that that
observation is in the representation in
the weight in space. When no node can
match existing information in the
representation new nodes are inserted.
That's this graph relaxation. So
basically what happens is you have this
latent space that grows with experience.
And so you know you either confirm that
you've been you you have this this
experience of the wait and spaces or
this structure of the weight in space is
either confirmed or disisconfirmed with
environmental information and then when
it's disisconfirmed you add nodes to
represent that. So next time when you
encounter something similar you have
that representation in place. And so a
couple words about the loop closure
algorithm. Um this is from introduction
to loop closure detection in slam. Um
this is where you have a form of error
accumulation that occurs similar to path
integration in animals. And so uh in
path integration as well as for this
form of error integration you count the
steps along a path and when a landmark
recurs the map is updated to reflect
that information. And so if we we state
this kind of in a pathy way, we can say
keep wandering until you find a loop
closure. Wait a minute. I've been here
before. So you wander down the beach and
you keep going and you find a loop
closure until you kind of go all the way
down the beach and back to another point
that you've been to before. So there are
connections between this kind of weight
in space approach and a cybernetic
system. So latent slam attempts to
recapitulate a neuroanatomically
interesting weight in space model.
Latent space allows us to compress a
full state space where we don't need
knowledge full knowledge of every state.
In control theory, state space models
serve as a path of dynamical systems
like we talked about with the lrangeian
and and all this about trajectories. In
a cybernetic formulation, however, we
can build upon latent slam by using a
state space, a growing network and
causal relations. So we can actually
formulate a solution to this in the form
of a cybernetic model and this is
something I think we also talked about
last year. We'll get to this in a minute
but this is an example of graphical
relaxation algorithms. So this improves
your oilerian path estimates for your
network structure by checking if a
shorter path can be found through
alternative edges. In this case adding
edges. So you explore this network. You
see what the path lengths are for each
traversal of the network and if um you
know if it if it can be found great. If
not it adds a node and you have this
shorter path. But this is kind of the
way you can do this in a cybernetic
context. These are these complex
referential or quasi causal relations
for different control outcomes. This is
from last year's um symposium where we
proposed this uh cybernetic model of
feedback loops that produce not just the
past, present, future but also
alternative futures and complex outputs
associated with all of them. So you can
model uh a feedback loop as sort of um
going back to the future basically um as
you have in a in a first order closed
loop feedback context and then it
produces a complex output with a lot of
different causal uh consequences and and
u with a lot of uh sort of uh causal
implications but then you also have
these alternative futures that can be
generated from the same system. Another
way to think about this in space is you
have these Teletubbies that are, you
know, there's one in the present, maybe
they were here in the past, here in the
present, and then you have these
alternative futures, maybe a future
state over here, and an alternative
future state over here. There's a
spatial location associated with each of
them. This cybernetic model recalls
Douglas Hoffstead's I am a strange loop
where in chapter 4 he talks about loops,
goals, and loopholes. And he talks about
how self-applied operations can produce
these circularities that are very
interesting not only from a causal
standpoint but from a spatial standpoint
as well. And so we can also think about
erodicity and how that can also
contribute to the sort of spatial
learning. So erodicity is this idea that
if you visit enough locations in a
space, you can produce a mean path that
describes every location in that space.
So the mean value is something that
gives you full spatial knowledge of that
that domain. And so this is a paper
where they're using a robot to learn all
the possible states of a movement path.
The mean path is described by robotic
systems. This mean path is optimal and
this can actually help uh assist people
with disabilities, people who can't move
optimally in space. If you have a robot
that can sort of explore all the spatial
locations in maybe like a movement space
like a workspace or in a in a room or
something like that then you can assist
people when they make mistakes and help
them cover up their mistakes um through
knowing sort of the mean value should be
at any location. So again, our our
graphic here in our piffy statement, if
you walk down the beach enough times,
you can predict a path that matches the
wap of the waves from a mean value. So
you can actually track the path of the
incoming tide and walk right along the
water's edge if you've walked along this
beach enough. This brings us to this
idea of an ergotic ensemble, which is
where if you sample a system enough
times, any given ensemble is equivalent
to the time average. That's sort of the
formal definition. Learning increases
information but an internal
representation may provide erodicity. So
an example of this is for native
language speakers the language tends to
be erotic versus English as a second
language speakers where the language
tends to be non-orgotic. And this is
from a study where they looked at native
speakers and English as a second
language speakers. you have to build
this strong internal representation
characterized by sort of native language
ability when described in basian versus
statistical mechanics terms. So
erodicity is usually described in terms
of statistical mechanics. Individual
cases are not equivalent to generalized
maps. And so this is something
interesting about this that we can use
this kind of uh erotic example. We can
use erodicity to describe spatial
navigation but we also have to take
individual experience into account.
Sometimes
um spatial navigation for one person is
not erotic but for a population it is.
So what have we learned? Uh the first
thing is that a representational system
that is anatomically explicit like such
as the hippocampus and evolutionarily
conserved so the hippocampus and
vertebrates provides the hardware for
quick efficient spatial learning. So the
longer you have that structure around
evolutionarily the more refined it can
be the more erotic your you know if you
acquire something in development then
it's you know it's erotic and you have
the hardware to carry that out. If you
have to use sort of a an expedient neuro
architecture for this to learn it or
it's not something that is typically
learned from development then you're not
going to have as efficient a spatial
learning. Number two, optic flow
mediates spatial perception in terms of
both the body egocentric and environment
eocentric. And so we have these
different frameworks for the body and
for the environment. Optic flow mediates
spatial perception in that way.
Viewpoint representations or frames of
reference also depend on sensory
specializations established in
development. So technically the sensory
specializations are established in
evolution, but you can have these things
play themselves out in development and
they influence the viewpoint
representations across species and how
the you know for different sensory
systems for different uh
neuroarchchitectures.
They actually mediate spatial learning.
Number three, path integration produces
dynamical trajectory with complex parts.
So this is again path integration
another form of spatial intelligence
where you get this dynamical trajectory
where you can compo decompose the parts
of the trajectory and it tells you
something about in you know uh periodic
spatial intelligence or at least the
behavior of spatial cognition and so
path integration results from sensory
and internal information as well as
processes of regulation and prediction.
Number four, a body can be characterized
by a sensory manifold while sensory
motor integration acts as an immediate
source of spatial bias. So again, we
have this the body plays a role and then
sensory integration also plays a role.
And so sometimes our body is getting
visual information from one location and
auditory information from another.
Sometimes our bodies can act to bring
those together, sometimes not. And so
this is an immediate source of spatial
bias. Action selection operates on the
integration of immediate or longer term
information. So we can have a simple
model of immediate uh sensory
information like in the habit case in
the electric fish simulations or a
longer term model of planning or
sometimes we can use a world model like
we talked about in the uh intelligence
augmentation example where you have this
model of the world that you draw from.
So it's a longer term context. Number
five, unified models such as GS slam
serve as a framework for embodied
information processing. This unifies the
role of hippocample path integration,
circuit, optic flow, and the spatial
bias to sensory reception. So, GSLM
really unifies a lot of these mechanisms
into one framework. Um, and then six,
which is an additional thing, and this
is kind of more of an insight. enough
free or random navigation can produce a
good enough cognitive map by relying on
an erotic ensemble of spatial
information. So if we just let our
simulation run forever, our agent
explore forever, it can produce a good
enough cognitive map, it doesn't
necessarily need a lot of architecture,
but the architecture deals with a lot of
these other aspects of structure that
random or free navigation may not solve.
And so again with the neuro we're
dealing with potential brain centers,
connectivity mechanisms for spatial
representations and cognition across
animals. The simulate we're using boxes
and arrows or cybernetic type systems,
spatial distributions of sensory
information, mathematical functions that
describe behavioral output, simple
biocybernetic agents, and models of
sensory processing from the literature.
So in future directions we need more
complex models, more exploration of
causality and systems context, expansive
and reconfigurable networks and of
course more synthesis of all these
ideas.
Thank you for your attention.
All right, we're back with our next
session. So, I will let Stephen
introduce the speakers and thank you all
for joining. Go for it.
>> Okay. Thank you, Daniel. Thank you very
much for having us here. Uh this is a
wonderful opportunity because we all
come from different backgrounds but
we're very much united in that active
inference has a tremendous potential to
help more people actionably in the
relatively near term than we think is
realized and we've been coming at it
from different ways and learning from
one another. So we appreciate this
opportunity to share this u uh Jakamo I
have to tell you before we started
talking with this with with this project
your work on light touch and and
contextual work um is something that I
have quoted and that I believe has a
tremendous relevance for my profession.
I'm a chiropractor. You're a PT. Uh Jim,
you're a body worker from a sematic
point of view, massage, but you've taken
Marco blankets in a whole new direction.
And I'm looking forward to seeing your
presentation on Friday. And Dave is our
academic that's going to be leading us.
Uh Dave Newuel is at UCCC. he's which is
one of the premier chiropractic
institutions globally and he's working
with a new group of pain inference uh of
active inference focused on pain and
that's basically the name of the group
and we look forward to Dave's work
pulling us together. So with that Dave
um take it away.
>> Thanks Stephen. So um I'm going to
attempt as far as I can to um chair
this. We're going to try and make this
relatively informal uh conversation. We
have a few sort of kickoff questions
that we're going to try to use to unpack
each of our um guests here that Stevens
has outlined in terms of their
background, their interest, how they got
to this particular point. Um um I I
think Steven and I but I think the two
of us did watch Carl's um plenary
introduction. I must admit um you know
listening to that I firmly put myself in
the developing category when it came to
um active inference and uh I've had some
interest in this for for a couple of
years and from particular background
before that which we'll probably get
into and all of us will um so but having
said that um you know we've each come to
this in our own particular way um and um
and um And some of the questions that I
ask and I suspect perhaps some of our um
uh participants here will will ask as
well will be somewhat rhetorical. Um and
uh and so we'll we'll do our best to
make it entertaining, perhaps
informative and um and and see how it
goes. So I'm going to really sort of
kick off um with each of you really and
and I guess I'm going to go I'm going to
go with Jim first and go back that way
through Jakamo and then Steven. Um and
um you know that what was your journey?
Tell us something about your journey in
terms of being interested in active
inference. Why it struck you as a
framework that excited you? You know
what's unique about this? Because it's
pretty esoteric in I mean like it's not
all over Facebook and the national
newspapers. So, it's still, you know,
relatively outside of those people that
are really into this, you know, um a
rather niche idea. Um so, so how did you
get into it, Jim? And uh
>> let me let me try to answer that. Um
uh the So, first of all, uh Stephen, I
I'm not sure. I just spoke to Daniel
online by email. I think that my
presentation which is a recorded video
um that I finally updated uploaded last
night um in a fit in a rush to make the
deadline. I think it's going to be
available um at 22:30
UTC
today, but um so I don't I don't know if
I'm presenting on Friday, but it would
be a video that's it's already recorded.
Um and I go into everything in depth
there, of course. It's about a 50-minute
video. And um so my background is um I'm
a I'm a uh my academic training is is
historic history and social theory and
and then my my profession or my love
really is is touch. I just love touch
and I'm one of those people and and and
I'm a deep tissue structural body worker
and I've worked with um the fascia with
the my focus was in the deep core
anatomy as I worked on people I came to
understand that everyone is really
dealing with what I call postural
collapse syndrome
uh which is a failure of the postural
the core anatomy the postural system and
so I've spent the last whatever 10 years
really analyzing that and when I read
Sharington so and I'm a geek so I'm
reading all over the place and I'm
trying to understand interosception at
first which I got from somatic
psychology and I thought oh everything
is interosception then when I read
Sharington um I understood that that
that paradigm that that whole notion is
completely wrong and it's proprioception
and after that I connected with with um
uh Carl Fris 's work on the topic and
the work of the active inference
community and the whole idea of the
Marov blanket and a model of life. Now,
Sharington was the one that pioneered
that neural architecture, that model of
life in 1906 was never developed until
Carl Friston really took the bull by the
horns. And um and I think that having a
model of life is such a powerful thing,
a perceptual model and it's a spatial
model. So for for those of us into
somatics, the spatial reasoning is
really kind of the way we work. We're
rather than a topheavy kind of intellect
reasoning, it's more of a ecological
kind of um openness to the ecological
affordances that are provided and and
those are deep within us. So So I got
really excited. I just love the um I
mean you know complexity theory the
cybernetics and and um and as a
historian my focus has always been on
what I call the somatic tradition. Um
two books were published in 1543.
Copernicus was a mathematical one and
that defined the mathematical tradition
which has become ascended today of
course quickly became ascendant um
starting with Newton but the somatic
tradition throughout history has been a
vital one and that is asking a different
set of questions than the mathematical
tradition. about life and complexity and
Vicilius um wrote his fabric the fabric
of the human body also published in 1543
the same year as copernicus and that for
me began that sematic tradition the only
way to understand
complex living structures is through
complexity theory and I think that
active inference is it's just definitely
the most exciting and comprehensive and
really profound expression of complexity
theory that I've come across. I'm a big
fan. Um, that's kind of my background
there.
>> Brilliant. Now, that's really
interesting. I've got a couple of
things. We'll come back to that in a
moment. Um, but we'll we'll move on to
Jakamo, I think.
>> Yes. Thank you. Yes, I'm Jakamo Rosetti
and my background is from
physiootherapy. I'm both a clinician and
also a researchers. And during my
journey of in research, I have had the
possibility to investigate and learn
some points from the contextual factors
placebo and noibo effects. And through
this journey, I have had the possibility
to read some points regarding the active
inference. And I find this proposing
theory really interesting because it
fits well with a real life clinical
practice because it can help us to
explain the unexplainable things that we
encounter in the clinical scenario every
day. So starting from placebo, nobo and
contextual factors,
we can conceive these elements as
strategies that can have an impact in
terms of active inference and can
modulate the perception of patients and
also have an impact in terms of
therapeutic outcomes. But I think this
really this this is a really interesting
theory that we should develop and
investigate well using a networking and
different perspective from different
fields.
>> Brilliant.
Thank you Jacko.
>> Thanks Jacko. Um, Stephen,
>> uh, I'm a doctor of chiropractic who
practiced for 26 years. And in my
somewhat schizophrenic profession, I
played a number of roles, but uh, as an
undergraduate in college, I was between
psychology and biology practicing. I
spent time in Prague with with Vladimir
Yand if anyone's in that world
uppercross lower cross syndromes was
words that he created concepts that he
created and also I was into yoga and in
my practice we I realized that simply
manipulation by itself was not fixing
the problems once there was a motor
pattern that occurred and so we came at
it from a biomechanic and yoga point of
view with a little bit of mindfulness I
began lecturing and
in 2003 and then in 2011 the course that
I've been teaching was posture and motor
control exercise integrated with
chiropractic
mobilization and manipulation.
The book that caught me was a book by
Bud Craig, how do you feel? A
neurobiological moment with your
intraceptive self. Bud Craig opened the
door to introsception as a sense that
was separate and distinct from
propriception and within a lot of the
psychological research now the mind body
research intraception has become a big
topic and when I started looking at
intraception then I ran into active
inference and it's the same grounding
because introsception is one of the
inputs for active inference and it's
something that is not being realized in
in my mind in just about any clinical uh
way. Jacum, I believe some of your work
is one of the few that are touching on
that that that linkage from a sematic
point of view. And I believe that
there's a tremendous amount of good that
can come from creating agency in the
part of people, giving them the ability
to have self-efficacy
and to harness active inference as a
framework to be able to systematically
import that to people in different
clinical situations. back pain to psych
the psychological issues.
>> Brilliant. Thank you, Stephen. Um, so me
I guess um
I sort of I've been teaching
chiropractors for many years. I'm I'm
now part of a wonderful university
called the health sciences university in
Bournemouth in the UK that teaches many
health pray healthcare professions now
um including the man all of the manual
um professions um physiootherapy um
osteopathy
chiropractic we don't do massage as such
but I have a PhD student who's uh who
runs a school actually in the UK who who
does massage um and I think over the
years um I've become interested in the
mechanisms behind how therapeutic
encounters with manual therapists, you
know, are are just doing the thing that
they're doing. I mean, I think there is
there's there's now, you know, plenty of
evidence suggests that visiting a manual
therapist has really positive outcomes,
but I think one thing that's been
missing over many years, very
frustratingly, for scientists like me,
is exactly what is going on. You know,
people do all sorts of different things
to patients. Uh whether it be
manipulation, whether it be some form of
touch, whether it be exercises, joint
mobilization, all sorts of different
things. And we know that um that things
like, you know, exercise from exercise
to talking therapies to manual therapies
to a whole bunch of other things seem to
work relatively similarly. They they
work as well as each other in many ways.
And uh so so I got really interested
into why that was that was happening.
You know, what are the mechanisms going
on and and through that I I obviously
came into the world of placebo and nobo
like jakamo and um found that somewhat
frustrating because there's so much
historical ladeness that goes with the
language of placebo and nobo. It's a
sort of uphill battle to get clinicians
to listen to you when you're talking
about placebo and nobo in many ways. And
um and out of that then um segueed into
contextual factors which are this these
these things in therapeutic encounters
that can essentially change the meaning
of of what patients are are expecting to
happen and um and really then um
stumbled across I think I I I don't this
is right remember there was a paper by
Angara on capt who talked about
predictive processing as being
a part, you know, potential mechanism
behind placebo. And I think from that
sort of just fell into the active
inference framework um community and uh
you know was so enamored by the breadth
of that framework, its parimoniousness,
the potential
u width of things that it could start to
explain. you know, notwithstanding that
it actually had a you know, it it told a
story of a mechanism of life, let alone
clinical interactions and um and uh I
was so enamored. We we just set up a
center of pain and active inference
research at the university. So that's
how I am now. That's how committed I am
now to this framework. So um so yeah
very similar stuff and um so one thing I
would say would be and I think this
again it's one of these rhetorical
questions you know why do clinicians in
your your viewpoint need this rather
esoteric new um uh
45,000 ft view of of life framework you
know because I I'm sure in all of your
professions you know they they will say
Well, you know, this is all very well
and good, very interesting, but you
know, you know, my patients are getting
better. What What would you say to that?
Anybody?
There's a book by Simmonson, begin with
why.
I believe that active inference is an
underlying why for a lot of different
things that has not been effectively
articulated nor communicated.
I would say very much that the effort
to to talk about it from Carl Fston's
point of view from the pri presentation
today that are things that I don't know
a lot about personally but there's
congruences
and I think the more that people in
different professions can look at those
conf look at those and pull those truths
together addresses some of the issues
that I believe are coming for the active
influence community which is trying to
spread wider
And so having a common why for different
schools of thought like we have here
within one trench manual therapies and
making those uh congruent with other
schools of thought to become more of an
accepted truth is this is the way life
is I believe that's because that that's
the underlying u to me fascination and
promise of of active inference
ultimately.
>> Yeah. So a unifying mechanism really
that's I would agree with you that's t
tend to be what I've found actually
segueing out from that or going on to
you know using that as a platform then
can can each of you and I I'll start
with Jacma can can can each of you sort
of then tell us a little bit about how
it's informing your own work
particularly because I think you all
practice still um how it's informing
that on the ground
practice ractice focus people in front
of you real world stuff um and uh and
you know uh because I think that's
really important it's so easy to talk
about the sort of high level stuff that
we're we're talking about and listen to
people talk about that you know even not
not that I can do this but um Stephen
and I were talking about this even the
sort of all the maths behind it which
completely discombobulates me but the
you know what what is going on on the
ground so so Jack give us give us an
idea how it's how it's in you know
what's happening in your practice.
>> Yeah, I think that active inference
helped me but also all the other
clinicians for many reason. First of
all, it can symbolize an over an
overarching framework that help us to
explain why different treatment
strategies can help and have an impact
in terms of therapeutic outcome in our
patients.
independently from which kind of
treatment we decide to apply, but it
works as an general framework that help
us to understand what happens in the
clinical encounter.
And as a second reason is that help us
to explain why sometimes the different
treatment solution that we apply with
our patient doesn't work because there
is a great complexity in the real life
that is somebody unpredictable.
For this reason we need a framework that
help us to explain what happens in the
clinical practice because you know when
we treat the real patients that
sometimes we are challenged because the
patient has a very strong prior strong
belief
that are really difficult to be changed.
So in this using this model we can for
example use the different element
presented in the therapeutic arena name
as a contextual factors in order to
modulate the perception of patient and
help them to challenge their prior using
our worth their rituality our techniques
our verbal and nonverbal communication
and all the other cues presented in
therapotic encounter. s that can be
combined with a specificity of our
techniques they can act as a boost that
have an impact for our patients
perception for for so in this reason and
for this reason I think that the active
inference can really help the clinician
to understand what they are doing and
also understand the patient response in
the clinical practice and for that
reason there is a strong need of more
research and more awareness among
clinicians regarding this topic.
>> Yeah, that's great. I'm gonna go to Jim
next.
>> Hi. Um yeah, well, you know, um
the title of of my my my video, my
presentation is exterceptive bias and um
somatic belief updating in the global
model. And so I'm going to um
>> unpack that for us, Jim.
>> Say that again.
>> Unpack a little bit of that for us.
>> Oh,
I'm going to exterceptive bias then is
an innate natural setting in the system.
If we think about the receptors on the
outside of the of the of the organism,
right? We have distance receptors, touch
receptors, taste, smell. These are
distance receptors. And we um the part
of the brain that's associated with
exterception is also the surface, the
cortex of the brain. And interosception
then would be the viscera and then that
would be the insula. Bud Craig's famous
um insight there is the insula. and but
but for propriioception it's going to be
at the at the root here in the
cerebellum and the spinal cord. Now so
exterceptive bias is just a situation in
which
the organism is running its outer
sensors and you as soon as something is
born into the world it has to
immediately look for for warmth for
shelter for kin for food for safety and
that never stops. So there's a certain
innate bias in the system. There are an
awful lot more inputs coming from the
outside than from deep within for sure.
But exterceptive bias then can become a
control bias or a sort of a a vicious
cycle, a positive feedback loop if we're
repressing the inner sensibilities
which um it's the postural system. So
it's all balance, it's all integration,
it's all stabilization, centering and
grounding. These are the chinesiological
functions of the system. But they're
also the cognitive functions.
And without those then we can jump into
you know basically we're just thinking
too much and we're stuck in our head. So
when I sit down, when you sit about my
work, right? Like for me, a classic
example of my work is like I'm over at
the cafe and someone sits down and and
you know they're talking about their
pain or their issues and everything and
it's like let's get out of our heads
here and I say come on over here and sit
down and let me work your arm or your
hand or let me rub your shoulders or and
I do this in their coffee shop and um of
course you know with consent but um
you know getting out of our heads is
sort of a huge huge important theme and
as manual therapists that's our
specialty is coming into the body and as
a manual therapist I see my work both
theoretically and also in a tactile
sense is as a somatic educator helping
people to understand that interior
perceptual system and come into their
bodies and have that grounding and
centering that's available to them when
they need it or when they want it. Um
you may not want to be doing your
grounding and centering if you're in
heavy traffic, but you definitely don't
want to be um disregulated internally
either. So there's it's that that
underlying system is always running. But
what I think we're seeing in the world,
the surprisal that we're seeing in the
world is overreach. We can call it
technological overreach or the
anthroposine. and that the society that
we've built is really very too topheavy,
too intellectual
as organisms in the world, we need more
balance. And so that's kind of my focus
um as a sematic educator as a
Yeah.
>> D can I say something?
>> Yeah. Go on statement.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Um,
a point that I believe to making active
inference clinically actionable in the
field on the ground with clinicians is
making it something that is what you
said before Jakamo a boost to whatever
else we're doing. And I would even
amplify that by making it a synergy
because it's not just I think 20%
better. I think it's more like
potentially 200 that's
percent better. I it can make a dramatic
dramatic difference because it cannot
just be in the moment of the uh
therapeutic encounter whether you're
doing a manipulation or I am however we
both do it. It's connecting with them as
a person that and Jim I think this comes
back to what you were talking about. Um
yeah
>> but a point that I think needs to be
made that ironically enough Carl first
said said earlier what he said was how
we see the world and how we react to the
world is what he was talking about but
uh um active inference being and when he
was talking about seeing I don't think
he was talking about visual visual I
think he was talking about the gestalt
of the self of the person and my add to
that my my riff on that would be how he
seatically and percept conceptually feel
the world and how we react to the world
and to that in terms of making it
actionable something that is a very much
an intraceptive insight is that it needs
to be moment by moment it can't be a
cognitive thing where now you know about
it so so you do it the interaction needs
to be now and now and now very much
correlating the the contextual
communication which David I I like I I
teach things using something that that
would describe But I never I've not used
that word in in how I lecture. But
that's exactly what makes sense to do
because contextual means in this
context. This is what I'm doing with
you. And the synergy between feeling
that on a sematic basis both
propreceptively and intraceptively and
they're connected but they're not the
same. Um
has a much greater um salience from a
sensory point of view and thus relevance
in terms of shifting behaviors.
Yeah, that's fascinating because in a
way um and I think we've all come to
this in different in different angles.
You know, I think um one of the things
that has frustrated me with with with
the profession that I've been most
associated with is chiropractic, but I
know it's also something in osteopathy.
uh I don't know much about bodywork and
massage but I I know that there are
similar conversations going on and and I
think there is something similar perhaps
in terms of physiootherapy as well and
and what I guess what I've seen through
the lens or the telescope even looking
at the wrong end of the telescope that
that I've seen is
um too much um uh body centric
explanatory frameworks. Now what's
really interesting about this discussion
we've just had here is and and I would
say that that Jakamo and I are probably
you know if you're going to look at a
spectrum sort of a cartisian spectrum
between mind and body with mind at one
end and body at the other um I guess
that Jakamo and I have become very
interested in the mind stuff and I know
that you know we've got some colleagues
George Estz and Mike Mikeer Mthaka that
will um that will very much be Steven
and Jim's end of the spectrum which is
which is very bodybased. Um but the
there's something about the
bodybasedness of certainly the
manipulative professions perhaps where
um you know there's almost a complete um
not a complete but you know a tendency
to sort of not worry so much about what
people are thinking and I think that's
that's why we've headed in well
certainly why I've headed in that
direction. On the other hand,
there's something about a body focus um
in a different way to finding a lesion.
I think the old traditional explanatory
frameworks are around, but you find a
lesion. It's very biomedical. Find the
lesion, you fix it, you get rid of it.
You know, if you're if you're a surgeon,
you take it out. If you're a manual
therapist, you fix the lesion in some
sort of way. But that's not the body
nest that you and Steven are talking
about. You're you're actually talking
about a very different bodiness. But
would you say that all of us are
actually trying to find some position in
the middle where we feel that we can get
these professions that get these
clinicians to just be more balanced
between these two things to get real
holism in a way.
I used to hate back back in the 70s and
80s the word holistic came into vogue
and I despised it because it quickly
became a mantra for selling all sorts of
snake oils and gadgets and gizmos.
I disagree with the question. It's not
mind or body. It's not it's not even
mind body or body mind. It's one
gestalt. It's one thing. I don't care
how much you're focused on and your your
mind. If I drop a brick on your toe,
your focus is going to change quickly.
And that's part of being human in a
momentby-moment basis. So from
clinicians
using that as le using using that
knowledge as leverage and making what
we're doing with them something that is
giving them agency that they can
understand in their in their language
that correlates moment by moment and
leaving them with a psychological
feeling of success of a positive a
positive response. So yeah I would agree
with agree with that.
>> Yeah Jim you had something to say and
then Jack thanks um thank you. Um I I
wanted to say that um I think that
probably for me at least the singular
contribution
of active inference which is also um I
point out in my talk and I go into it
very extensively uh Sharington's
original um his probably his greatest
achievement is his the model of life the
model a neurological he calls it the
neural architecture of the animal as a
whole the perceptual model of life that
is scalable and it's scalable from from
abstract systems like the Marov blanket
to the very intuitive example of the
cell to the vertebrae body and and um
and other kinds of systems but but it
certainly makes
Hi Daniel.
>> Yeah, it's
>> Daniel mute your mic.
>> Um, so um the model of life I think is
is a way to look at things. Uh so it's
three perceptual systems with three
different fields in the body. The outer
surface, the inner circus, internal
reception and then the core
propriception. all of which are minded
and embodied at the same time. And this
is just a different way of seeing
things. I think it's probably the single
um most exciting and powerful insight.
Um in addition to the notion of active
inference itself, a kind of a active
inference then takes the mind and the
body and brings them together. It's
active and inferential at the same time.
You can't break apart the sensory motor
loop, the perception action cycle. And
this is a real shift in thinking so that
that when we touch, we're touching a
person. We're we're touching a person in
different ways at different levels with
with boundaries set up within those
levels so that I can be touching you
more superficially or touching you more
deeply. I can be touched more
superficially and be touched more
deeply. I think it's an exciting massive
I think I think historically speaking
it's a civilization level paradigm
shift.
>> Yeah, I agree. I do agree. Yeah. Yeah.
No, thanks Jim Jack.
>> Yeah, Dave, I totally agree with you
regarding the challenge between body and
mind theory because we should also and
always consider that the things are
different if you you are living in the
lab or if you are living in the clinic.
So if you are living in the lab, you can
ask about
something related to the body or to the
mind. But if you are living in the real
life clinical practice and you interact
every day with a patient, you know well
that your life is composed by moment by
moment interaction where you apply some
tools that are related to your clinical
background and expertise such as manual
therapy exercises, physical therapy
agents and conccommittantly you modify
the context using different types of
touch for example modulating different
types types of verbal communication and
nonverbal communication in order to
synchronize your body and your person
with your patients in front of you. So
in this if you consider this real life
situation we should stop to oscillate
like a pendulum from one extremity to
the another but we should try to be
balanced
in order to strength both uh the
positive elements of the different
theories and in this sense I think that
active inference help us to have a
general framework that can help us to
explain what really happens in the
clinical practice. So I think that if
you are living in the clinical practice
you encounter different challenge every
day and the models the framework of
active inference can help you to
um give an interpretation of meaning of
what the patient uh present in terms of
pain dysfunctions
beliefs prior and try to challenge them.
>> No that's that's great. I um
one of the things that I I thought about
is you know that there is a sort of
rhetoric that goes with um you know an
integrative approach to whether we call
it holism whether we call it integrated
medicine or integrated approaches and it
feels to me that you know um like you
all of you have said in different ways
that active and I agree with Jim I think
it's a paradigm shifting idea um and of
course it's got a long history it's not
you know as as much as Carl has been the
sort of contemporary
uh horseman that's take this forward,
it's obviously come come all the way you
could say it goes all the way back to
Plato's cave and and and you know
for sure.
>> Yeah, exactly. But but the um so it's
interesting what you were saying Jim and
I think the
cuz you said everything is minded. I
like that phrase. And um it does that
speak to this sort of hierarchical
um models at all hierarchies? I know
that um Mick our colleague
um and uh I don't know what Carl and the
guys would think about this but I know
that there are other authors that have
suggested that you know their everything
or from cells upwards have a Markoff
blanket and they also have a model of
themselves and they act you know within
their own environment to confirm their
own existence by by by generating that
model and acting in such a way as to
keep that generative model going. So,
you know, it sort of gives the idea that
there is a sort of mind or a model at at
every level. And I guess what we're
doing we I guess we've got somewhat
interested in different levels of the
hierarchy of those models perhaps, you
know, we could say, you know, um we're
interested in prior because we're we're
interested in sort of high hierarchical
models of meaning and culture and what
this really means and but yet there are
all these models all the way down. I
think you actually talked about the core
being a being a sort of model of its own
that had its own markoff blanket and so
on and maybe if yeah maybe talk to that
and I know Stephen has got some similar
ideas as well so you know pitch in.
>> So I um I love that uh thank you for
that introduction. Um the thing that I
played around with um in my talk is the
idea of of a double blanket theory. Now
we know that there are two blankets. A
model has to have an internal model that
you know there are two blankets in the
model. But the inner blanket tends to be
um subsumed by by by just the
calculations of of of its parents and
and and um and siblings and stuff. And
and I don't know much about statistics.
I think it's fascinating, but I'm a
historian. Um
so what I the way I play around with it
is I I call it blanket politics
and the inner self has now
interosception is a little different.
It's a little more amorphous but the
propriioceptive it's a very concrete
sense selfidentity. It has very concrete
intentions and goals and a concrete view
of life that's different from the
externalceptive the outer blanket. The
inner blanket and the outer blanket of
course are integrated profoundly
integrated in terms of of
propriioceptive prior and exterceptive
you know sort of um maybe posteriors or
actions there there's no distinction but
at a certain level
um it's possible for there to be blanket
politics and I think we can talk about
that in terms of Fristston's dis uh
connection hypothesis but also I like to
think about it as a cultural theorist
in terms of um the double bind, Gregory
Bateson's double bind and from there
starting to really think about things
like like psychopathology and
schizophrenia. But the point being that
that
we really have different selves
and there are different agendas
involved. And if we're really too maybe
too internal, but that's rarely the
case, far too external, then that can
set up a kind of a um
a situation uh like the double bind that
I call blanket policies. I want to say
one thing about the relationship of the
mind and the body and just throw this
out there. For me, the relationship of
the mind and the body is like a rider
and the horse,
except that you're both the rider and
the horse. And the horse knows the
rider. The horse knows where to go. 2:00
in the afternoon, we're going up the
mountain trail to the spring. 11 in the
morning, he we're going downtown to go
shopping. And if that rider has a heart
attack or falls unconscious, the horse
is going to turn around and head right
back to the to the paddics um to get
fed. and and and the horse. So, the mind
knows the body, the body knows the mind.
As manual therapists, we're really not
fixing people. Of course, we are fixing
people. I fix people. But if we want to
really get um get into the semantics,
the body heals itself and the collective
body, the collective society also heals
itself. The point is how to get out of
top- down control and start to really
post. you know, when you post on a
horse, you get into the rhythm of that
caner and the whole thing works
smoothly. How do we really find that um
that connection with our patients
>> and enable and help and assist the body
to heal it? Sometimes there has to be an
excision, a surgical excision, but in
general, what we're trying to do is
really facilitate the self-healing
processes of the organism. Yeah, that I
what comes to mind is before I go on to
Stephen and then Jakob as well. Yeah.
>> Um that really what we're saying in is
in dysfunction of whatever that may be.
Whether it results in pain, whether it
results in um anger, whether it results
in um um anxiety, you know, whatever
that that there are lots of situations
where the body gets in the way of the
brain and the brain gets in the way of
the body and and in a sense, you know,
that what again it goes back to is there
some sort of way where, you know, using
your analogy where the horse and the
rider um notwithstanding that they are
one, but they actually start to function
as one. And then there's a and the
dysfunction is when they're not
functioning as one and they're sort of
getting in the way of each other.
Anyway, that that's a great idea. So,
Stephen,
>> yeah,
humans are unique in terms of the
hierarchies of complexity that we've
been talking about, which one of the
things that attracted me to complexity
theory because in the lab you learn
about lower animals, ants, there's
earlier today and the truths of those
things up to the mammals are truths for
life. But humans have a number of
uniquenesses both on a biomechanical as
well as a cognitive uh uh framework that
both interact to connect mind and body.
We're the first creature on earth to ask
what is it mind or body. No other
creature has posed a question. with the
first creature on on earth to have to be
an oblate biped that is a mammal. Birds
are oblate bipeds but they fly. Our
superpower is cognition and thinking
about things and being able to have
choice. So in the rider or the horse,
the rider is the only one that can say
you know what um I just remembered
something. Someone asked me to do
something. I forgot about that. Let me
go back and and and change directions
where the horse will keep on following
that pattern. And for most of our lives,
we keep on following the path that we
followed before. And that's one of the
challenges with any kind of rehab jakamo
with with patient compliance that we all
know about. And that's why from an
active inference point of view, getting
to people in the moment is where there's
so much leverage. What everything that
that you said is make is being present
with them and relevant to them which
means addressing what they're perceiving
with what you're doing and having that
affect what they're perceiving and
building a virtuous spiral to take this
to a whole different level.
And when you look at it from even
another point from a overall wellness
besides a pain point of view, all the
quadripeds their their locomotion and
their diaphragmatic function are linked.
And when they're breathing and and
living, they are breathing in the same
sink. Humans are different. We've
disconnected our breathing. Moreover,
we're the only creature that can
intentionally I'm going to stop
breathing and hold my breath. Other
animals don't have that as a voluitional
and we've used that ability to control
and then modulate to develop language
and language has become everything else
that we've done from a cognitive point
of view. So I I think that beginning
with the fact that we're getting
vertical and vertical but the first leg
that we talk about is postural balance.
It's not just posture. If I'm standing
here like this, what looks crooked may
appear crooked, but an overall
biomechanical level, it is physically
balancing from a biomechanics point of
view and from a headsp space point of
view. Your posture is how you balance
both your body and your mind.
>> Yeah. No, that's great. Jakamo, did you
have anything to to to add to that segue
outwards, which is entirely my fault. I
do apologize.
>> No, no problem. I was thinking about a
previous conversation regarding the rule
of touch and as a clinician I'm thinking
that for example when you decide to
apply a therapeutic amotherapy
techniques for example and you are
informed by evidence that you can
modulate short and medium terms the
therapiotic outcomes you have a tools
but active inference help you to explain
how to apply it if you want to have an
impact in term of patient interceptions
for example
When you decide to apply a manual
therapy techniques and you use for
example a very hard pressures, if you
are not in a moment synchronized with
your patient, you and you are not aware,
you are not in a listening phase, you
can adapt, you cannot adapt the touch.
So it's a a very it's a fundamental step
because you have a powerful tool but if
you if you apply it in a painful way to
your patient there is a risk to have a
worse outcomes.
>> So you need to modulate the touch in
order to get the positive outcomes and
you can do it only if you are
synchronized with your patients.
>> So this is a dance.
>> Yeah it's a dance. It's fundamental. If
you want to change and try to challenge
the prior of the patients, you be at
first be synchronized with your patient
in connections.
So would you say
>> yeah go on go on go.
>> Yeah that's great. So would you say I
mean the question a rhetorical one um
you know how do we stop some hardedged
um scientific u manual therapists have
been doing this for years. How do we
stop what we're talking about just
sounding like new age woo that that is
one of the problems here obviously we
don't think like that but I mean in a
way our talk about dancing about holism
about you know horses and riders and
whatever do you think that it is that is
the role in a way of this framework that
the active inference framework is is
something that is entirely
>> scientific it's we'll talk about
empirical evidence in a moment when we
finish but But that that stops it, you
know, um feeling as if we're sort of we
we're being very woolly because actually
isn't woolly whatsoever, Jim.
>> Yeah. I I want to say that it is woo
woo.
>> It is woo woo.
>> Yes. And that's very important. And so
there's two fields in the model. There
is the surface field and then there's
the deep field. Now the surface field
has language, volition, intention,
communication
and it has a kind of consciousness that
we associate this is who we are. um we
identify that as reality and the it's
the evidence that it produces is other
evidencing
and but there's another field and that
field is haptic
and that awareness is a haptic awareness
and haptic awareness in the deep core
doesn't have access to all of these
different um expressive mechanisms that
exterception does. It doesn't have
distance receptors. that doesn't have
language. It's a pure haptic or um
uh a touch sense that's generated. So
that's very important because the body
can go over here a little bit too far,
but that system is going to recalibrate
and reorient and establish and
reestablish stability and balance. It's
a very important function,
but it also has a form of consciousness
and awareness. We look down on it
because it's not verbal, visual, and
symbolic, but it is a form of
consciousness. And so when you walk into
a yoga studio,
you know, the first thing you establish
is epistemic trust,
uh, uh, a meditation,
>> we would call that therapeutic alliance,
wouldn't we, if you were in some other
clinical setting,
>> perhaps? but going just a little bit
deeper into that system and working in
that quiet field, that deep field. And
um there really is a kind of a
um the semantics are different in that
language. And I think one of the things
that active inference is doing is trying
to create a semantics or a sort of a
grammar and a vocabulary which you can
hear in Carl Fiston and others talking
that we ourselves are starting to
practice using that really expresses
that that innate active inferential
>> um potential that comes from the deep
field which is woo woo. And we need to
be able to affirm that
for what it is. It's the deep field. It
isn't the exterceptive field. But but
there needs to be kind of um balance and
integration uh between them. I think
that is a lot of evidencing work that
needs to be done for that.
>> Yeah. No, that's great. any before we
move on to something because I think we
we will wrap up and I just wanted to
wrap up with
>> um I think we got an hour so and I know
that Jack Jakamo's got to go so I just
wanted to to wrap up around that and
what do you think are the barriers that
that get in the way of active
potentially might get in the way of
active inference in our fields be you
know gaining traction or or perhaps not
just our fields but in in the scientific
community generally particularly around
anxieties around limited empirical
support for example and um you know
accusations of non-falsifiability
I know Jim has got something to say
about this because we talked earlier on
and I brought this up but I mean just
let's just go can we start with Steven
what what do you think do you think
there are there are a few hills to climb
here in terms of that that scientific
support
>> I think that we have more than the seven
hills of of of of Rome here. Uh there's
many different ways of climbing it. U
one of one of one of my efforts that to
correct you, I I I no longer practice.
I've not practiced since 200 2008 pretty
much. Uh but I've lectured and taught
and that's given me a a viewpoint of the
world and the professions. Um I um I I
spoke this morning about with um Tampa
General Hospital where we spoken to PTS
and OT's over there and I think Jakamo a
lot of the things you talk you've
mentioned before P OT's are doing as
much in the moment by moment more than
PTs more than chiropractors now in a lot
of the daily practice of what they're
doing. uh to to answer how it would look
differently. I'm speaking in two and a
half hours um about the paper that we
did in uh that was published in
frontiers of neuroscience intraceptive
posture pictures and taking a picture of
someone's body because posture is
important not pathologizing it not
making it a disease that I'm going to
fix cure but observing their perception
internally of what it feels like to
stand tall and capturing that in a
systematic way that you can do it with
an objective to be able to observe what
the body's
because I think that there's going to be
different techniques. I pref on a
personal point of view I may prefer more
active oasis technique and or light
massage or jakamo you might prefer light
m the other way around and there's
ultimate variations within all of these
sematics. Uh I I don't like wearing wear
wearing turtlenecks. It doesn't feel
good to me. You don't like wear it's not
a matter of what's right or wrong. It's
a matter of what works for that
individual. And your point I totally
agree with. We need to connect with that
person for their body, for their mind,
for their priors.
>> Yeah.
>> And moment by moment help to reshape
their perceptions towards their actions
and behaviors because otherwise it's
academic which is fun but it's not real
and that's the challenge.
>> Yeah. So, so there are many there are
many doors into the system at many
levels and and and you have to figure
out the particular door that you're
being faced with. So um yeah uh Jack and
then we'll end with end with Jim if
that's okay. Anything to say about your
worries about the uh empirical support
around this framework you know will it
will it just fade away and become like
you know the the ether hypothesis you
know back when and then discover that it
doesn't exist. I'm sure it won't. What
do you think?
I think there are different issues and
challenges up to now. For example, that
we don't have too much paper produced
convol involving patients with muscular
skial pain or chronic dysfunctions and
this is an issues that we hope that
evidence will cover in the futures.
Another issues is related to the lack of
knowledge
of clinicians and researchers. If you
don't know it, how can you use it? How
can you investigate it? And the third
possible issues is the bias of
the try to defend themsel using the
previous frameworks and asking
themselves why should I update my way of
thinking, way of way of acting. But we
know that uh science is growing and
networking share different perspective
and try to see the the things from a
different uh point of view. So I think
that the model is really interesting but
now what we should do is to move a step
forward inform evidence producing
literature and also inform clinicians
with some tools and also some
suggestions in order to help them to
apply this and integrate the model in
their clinical practice.
>> Brilliant.
>> We have a great opportunity and
responsibility but we should move it
forward. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, agree. And I think I
think all of us in our own way are
trying to do that. Jim, I'm gonna give
the sort of semi last word for you and
and then we'll we'll finish up. I I mean
I think um I think in terms of active
the active influence community so long
as it remains heavily exterceptively
biased it's going to continue to to be
kind of insular and and and um there
there are going to be major gaps in in
in the theorization. I think that um the
impact that active inference ha can have
on the clinical environment, the
clinical experience
is not different than the impact that
complexity theory is having the
biocschosocial model and also the
structural model of the body. This is a
major revolution. This together with the
active inference the a civilization
level paradigm shift is very
multifaceted and there is a cultural
expression of it as well in movement
movement but the um understanding of the
body as an integrated whole I think the
most important single discovery in
anatomy is the rediscovery of the
fascial matrix and understanding how
isolated muscularkeeletal disorders are
part of a a a of a global model, a a
structural uh system. And this is
something basic to what structural body
workers do. And the book behind me is um
a really great source of this kind of
new synergistic or I would even say
cybernetic anatomy.
That's just a new revolution that hasn't
been developed. Just like active
inference itself, much of the terrain
has not been mapped experientially.
And so I think that we're really um we
really are um at the very beginning of
something that's quite exciting.
>> Yeah. No, I I would agree. Um Daniel has
been very kind and just ask us one
question. I I I know Jakamo has to go.
Um well, maybe I could just ask this
question to you very quickly, Jakamo.
Um, and I think we've sort of answered
it to some extent, but if you can think
of anything else, but he says, uh, you
know, how would the encounter setting
look different? Um, in what ways would
this be technical, algorithmic,
educational? Certainly, education
interests both of us, Jack, I think that
would be something we would say would be
would be important. But, um, any any
insights just very quickly into that
question?
I think that active inference help us to
apply what we just know. For example, in
terms of contextual factors, we know
that we should use verbal and nonverbal
communication and the use for example of
therapeutic touch. But using this new
framework, we can decide how to apply
it. But this strategy
arise from a stepto-step evaluation, one
moment to one moment evaluation. So I'm
interacting with the patients. If I
notice a particular
anxiety, I try to modulate it using a
verbal communication that is not a rigid
way of interact but it can change and
can be modified and modulated on the
base of patients response. This is an
example.
>> Okay. So, so perhaps one way to to to
sum that up is that although clinicians
are already dancing with patients to
some extent that they they could dance
better um and uh and you know perhaps be
as responsive to the person standing in
front of them as as as how they feel
they should be moving their uh their
feet as well in this thing. May maybe
you know if you can think of the most
complicated dance to do maybe that's
what clinicians could do better. Jim,
one last thing, Jim, and then we'll have
to go. A
>> terribly quick little point. I'm just
looking at the little chat. Um, in what
ways would this be this change of the
clinical environment be technical,
algorithmic, educational, etc. I want to
add the word somatic,
>> right?
>> And I think the somatics is really the
um the the the area for pioneering right
now. Um, and in all that that means on a
very profound level.
>> Brilliant. Fantastic. Daniel, are you
there?
>> Yep.
>> So, I think I think we're done. Um, that
that was real fun. Thank you so much for
that question. I think we've been uh
we've enjoyed it. I think I think uh
this sort of stays up on YouTube anyway,
doesn't it? So, maybe people will still
have a chance to watch this um beyond
this this live session. Is that correct?
>> Absolutely. Same URL.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Thank you so much for the opportunity.
Right.
>> Yeah, really fantastic opportunity and
and thank you for our um uh our somewhat
holistic way of approaching this and uh
um uh and uh yeah, I think we all really
enjoyed that. So hopefully people will
enjoy that in the future. Thanks so
much, Daniel.
>> Thank you. Bye.
>> Thank you, Daniel.
>> All right. Bye.
All right,
next up is going to be a pre-recorded
video by Sonia De Jagger and the title
is
going to be described in the video. So,
20-minute video by Sonia. Here we go.
Hello.
The title of this presentation is active
self-referencing.
The concept of self-reference might be
that which joins complex self-modeling
with reference problems in formal
languages across a spectrum.
And
before beginning, I want to thank Chana
Dobson for the conversations that we had
leading up to this. Unfortunately, she
cannot join this presentation. That was
the original plan. So what I will be
showing are a series of speculative
proposals
uh slightly all over the place
but uh hopefully interesting
um and in keeping in line with the theme
of the presentation. There will be no
referencing to other authors and
sources.
Um these are tacit in the background and
hopefully if you are interested enough
and you would like to know more about
this you can reach out to me um and
perhaps later on to myself and Shana as
well. uh we will try to write this paper
for which she was going to cover uh some
of the mathematical aspects that we were
interesting interested sorry in
exploring.
Having said that let's move on to the
presentation.
So in the context of thinking ourselves
as predictive
actively inferential
organic creatures,
we can understand reference
as shared models encoding possibilities
for action. Anything that gives us any
kind of information is capable of
orienting ourselves uh in a specific
direction.
So all linguistic, logical etc.
reference are inherently ambiguous.
We need to actively infer.
reference require context for
concretization
or else they remain unactualized plans,
imaginations, memories, whatever we want
to call them depending on the context.
And this becomes very important when
we're going to well if we're going to
think about self- reference because
in a lot of the situations during which
we can contemplate self-reference there
is a sort of suspension of um action as
we will as we will see.
So simple reference with relatively
easily concretizable possibility spaces
such as let's say the reference cat
are I would dare to say obviously less
computationally challenging than complex
ones such as negation for example or the
concept of reference itself.
Here we can think about
situations that we have um decided to
nominate as paradoxes, contradictions.
Um and in some contexts I have really
stretched
uh the boundaries of this sort of
conceptual space and and um included all
sorts of um problematic toological
statements and and situations during
which things have to somehow return to a
let's call it a set point for now. Um
all of these phenomena are cognitively
challenging reference moments during
which bifurcations during which
information can be created during which
something can be contemplated and
possibilities for action become
possible. Um these are indeed moments
during which we are challenged by the
problem of reference because as things
uh need to actualize themselves when
there is no immediately apparent
possibility for action things get rather
tricky.
Of course, we can think about this
rather
well-known situation where we have
a statement which refers to itself
and in many different ways but also in
one simple way contradicts itself in
what it is stating. Um, its
actualization is rather awkward or its
actualization isn't. We could say
so here we have this pointing to the
sentence
this sentence what we are pointing at
what we are referring to is what follows
after this.
So this when we're looking at this this
right now this is what is true now
as we move forward because we are
inclined to do so reading is something
that kind of happens before our very
eyes once we are able to read we cannot
but not read almost
uh this points to the sentence this is
true now this sentence is true now or
sentence is true now and Now this is
true the fact that it is a lie. So what
just happened actually in many ways did
not actually happen. It did not
get actualized but it is actualized
before our very eyes. So what is
happening here?
We can also just simplify this and we
could go down many routes.
Um but we could just simply remove the
sentence bit of course and just
understand that this is something that
says that it is not this is a lie and
that is a problem.
One of the problems of ambiguity and uh
sort of the actualization of
possibilities and statements is that
this goes all over the place. Of course,
different types of contexts will lead us
in different directions depending on
what it is that we are
uh
depending on the context in which we
find ourselves. So obviously all
reference as mentioned earlier are
ambiguous. Everything requires context
for disambiguation.
And in the space of sort of in the
metacognitive space of thinking
rather abstract future possibilities, um
these things of actualization versus
nonactualization become confusing for
the actively inferential agent
again. So this situation is
contradictory by being what it is
because the future as we know affords
possibilities which we can sometimes
calculate as probabilities sometimes.
So what is remarkable in an active
inference context is this predictive
challenge right that we encounter when
we enter these self-referential loops
when reference kind of models reference
itself when we have to say something
about the very
sort of fulcrum the very the very
substrate which is enabling
um the capacity to witness possibility.
So reference and this kind of sort of
metacognitive capacity to self-reference
or of self- reference is an incredibly
powerful device for witnessing and or
creating
new information. This is the discovery
versus invention challenge which if we
are given to entropy as we know it is or
can be conceptually collapsed as one
phenomenon which is the inevitable
recombination that we are given to of
systems stacking upon systems
um which we can only understand in terms
of uh how they orient themselves towards
something. That is how they you know uh
minimize uncertainty for themselves and
remain being what they are through these
aforementioned
reference processes as a minimal
condition.
So what predictive function does
self-reference serve?
What are we what are we arriving at when
we are able to witness this? What is it
that that that we are doing when we
engage in the witnessing of
of reference
as as that which enables the very
witnessing, right? Is it a foundational
feature of selfmodeling or is it a side
effect that we kind of inevitably
developed because of the capacity to
to actively infer to sort of be in a
situation and need to experience moving
on to a new situation.
So again well as we were thinking about
it this this
would amount to the proposal that um
kind of basic self-reference is a
prerequisite for selfhood where selfhood
emerges gradually evolutionarily uh
developmentally
through the self-s surveilling and
synthetizing of one's own information
processing.
And this is what becomes confusing or
contradictory in formal contexts again
in sort of purely witnessing contexts
that do not yet actualize.
For example, when arithmetic says
something about itself
because being the creatures that we are,
we did not always have
reference. Uh it could be
could be speculated
because well in general we are used to
self-reference being an information
creating endeavor. We inevitably
actively infer ourselves towards
something always there is always
orientation. Um whether we are highly
aware of it and have very um
concrete mapping of what it is that we
wish to follow or whether uh we are
simply let's say
uh inevitably given to whatever
actualizes itself before our very eyes
for us because we continue to exist.
So when something is incapable of
stabilizing the informatic result that
we usually expect from referential
exchanges, no inferring is is possible.
No action is possible.
But what can also be said under
speculative investigation here is
therefore the concept of self-reference
as that which enables exity uniqueness
because it creates information and in
general given to language as we are most
linguistic
um or communicative phenomena in general
are representable as as reference within
shared generative models. There is
always the expectation
whether
um I mean there are many ways in which
this could be said but
because language exists between
creatures and we expect that meanings
are you know relatively shared u
reference often point to more or less
um the same thing.
The actualization of things even if we
cannot parse it ourselves is happening
elsewhere. That is always the
expectation. That is what language is
sort of doing for us. But reference
itself. So the substrate that enables
this linguistic modeling cannot be
modeled as a reference within its own
system of course and this is much like
the self which remains computationally
intransparent to itself. A thing cannot
fully account for its entire structure.
That's uh quite a simple and at the same
time incredibly
complex thing to realize
the loop that is then created.
What is what is this this this loop of
self-reference and sort of something
being able to maintain itself as a thing
that has to check itself
um for existence permanently pretty
much. This is sustained by agents first
modeling themselves as agents of course
to effectively act but this is always
incomplete and and um
well complex in many ways as as has been
mentioned.
So framing it as such self-reference can
therefore be interpreted as the process
of representation of thisness or
individuation hexity a thing becoming
aware of its capacity to act. So act
uniquely creating information each time.
It's sort of the the
what what we can hang on to, what we can
um understand as remaining the same in
the face of
um eternal
unpredictability unfolding before our
very eyes. We need to hang on to
something and that something is
the self of course and that is sustained
by the self being able to check itself
for existence.
Um that's sort of self-referential thing
that that anything that is that we can
call conscious uh and in many cases and
capable also of metacognition
um
that is that is what we are doing and
when that function is not performed
because we enter
uh other
hierarchies of stacking reference upon
reference upon reference.
uh we enter loops where it doesn't seem
as if we can create or we can witness
novel information. So the sentence is a
lie for example that is either we can
contemplate that as something that is
creating a lot of new information
because it's creating this sort of back
and forth paradox where we need to go um
back to the beginning
to the end back to the beginning to the
end uh in order to understand what it is
or try to understand what it is that
that thing is doing. Um but there is a
kind of symmetry that doesn't work for
us for predictive purposes there. So
um we we kind of witness these formal
tensions and there is no active
information giving resolution um in this
sort of self-referential self proposal
that we usually witness as being capable
of giving noble information because we
are given to uncertainty.
So maintaining this recursive process um
sustains the experience of continuity
through memory and planning which cannot
be symmetrical um but can be intertwined
through through reference points. These
are the things that we hang on to again
for uh sanity
and for all cognitive systems lived
experience necessarily involves the
continuous rehearsal of self-predictions
as already mentioned and the permanent
updating hereof and again as already
mentioned this becomes extremely complex
uncertain um if not unmappable and
literally unmappable in dynamic communic
in the in a dynamic communicative
landscape where we rely on others
self-re others self-reerential processes
not only their selfhood let's say but
also processes which depend on specific
set points um and and sort of
formalizations
in the hierarchical systems that we are
a part of.
So
a self model which is capable of self-
reference as linguistic communicative
capacities updates all the time its
predictive self-referential tension with
itself which creates new information and
this effect is mirrored in the larger
communicative landscape through other
processes of self-reference.
So because we wi we experience this we
also witness it as happening in examples
such as this sentence is a lie or as I
like to formulate it often this lie is a
sentence which um I would be happy to
talk about but there is not uh time for
doing that here today
and of course this has implications for
understanding metacognitive prediction
limits and the emergence of perspective
and selfhood in in all actively inferial
agents
because what I think I would like to say
here is that
the reliance on the idea that things are
actualized elsewhere. We might not be um
let's say capable of witnessing what um
our neighbor says about an event that
happened when we were not there.
But we are able to understand that as
having happened or something which might
happen. So the mere idea that
actualization is possible and that this
is actually what language gives us the
sort of representation of possibility
through a shared uh linguistic uh niche.
Um that enters a very strange new domain
when we uh create well new new language
systems, new formal systems which
actually take reference elsewhere and do
something entirely different with it.
I hope that was not too convoluted. Um
these are all
work in progress thoughts and uh things
very much at the edge of what a brain
can afford. Uh and again as mentioned
thank you very much to Shana for the
conversations that we had leading up to
this and uh it would be really cool if
in the future we can um finish this
paper with uh with my half which is what
I just presented here and then her half
which would be uh some mathematical
aspects of uh of considering this.
Um, thank you very much and especially
to Daniel who holds all of this
together. Um, and to the active
inference community.
That's it. Thank you.
All right, next up is going to be a
quick 5 minute lightning talk by John
Clippinger. Here we go.
Hello, my name is John Clippinger. Uh,
in this lightning talk, I would like to
talk about the end of extractive
economics. and arbitrage towards a
holistic economics through adaptive
inference, value creation, and
verification. So, there's some big ideas
I'm going to be throwing out here. Um,
and it'd be difficult to get them all in
in a really coherent way in 5 minutes,
but I am building on an earlier
presentation called aic finance uh
active inference and dynamic portfolio
management that you can look at that
provides the fundamentals for this. But
what I'd like to do is really sort of
get these ideas quickly out there um
towards a new kind of economic system,
the whole new kind of economic
framework. Um it's one that that really
goes from looking at different opinions
of of arbitrage and establishing markets
and bidden ass um towards uh a
measurable uncertainty reduction uh
rather than speculative opinion and
combining basian inference um and
thermodynamic accounting and multi-agent
coordination. It proposes a verifiable
and adaptive energy efficient
architecture financial systems capable
of aligning real capital with real world
outcomes. So what's the problem that
we're trying to solve here? And it's
sort of fundamental to everyday
economics and finance and that is that
you establish value through bid and ass.
So it's what people are willing to pay
versus what they're willing to buy for.
What's the spread? What's the difference
in opinion? So prices are really tied to
differences opinion. is not some kind of
underlying objective measure and these
can be manipulated because there's real
incentive to to create spreads in order
to make the
difference in the margins of value. Um
and so there's an intentional
information asymmetry that's always been
exploited. So liquidity is not
necessarily equal to value. I mean you
manage liquidity. You've got to create
liquidity in order to create markets and
you can change and manipulate liquidity
by through interest rates. But these are
just ways of adjusting it within the
context of different kinds of opinions.
Not saying there's any underlying
principle of assigning value there. And
what it does is it creates an incentive
to manipulate value and hence you get
bubbles and you get rug poles and you
get a lot of the problems that we have
right now with current markets. So what
we're arguing for is core replacement.
Price is the capacity to reduce
uncertainty for a unit per unit of
energy. So you use active inference to
treats every agent as a system that
spends energy reduce predictive error
around targeted outcomes.
We then price the asset by the expected
reduction and uncertainty normalized by
energy and capital used. Now these ideas
are pretty radical in the context of
current economics but they're not as
radical as you might think because when
the interest rate swaps when you have
fixed rates versus variable rates or
floating rates there's something called
the basically so far which is secured
overnight financing rates which is a
broad basic measure of the cost of
borrowing cash overnight backed by
collateralized by US treasury. So there
is this this mechanism that allows you
to exchange things of different kinds of
value proposition in order by virtue of
the standard and now this is set by
regulation but we're arguing that this
can be set by basically a scientific
method of assigning a val around energy
prediction reduction and information
reduction. So it creates a way of
incentivizing markets. If you look at
markets as markoff blankets, basically
markoff blankets of nested agents,
they're trying to synchronize around a
common outcome that minimizes
uncertainty and aligns them all around a
common outcome and stabilizes it. So you
can create have a welfare index. who can
have some kind of outcome or set of KPIs
around a project that allow different
players in a marketplace to get the
signals the signals they want in order
to achieve a shared outcome that is
beneficial to all. So this is the
holistic notion of a markets. We're not
it's not adversarial. It's cooperative.
It's alignment of interest. A multiscale
alignment. And you really have
posteriors as prices. Each agent
published a verifiable posterior. Each
dollar jewel reduces x units of of
uncertainty around a a desired outcome.
Settlement by evidence. Basically
self-synchronization.
Now what this does is is obiate the need
for the fundamental on market mechanisms
like bid and ask liquidity pools. So you
have decentralized exchanges. You have
monetary policy which is adverse to
fiscal policy. This combines them all in
a new kind of metric that is very
powerful. So if you're interested in
this, please give me a note. I'm at uh
johnfirst principlesfirst.ai.
That's fp1.ai.
Thank you.
We're back with entropic motivation, a
panel discussion. Alex Kefir will
facilitate and share some slides. Thank
you all for joining. Go for it, Alex.
>> Yeah, thanks. Thanks a lot for joining
me on very um looking forward to this
discussion a lot. Um, so yeah, since we
have an hour and these are like this is
like the deepest theme I can think of to
discuss. Um, I didn't want to spend a
lot of time on on introductions. Um, but
just really briefly for people who are
who are following this. Um, so I'm Alex
Kefir. Um, we've I'm really thrilled
that everyone has decided to join uh
today's panel. Uh we've got Daniel
Palani who again I'm not going to give
lengthy introductions here but um Daniel
of course has developed the empowerment
framework for understanding u motivation
and agents. Um Roirez Ruiz has worked on
the maximum occupancy principle uh which
we'll discuss today as well. Um Adam
Saffron is um I I think of Adam as like
a active inference and like physics
inspired machine learning kind of
generalist but I also just love
discussing philosophical topics with
Adam. Uh similarly for for Dalton um
Dalton has also done some work on well
you all know Dalton uh here but uh on
the free energy principle developing
some of the mathematical foundations and
also with a particular emphasis on its
relation to um things like maximum
entropy and maximum caliber so obviously
relevant here um and Sander uh Venda Cro
uh some some of you have only met over
text so I apologize if I didn't
pronounce things correctly but um Sander
is a psychologist who works in the um
predictive processing kind of actor
inference space as well and um I
recently came across some of his
writings. There's a great blog called
there is no reward. Um so I thought that
each person here would would make a
great contribution to this discussion.
Um so I wanted to just say a couple of
introductory things and then we'll move
away from slides and just get into a
discussion. Um so the overall theme here
in my mind anyway is um what role the
question is what role does entropy in
particular like the maximization of
entropy under constraints as we'll talk
about but like what role does this play
an intrinsic motivation so you know
entropy is one of the probably most
uttered words in cognitive science in
this uh you know uh 20 certainly 21st
century um so you can define it many
ways but basically I just mean the you
can Think of it as the average surprise
or um the spread of a probability
distribution or the amount of
uncertainty associated with the
distribution. Um and of course it has a
thermodynamic meaning as well and we may
get to that. Um and by intrinsic
motivation I mean really this is just
about motivation but I'm I'm just to try
to focus ideas um there are many ways of
thinking about how creatures you know
artificial and biological or natural
naturally um arising might be u
motivated and intrinsic motivation again
many ways to define that but I think of
it as just kind of separating trying to
isolate or distill or understand aspects
of motivation that don't boil down to
like the kind of thing that's modeled in
very vanilla reinforcement learning. So
that might be a straw man, right? But I
mean there just like learning sort of to
pursue some uh reward or like learning
associations between certain actions and
reward. So um the question here to for
me at bottom the question here is like
is there a an aspect of motivation in
intelligent agents and living agents um
that that doesn't just boil down to to
reward seeking behavior? And that also
might might encompass things like um
fitness in the in the context of natural
selection. So we'll talk more about
that. But um I wanted to get right into
some questions here. Um so and please
feel free to interrupt by the way. Um
yeah uh yeah so so as I mentioned um I
think one useful lens on this which has
featured in my recent work is to think
of um to look at the connections between
particular accounts of what intrinsic
motivation amounts to um and how it
might be related to the idea of
constrained entropy maximization which
is important in a number of ways in
cognitive science and in physics. Um but
so I I recently have been looking at
these three frameworks, empowerment,
active inference, and the maximum
occupancy principle. So, um, Daniel,
since you've joined us here, um, I won't
ask for a general introduction to
empowerment, but I wonder if you'd want
to say just a few words about what what
empowerment is, like what it means
formally and and how it um how it
relates to how you think of it relating
to um
motivation in agents.
>> Okay. So the basic definition of
empowerment is
essentially it's a measure of the
potential information that an agent can
inject into the environment by its
actions and pick up later by its
sensors. And it has multiple
interpretations. There are many
converging ways of looking at that. One
ways to look it is to maximize the
um possible choices that the agent could
have
in choosing its future that it can
distinguish itself. So it's not just
able to choose different futures but it
must be also able to distinguish it
itself that these different futures have
been chosen. So the the idea is
basically that if you're in a situation
where you have more choices, you are
more likely to be let's call it
vitality. It's a it's a way of of
maximizing your vitality, maximizing
your options to run away from death,
which is zero empowerment. Um there's an
interpretation in terms of evolutionary
niche that your sensory motor niche mean
is if you have high empowerment, it's
well well matched where the actuators
and sensors are well matched. If they're
not well matched, you will try to match
them better. Um there are of course
other criteria like energy conservation
so on. But uh assuming you have a given
sensory motor equipment, you will try to
go somewhere where they are best matched
where what you do and what you can
distinguish um are maximally compatible.
Uh there's another control theoretic
interpretation. Basically it's combined
controllability observability measure
and there are many others. You can think
of it as mobility in games. If you look
at deterministic games you could look at
it money is a form of empowerment. It's
a potentiality. It's not what you
actually do. That's in a nutshell. Um,
of course there's much more one can say,
but just to give you a quick upshot what
empowerment tries to capture.
Oh, thank thank you so much. So, right,
so you can already see how a lot of
those things that you mentioned don't
just boil down to simply seeking reward
in a in a more basic sense. Um but so
obviously I want to open up more for
discussion but um I thought it would be
good to maybe since we have people who
are sort of representative of these of
these theories to sort of lay them out
first as as background. So um so so for
active inference um anyone who'd like to
jump in but but Dalton I think you you
partic in particular have done work on
again on sort of anticipating a bit um
pointing in the direction of of the sort
of duality between active inference and
um entropy maximization under
constraints. So would you want to we're
also at this implied active inference
symposium so it's not as if you really
have to introduce active inference but
would you like to say anything to frame
how you see these um these related being
related at this at this point?
>> Uh sure well I can say a couple of
things about um the particular view of
active inference that I think would be
most productive to take in these
discussions. Um one thing I want to to
point out immediately is uh when you
have uh an active inference agent uh you
are looking at something that uh looks
as if it has the policy of minimizing
expected free energy. So the actions
that it takes in order to maintain its
set points are uh appearing to minimize
expected free energy and and indeed if
you build an agent and code it up such
that it is an active inference agent
then you can do this explicitly by hand.
Um the interesting thing about the
expected free energy uh is that agents
that minimize expected free energy they
both pursue information gain and also
goal satisfaction. So there is a sort of
uh balance between some kind of
intrinsic drive or epistemic value uh
and also a reward-seeking exttrinsic
behavior. Uh and these are are bridged
in in one quantity. Uh this kind of um
on the face of it has a lot to do with
empowerment in the sense that it's it's
not simply exploitation.
Uh it has an exploration element. It's
it's saying also I want to learn as much
as possible about my environment uh so
that I can improve my future uh suite of
possible actions or possible
modifications of the environment. So I
want to explore in such a way that I can
eventually bring about an environment
that might be even better for the goals
that I want. Um as opposed to simply
preparing a state of the environment in
the goal that I currently want. Um
more broadly if you look at the free
energy principle itself uh this same
kind of dichotomy is there when you have
a complex system you have some kind of
typical behaviors some kind of uh states
for which the uh system is characterized
uh by which the system is characterized.
say these these characteristic states
are things that we think of as in humans
lielike states in control systems they
are the set points that make the control
system uh be the sort of thing that it
is. Uh but within that if you have a
system that remains organized for long
periods of time it needs to have some
kind of flexibility to respond to the
perturbations that it's receiving from
the environment. So a system that very
rigidly stays within a very small set of
characteristic states is actually not
very good at organizing uh because it is
very easily dispersed by changes in the
environment. So again there's a kind of
trade-off between maintaining a very
rigid uh set of of characteristic states
uh those are your sort of constraints uh
but also exploring within those
constraints what is possible and
reconfiguring as the system goes along.
Um, so I I think empowerment uh and
constraint maximum entropy have a lot to
do with each other in the way they treat
this balance between exploitation or
reward seeking kinds of behaviors and
exploration or uh dispersion kinds of
behaviors. They both allow a certain uh
flexibility within some kind of
confidence bar. Uh, and I' I've thought
a lot about this. Um, and I know Alex uh
and Daniel and others have thought a lot
about it. So, I'm interested to see what
insights come out of this panel.
>> Thank Thank you. Thank you, Delton. I've
been throughout both of these these um
sort of discussion introductions, I've
been nodding vigorously. I don't know if
people can see because we're looking at
the slides, but we'll go to the cameras
soon. Um, thanks. Uh so uh um Jorge
would you like to um introduce anything
about maximum occupancy in terms of the
um sort of yeah well just what what what
the framework says but also like um uh
what what its motivation is in this
context.
>> Sure. Um um yeah so I'd like to I think
it the maximum occupancy like uh fits
very well with what people have said in
and the theme of this um discussion uh
looks like the main motivation for this
uh work was to think of how people
usually think about like curiosity you
know um and exploration as you know
means to an end you know like uh
exploration is very good because then
you can uh reach higher rewards in the
long term by just exploring are in the
state space and action space. Um, so we
wanted to flip that around, you know,
because like uh reward functions are in
reinforcement learning for example are
like uh when you're engineering, you
know, is trying to uh have a robot do
something. Um, you have to really try to
engineer that reward function. Um, and
there's no real principle way to think
about where reward functions come from
other than what other people have said
before in the past like how reward
functions can be evolved and and so on
and so forth. But uh so we wanted to
turn that around and say well rewards
what uh organisms think about as rewards
are actually means to an end, right? And
and or should be more like means to an
end which you can think of many ways
like survival or whatever. But so we
wanted to develop some kind of objective
um that has the like minimal assumptions
you know um so we we came up with uh
this objective of maximum occupancy like
just from inspiration of the second law
of thermodynamics and Carl Fen has said
it before of how there's a duality of uh
like max path uh maximize path entropy
and and minimize entropy uh for the
organism. Um so yeah so it it it comes
with very well with this theme because
you know like just maximizing entropy
for example in this case maximizing the
future entropy of your actions and
states doesn't really make sense without
constraints right so it it just
maximizing entropy of your actions and
states is not an interesting thing to do
if you just random walk um all the time
um but when you actually think about
constraints of organisms that have
evolved then you have very interesting
things where they go go away from those
states that are uh as Daniel has said
like low empowered or in this case you
cannot access future action entropy and
state entropy in the future if you die
for example. So it has this survival
kind of instinct um trying to work with
its constraints to still maximize um
path entropy. Um
that's basically kind of the the
inspiration in what the maximum
occupancy is about. But um yeah, if you
have questions, uh yeah,
>> great. No, thank you. That's that's
wonderful again. Um so yeah, and I think
that that that kind of perspective that
maybe things could be flipped on their
head so that um these sort of curiosity
or novelty seeking um behaviors are in a
sense perhaps more fundamental than um
reward seeking uh is is a really
interesting idea that's that's I think
been a major inspiration for me in
wanting to do this. Um so before we we
move to sort of phase two of this um
which would be excuse me to consider
some specific questions although I don't
want to over constrain this because
there's there's um a lots to say um um I
guess Adam or Sander do you want to say
anything on the on sort of the over
overarching theme of intrinsic
motivation or any of this? Uh any
comments you'd like to make at this
point? Adam first maybe just
alphabetically.
[Music]
Uh, no comments at the moment. I'm just
enjoying the discussion.
>> Awesome. Um, yeah, Sandra,
>> you have a few comments. Um I I I I I
see some of the discussions that have
been like historically been taking place
in psychology and and whether like like
this need for cognition or stimulation
or exploration
what what place it has within the other
so-called basic more basic needs. This
is this is pretty interesting
um that I mean that um there's now with
this maximum entropy or with the
empowerment of maximum occupancy this
possibility to invert indeed that
picture and to to to not see the kind of
um knowledge drive or stimulation drive
or need for cognition as like the old
one now. something that is alien to the
the rest. But that is really front and
center of of of this picture. And that's
I think there's evidence in psychology,
but it's never I mean the the kind of
evolutionary basic drives have have
always been a dominant thing. So, and to
see that there's a framework that
framework that that doesn't deny that
picture but but that can make it more
rich is is for me very stimulating.
Yeah.
>> Awesome. Thank you. Uh I'm going to I
think
stop sharing slides now. Um so
um is this is this good? Can we all see
the cameras now or are we
Yep.
>> Okay, cool. Um, so yeah, so I did, you
know, there were some other just slides
with with little prompts and notes, but
I I think I'd rather have more of a
personal interaction as we do this if
possible. Um, so I I just wanted to go
through some some So there's a lot I
wanted to get to today. Um, but thanks
for for laying out the sort of um basic
um ideas and frameworks here. Um, so in
in compelling terms. Um so I had I had
three themes in mind to discuss and
again we can go as far off the rails as
we want. Um that's the entropy part of
the of the of the equation. Um but but
the first theme uh that I had written
down here was on sort of the degree to
which um these two aspects of in of
motivation. Okay. So intrinsic
motivation usually seeks something
that's not just reward in a conventional
sense but so we have rewarding behavior
or risk minimization and then everything
else. uh and the everything else um I
tend to want to um place under the
heading of maximizing entropy but I also
don't want to frontload that assumption
too much but um I guess the question is
to the extent that we have at least two
de dimensions of motiv motivation in
general that that fall out of many
different frameworks for understanding
motivation like uh is is one of them
more fundamental than the other and
we've already heard from a few people
who want to flip the conventional wisdom
on its head in a
and say that curiosity or entropy
seeking behavior is more fundamental. So
maybe we all agree on that. Who knows?
But I'm curious whether anyone has a a
view on that.
Um
I could call in particular people. I
feel like a Yeah. Yeah. Daniel, go ahead
please.
>> Um I would say from my perspective I
think the arbiter is evolution. So
in evolution there is no real thing like
reward. Reward is a fiction that we
employ to compute um behavior to compute
desirable behavior and it requires the
concept of utility which has a fulfill
number of axios which we know is not
that easy to get if you actually operate
with real beings, real organic beings,
human beings. we know that naive uh
utility theory doesn't perfectly work
there. Um so I would say ultimately what
you want to understand is how does the
concept of
seeming reward or seemingly reward
driven behavior emergent evolution. Um
concept of goals for example is also an
emergent concept in my opinion. It is
coming through the fact that certain
behaviors have to go through
bottlenecks. Like I'm not talking about
information bottlenecks here, just
behavioral bottlenecks. For example,
when you catch food, the food is
localized. So it is a bottleneck to
catch the food. Um it looks like a goal,
but the reality is if the food would be
all around you, you wouldn't care and
you would not it would not be a goal to
catch food. I I always give the example
this your tapeworm sits nice and warm
and is constantly flooded by food around
it. It doesn't the food acquisition
behavior is not a specific goal because
the environment is nutritious as it is.
And I do think that's what misleads us
as humans. We like to categorize things
but this is an emergent phenomenon. I
don't say it's not a real phenomenon but
it's emergent. It's not primary in my
opinion.
Thanks, Daniel. Um, so, so that's it's
I'm glad you brought up evolution. Um, I
think so, so I take your point that,
um, yeah, that reward is perhaps an
emergent concept or emergent notion. Um,
but I think I think one question that I
have here and I will I will not take too
much time. I I promise. One question I
have here which which informed this this
this idea of of having this panel is
that I I think in a broader sense like
ev if we take evolution to be sort of
producing variability and then selecting
according to some fitness function that
the fitness function has received a lot
of attention but the the producing of
variability is is is maybe the other
dimension of or aspect of this process.
Um, and that might have a lot of
structure or it might not, you know, I
mean there's Anyway, uh, so
do do does anyone else want to comment?
I was I curious. Yeah, I don't want to
over prompt people, but yeah. Yeah, I it
it reminds me of like the studies on
single cellled organisms that when
stressed that seem to upregulate their
mutation rates. So that that there's
just more bets made and and that seems
like a more random walk that that might
end in a lot of um yeah attrition but
but will also give like the necessary
structure for the future for the new
environment apparently. So is that what
you mean with the exploration and
evolution?
Um I sorry no please I mean I mean this
the increased stress right what it means
in my opinion evolutionarily it means
that you have a higher chance of dying
out and so um is basically a change
environment that um actually reduces
your vitality and to counteract it you
create just more options so that at
least one will survive right so you
don't do that when you're in a good
shape right you don't take risks when
when you're doing Well, you keep the
risks under control. You only take major
risks and vital risks um when when there
are many chances that you might not
succeed.
>> So I say
>> you can understand it from that.
>> Yeah. Sorry. Yes.
>> Yeah. No, sorry. Um just that in humans
it seems to be the reverse, right? When
we play or when children play, it's when
they're wellfed, when they're they don't
have stresses, when so it's reversible.
>> Sorry,
>> it's reversible. This is a reversible
risk. That's not really risk. It's just
free learning. Uh taking risks, um when
I when you say you increase mutation
rate, you take irreversible risks.
Basically, it's like having a a company
and the company is in a bad shape and
then you start taking bigger risks to
make it survive than you would do if
it's doing well.
>> Mhm.
>> But play play is different. Play is a is
a safe um it's actually an excellent
point. So reversible is important. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I see.
>> Cool.
I'm I'm curious whether so um I don't
know in what perhaps I'm reading into it
but uh in your work on maximum occupancy
I tend to think of of this as somehow
modeling
like the desire is to stay alive in a
way sort of for its own sake right it's
it's you want what you want is to be
alive and that is to occupy state action
space path space so I don't know if you
have
further comments that I might make.
>> Well, yeah. I mean, I think that in this
case, surv surviving is kind of a
consequence of trying to occupy your
future action and state paths. Um
because when when you die, you can't,
right? So, but it's not the primary
drive, let's say, of just surviving.
Like surviving is a very degenerate kind
of reward function, right? Like if you
survive, there's just so many ways to
survive. Um um but uh but when you are
actually doing some kind of maximum
entropy on actions and states in in the
future then you're you're encountering
some some you're you're you have very
minimal assumptions of what you can do
but you're constrained about those
things you can do. Um so um yeah so
that's kind of what I would say about
like survival but coming back a bit to
towards like what is kind of more
fundamental
um I think it would be more fundamental
with regards to what what you want to
achieve right um so like if you're if
you're an engineer um that wants to just
make robots that do stuff um you know
like uh if you can engineer could reward
function Um then you could say that you
know intrinsic those intrinsic
motivations that you give uh you could
give uh to robots um they serve the
function to um maximize work or in in
that case kind of intrinsic motivations
is not as is not the the driving thing.
U and and people you know have argued
that reward is enough. Uh but kind of
the idea of of maximum occupancy was
like well reward is not necessary. Um
and and I think that that the the the
what what we wanted to argue with this
work was that as Daniel has said like
rewards is kind of like an emerging
thing. Um it's something that makes you
want to achieve uh other something else.
uh and and in that sense um that kind of
extrinsic reward I mean um it's funny
cuz I like I we organized a workshop
about like intrinsic motivations in um
in this RLDM conference and and kind of
like what came up with it was like well
all rewards are intrinsic rewards and
and and in that way um I agree um but
like these rewards are kind of something
that has evolved over time to make you
achieve something else uh or to help you
achieve something else. Uh and so in
that way I would in that sense I would
argue how that um there's something
there should be something like a
principle um that makes you uh over time
or perhaps evolutionary time uh develop
this uh reward functions uh these
extrinsic rewards that people call um
Yeah.
>> Great. Yeah. Um
so so maybe a more a slightly more
focused way of asking this question is
um
so I mean in in a sense it's it's all
down to evolution but like um
curiosity for example like curiosity and
um like things like epistemic drives and
information seeking behavior um
with respect to that question like one
question I had is well Do we must we
view that as in the service of obtaining
something else? Now, I guess we've
problematized the notion of rewards
somewhat here, but like is is that sort
of information seeking always in the
service of obtaining some goal? Is it
always a means to an end or might it be
like a more fundamental aspect of what
drives life and agents? And I'm um that
that's that's
I I think under some guys I'm I'm I'm
tempted to suppose that there's
something fundamental about that this
other component of motivation, right? So
so there's the constraint, right? Then
there's the entropy maximization.
Um but so so um I I think Dalton maybe
I'll call on you here. um from from an
active infant perspective, it seems like
in a sense these two things are on a
equal footing at least
rather than everything being in the
service of risk minimization,
>> right? Um I I suspected I might be
called upon soon, so I I intended on
volunteering myself uh just in case. Um
before I answer that, I just want to
echo something uh that Daniel said uh
which was that I'm I'm very partial to
the view that uh reward is a useful
explanatory fiction. uh and in
particular I'm I'm quite partial to the
view from the free energy principle
where we say if a thing is
existing for long enough to be
observable to be modelable at all as
that thing then it must look as if it's
seeking environmental states conducive
to its continued existence and that that
appearance
uh gives the the impression of desire or
it gives the impression of some reward
some some goal seeking behavior. But if
you take something simple like
chemotaxis,
uh, something like a bacterium or an
amoeba, it one could argue it would be a
mistake to anthropomorphize that as
seeking reward as opposed to merely
following a gradient because if it
weren't following that gradient, it
wouldn't exist to be described at all.
um what is fundamental what is physical
is the maximization of entropy. So in in
the end uh even um the imposition of
constraints
is something that we do as a modeler. We
say here is a constraint that
phenomenologically describes our
observations. It gives us the right
answer. Um, but does that constraint
exist in reality? That really strongly
depends on what your sort of
metaphysical or ontological position is,
right? Um, so it it becomes a little bit
more subtle than than saying actually
that uh constraints exist as opposed to
there's something that that matter to us
as the modeler, right? Um,
so that that's sort of one component of
the answer. Uh the other component is um
it is often useful to describe agents uh
broadly construed as balancing both of
these things uh because
often times there is that impression of
reward-seeking behavior and when
engineering agents when building things
we may want to give them reward-seeking
behavior. Um so active inference is
telling a story where both of those
things are given uh equal um waiting
that they're they're regarded as uh
equal contenders in a competition. And
this proves to give very succinct very
explanatory descriptions of a lot of the
dynamics that we observe. Uh so if if
you're in the business of flipping the
story on its head and saying if there is
something to be observed for a long
enough period of time then it must be
somehow balancing preparing
a preferable environmental state with
exploring its options to decide uh what
could possibly be preferable. uh if
you're in the business of telling that
story, then active inference is a a very
useful way to tell that story because of
the way the two things are balanced. Uh
but I think it's a somewhat deeper
philosophical question whether all
systems or some systems or no systems
actually do this. Do they actually have
the policy of minimizing expected free
energy or is it a useful model of what
we observe as the dynamics of such
systems?
Yeah, thanks Dalton. Um,
I guess I have no problem sort of
unconsciously taking a realist stance on
that question, which is often a blind
spot I have. But, um, I think, okay, I
mean, but granted, it's a it's a good
point though. But so so regardless of of
how sort of much epistemic humility we
want to adopt about our models of
situation um it does seem it does seem
that well you've you've you've raised
the second major kind of question I
wanted to address which we'll see how
long we want to spend on it. Um I think
we're each of us in this panel is is is
um sort of immersed in the you know
thermodynamic descriptions of things to
different degrees but like um
the the second question I wanted to ask
is well what it's probably there's no
single simple relationship although I
would like there to be but what's the
relationship between these formalisms
which describe after all they're
describing sort of um objectives for
agents um and just entropy constrained
entry maximization, things like that in
the physical sense. So, um I don't know
that just asking the question in such a
flat way is going to be a good
conversation starter. But I mean,
Dalton, you brought up um
active inference agents look as though
they are um seeking to minimize free
energy, expected free energy in
particular. So um and actually so so let
me just just say something here. Um so I
think like in a sense if you think of
agents or um sort of inferial processes
like minimizing instantaneously
minimizing variational free energy
that's an easy that's it's a very easy
very clear illustration of this sort of
you know um minimize energy while
maximizing entropy because like in
Helmhold's free energy you have the the
energy which is the average internal
energy of the system minus the entropy
and so to minimize that free energy you
want to maximize the entropy right um or
minimize the energy um or both at once.
But so but in a lot of um these
frameworks, we're not really talking
about just that. We're talking about
policy selection. And like I know I mean
also I think this applies as well to
empowerment like Daniel. So you're
right, you think of empowerment as it's
not just
you want to choose it's it's an
objective for choosing states, right? So
that you maximize the sort of the
empowerment that you'll be in once
you'll have once you're in that state.
Um and so so neither of these things um
policy selection under expected free
energy as an objective or empowerment uh
bears a direct relationship I guess to
you know maximizing entropy in this
Helold's free energy sense like just
maximizing
the entropy of states under under
constraint directly in states. So I'm
wondering if there's anything to say.
Okay, the the overarching question
>> I mean empowerment is is can be used as
a surrogate for a utility function.
Okay. So um while it depends actually on
this this channel capacity it's a state
function and it's defined by the
pathways available from the state and
and how much you as an agent can
influence that. um free energy and other
models do depend also on distribution.
So there is a bit of more additional um
structure that they um have and it
probably models different things too. So
one of the things that we need to um uh
realize is that um empowerment people
always say oh we use it for exploration.
Exploration is incidental. It's not the
main thing that empowerment does. So
yes, sometimes it can lead to
exploration, but that's not um it's a
spin-off if you like. It's not its main
agenda that there are tools which are
explicitly explorative.
>> Mhm.
>> Right. Right. So, so one question I had
here is sort of
like of the various things that you
might pursue as an agent, uh,
exploration is one of them. Um,
empowerment I when when I when I try to
reduce it to a bullet point, I think of
it as based on things you've said, I
think of it as like
sort of maximizing the variety of
futures you can realize or something.
Um so that's obviously different from
conceptually from exploration
in terms of trying to get information
about things.
>> Exploration comes into play if you need
to develop your model. If you have your
model, there's no point in exploring
anything, right? So when you don't have
a model, exploration can increase your
epistemic uh empowerment. So empowerment
can change by what forward model you
have. So if you have a very detail
forward model, there's no nothing to
explore and you just maximize
empowerment straight. If you have a bad
epistemic model where you don't know
exactly what your actions will do,
there's an advantage for you to explore
what actually actions are going to do.
So empowerment will uh invite you into
exploring the states, but not just any
states, just the ones who are most
promising for maximizing your options in
the future. So, as I say, exploration
here is more side
quest rather than the main issue. Um,
which I don't think it's necessarily
bad. We we sometimes feel like um if
things are not primary, that's a bad
thing. But I I feel that evolution
doesn't care, right? In evolution, there
are lots of these side quests that turn
to the main quest. So, for example,
curiosity. I would for example speculate
and this is pure speculation that
curiosity might be a side quest um to
make higher organisms ready for changes
in the niche. Um so because curiosity is
dangerous. Curiosity killed the cat. The
reason why it's they say that but maybe
for higher organisms which are which
cannot compete by larger numbers um
where they're sensitive to to to
environment. It is a distinct survival
advantage to have curiosity in the
population on population level. On the
individual level, probably not. I don't
think that on individual level exploring
Antarctica is good for your offspring,
but on population level it might be.
Um,
>> if I could if I could add something just
before you move on. Um, I I do want to
uh note that I think it's interesting
Alex mentioned uh variability a little
earlier on. Uh, and it's interesting to
note that uh variability is itself a way
of increasing the capacity for side
quests. You know, you introduce a whole
bunch of different mutations and see
which ones persist, see which ones
increase fitness. So it gives you a kind
of test bed for other beneficial uh
things that are not simply about uh
increasing uh reproductive ability uh
but are maybe unexpected ways of of of
increasing the duration for which an
organism persists and the amount which
it can reproduce and pass on its genes.
Uh so there there's kind of a uh a link
between this discussion and the earlier
discussion which I found uh quite uh
compelling.
I I also wanted to um open if if that's
okay. Um just to to note perhaps I don't
know if it's kind of technical more but
um something I've I've noticed from both
empowerment and active inference um was
that this this idea uh that um if
there's you know if you have perfect
knowledge of the world let's say or your
model is very certain or whatever u and
there might be ways to keep you
exploring so that you're never like
converging but let's say that you do and
that you're learned both of these two
things kind of stay put forever, right?
And like you could say, well, the
environment is always changing so you
need to go back and like you know your
internal states change so you go back
and fulfill your model or you minimize
your surprise about your model. Still, I
feel like there's nothing fundamental
about exploration if if correct me if
I'm wrong in that sense of uh as Daniel
said, like it's a side quest to fulfill
those things, but it's it's it's like if
you converged, you stop and then that's
it. You leave your organism there. Um
and and so that's that's why I wanted to
like kind of contrast that to what we've
proposed which is like well no you keep
doing stuff as if you're allowed to kind
of thing. Um and and and in that sense
that kind of keep can give you more
robust robustness in your um
um in your organism or in your
artificial agent more in a fundamental
way. But uh but I yeah I I that's kind
of my question.
>> Yeah, Daniel, please go ahead.
>> Um I think this is a very good point. Um
the question is when is it okay to um
you know dry out in a in a given niche
or when not? And my claim would be the
following and this is this is purely
speculative here. uh that
the reason you want to continue
exploring when you found a good maximum
is because you have no idea what happens
to your environment. See, you sit on
somewhere and everything is fine,
everything is happy. Uh you and you live
in this this this perfect paradise and
you don't don't look around. What
happens is you lose information about
the neighboring states and in so in
other words in the language of
mathematics you become only point
oriented rather than neighborhood
oriented and I I believe that this is um
makes you very vulnerable if there is a
major change. So you will not be ready
for any major I have some examples but
they're bit too long to explain here but
essentially you're not ready for um
changes where the local environment
would actually tell you look something's
going to happen. uh but because you said
only on your point you never notice and
that's why I think uh we when we stand
as humans we never stand still we
constantly evaluate the ground
constantly
u and and anything we do has a certain
variability even the most perfect sports
people
they should just reproduce exactly what
they always do and they never do and I
it sounds like a like a bug but it seems
to be a feature of nature to never do
the same again.
>> Okay. Yeah, I like that. Um it sounds to
me though that it's like um it's an
emerging thing, right? So it it of like
Okay, it's just because you live in a
world where things change and things
have evolved to look for for other
things around. Um
perhaps it's an even empirical question.
I don't know to say like well if
actually you have a very very stable
environment do you have do you evolve
beings that do not export
>> I I actually claim you stop evolving and
we have examples for that and um there
are frog species which are so
specialized they require very specific
setup to continue um you disrupt the
environment a bit and they're finished
right um and you see this in nature but
Mostly you don't because in large scale
echo webs um you don't have the
stability. It's always something that
intrudes your in your world. But you can
see that in economy too, right? An
economy that is relied oh we always
relied on the same things working fine
and suddenly something major there's a
major change um that happens. You now
have the problem um you're not ready. So
um bubbling um as I think Adam said
bubbling is the right thing to do
constantly to some level. You don't want
to waste too much on it but you have to
keep doing it. There's an advantage to
that.
This this is this is very interesting
because my one of my intuitions here is
that it just sounds like it sounds as
though there needs to be a reason for
this this babbling. And of course it's
very useful but but I I guess I I wonder
whether just being alive like that's it
is babbling like that's that's the
fundamental thing. So there's always you
know if you planned and you can always
you can have these goals that pull you
from the imagined future but then
there's also something that just pushes
from behind right which is sort of the
essence of like being alive and I I I
guess I want to link those two things
but they are quite different. planning
to stay alive, right? Planning to
maximize entropy on infinite time
horizon is still quite a different thing
from just doing stuff.
Um,
>> I don't think you randomly bubble
babble, right? I mean, one of the
problems with with many exploration
strategies is they are um
undirected. You you don't care about
knowing what the lint under your your
bed is doing. you most of the time
you're not interested in that there
specific things you're curious about.
>> This this is true. Um so well okay that
sort of conveniently brings me to one
question I had was this this sounds it's
a funny thought but like is is there any
reason to think that so evolution is
quite a general concept of course right
it happens at different scales but like
evolution on the phoggenetic time scale
how you usually think of it. Um is there
any reason to think of it as having some
kind of curiosity component? Um
exploring state space um you know in the
similar sense to how an individual might
I mean maybe that last thing makes it is
is not helpful. You were nodding earlier
Daniel. Um
so I mean you could think of that you
know from the point of view of like
multiscale active inference like oh
nested agents all the way up and down
but um that's a very thin sense of agent
um but um
I mean it so I I think I was reading a
article by um Terrence Deacon and he
mentioned sort of um
something about
Anyway, something about the fact that
evolution is driven by I mean this is
just obvious evolution is driven by sort
of variation.
Uh so
you know if you're implementing a
genetic algorithm the obvious thing is
you need the fitness function and you
need the modification functions. Um so
it's it's it's just sort of a question
about whether and I mean Delta maybe
you'd say this is a matter of how you
model things but um if we're looking at
processes of evolution on the on on the
time scale of you know speciation and
things like that. Is there anything that
we could view as like a structured
process of exploration?
Anyway, it's a question
and um I don't have the answer. So,
I'll let that sit for a second while I
dig for
um well, if sorry, is any comments on
that? Adam, thanks, by the way, for
doing some chat jockey. you've been
quiet, but I really appreciate the what
you're adding to the chat.
Um,
if
I mean if
>> I mean I I can make a comment. I just
didn't want to hog the hog the panel.
Um,
evolution thinking of evolution as an
agent is a very interesting thing. It's
not an agent in the usual sense because
the interface is very vague and and and
distinct. But I do agree uh that yes
evolution has a way of learning has a
way of I think just recently I read a
paper that evolution does have a um
ability to improve its learning
mechanism. I would be surprised if it
doesn't do that. Um we know that Lensk's
experiments are a nice example of
pre-structuring
um evolvability pathways.
um this long-term experiment that he did
I don't know 20 years ago I think it was
this paper uh really really nice paper
fantastic experiment
I do think that we we can think of
evolution in this as long as we don't
say oh it's an agent with clear membrane
creation or something we can think of it
as a kind of as a kind of
cur curious learning mechanism uh But we
also have to understand that evolution
unlike normal agents doesn't have that
constraint. It has to work under
constraints of physics and chemistry but
um energetically is quite unconstrained.
Number wise it's quite unconstrained. So
it can be generous with that.
>> That that makes sense to me. I mean well
thanks for thanks for partly so I'm not
I'm not crazy or both we're both crazy
or to to think this that there's some
there's
>> that's all right. Um so so there was one
more kind of big picture thing that I
wanted to get to today. We have about
less than 10 minutes left. Um and that
was just about rationality. So again,
we'll see if this sparks interest or
not, but um I think of I mean, so
rationality again has many senses, but
like um you know, often when you're
thinking about agents and behavior and
motivation, thinking about practical
rationality, like I can reason my way to
obtaining some goal uh which is a large
part of what we've been talking about.
Um so the simple question here is just
well in so far as motivation intrinsic
motivation does not involve that in so
far as we have like entropy seeking
behavior and it's not just in the
service of obtaining a specific goal. Um
is it what's its relationship to
rationality? Is it irrational? Is it
irrational? Does it have to do with
bounded rationality? Um
that's the question.
Um,
I'd kind of like to think there's
something s super rational about this
that it's not it's not not everything we
do has to be in the in the pursuit of
some of some
>> Yeah, I I agree. And yeah, I think from
I mean I've been struggling with
long-term illness and it's made me
realize that the ends that you described
in rationality, the goals are like for
healthy people like for a sick person,
it's just about expanding your action
radius, gaining ground and just being
pushed back and and like expanding your
world in in a very literal sense and
gaining some freedom really. And that's
the basic thing. And of course, you have
to be
be eating eating or or be well fed and
and and
but but it's somehow natural for me to
see that the freedom and the empowerment
really is is is primary.
Um and only once you have like
discovered the goals, you can start to
optimize. So, so you have to form form
the goals and and and that's true, I
guess, some form of maximum entropy or
or empowerment. Um, but but yeah, it it
resonates with me to to think that it's
very much primary. Uh,
yeah. Um,
thanks. That's that's that's that's
interest resonates with how I been
seeing it as well. Um, so,
um,
yeah, I'm not sure I'm not sure I have
much more to add to that actually.
Thanks for Sandra. I was going to ask
you to chime in and I think that was a
good moment to do so. Um
>> yeah
just to get a bit back to sorry to I
don't know whether I can articulate it
but like somehow like this this premacy
of like the maximum entropy
it seems like I mean I've been reading
rolli who's taking like this kind of
more perspectival more interactionist
view of of um thermodynamics and and
maximum entropy and and this seems to
map onto somehow onto empowerment for me
that it's a a relative measure
perspectival measure. Um I cannot
articulate it because yeah I'm not on
top of the the physics of it but it
seems to be that there's a link between
the kind of like the blind entropy of
course you have where where heat is
spreading where where gas is diffusing.
You have like the the structured entropy
where where constraints are used to to
better dissolve gradients. And then you
have like some kind of empowered entropy
where where
it somehow reflects on itself. It it it
models its own entropy predict
production. It it starts to um model
that and optimize like the expansion of
the of the paths the possibilities
um with this agency then of course. Um
but that seemed to be like like very
simplistically in my mind like the the
steps that that are are taken and that's
why I I agree that I think this maximum
entropy is with the link to empowerment
is is more fundamental than
um yeah than reward or goals or um
but I don't know whether that that's uh
I is very philosophical and um sketchy.
>> I I am a philosopher by training. That's
that's that's what that's what that's
that's why I'm here. So, I appreciate
that. I mean, this this is the kind of I
wanted to just just dig deep and see
what people
It seems that um we have a couple
minutes. um probably wrap this up, but
it seems to me that like well so the
reason I maybe we have time for one
quick thing like
I kind of want I admit I want there to
be a connection between physical entropy
maximization and entropy maximization
under constraints and in agent aential
motivation because they're so
it just seems like a bedrock sort of
thing like why do we keep seeing this um
this sort of um structure in which you
have um a spread of of trying to
maximize sort of possibilities under
under under constraints um from from
many different points of view. And so
although there's no simple relationship
I guess when it comes to things like
policy selection under you know um like
pathic integrals of expected free energy
or or looking at empowerment per state
um it does this this is the reason that
that I thought it was an interesting
theme to explore under that under that
heading is that it seems that there's
something fundamental that might unify
these different approaches although that
said they are still different approaches
in many ways. So, um,
I think I'm going to awkwardly conclude
this. Does anyone have any closing
remarks? I really appreciate you all
being here. This is this is I I have
never done a panel before and I I I'm
glad I did this as a panel rather than
just, you know, trying to um um badger
people with my own views. So, this has
been really great and I thank you so
much for for joining everyone.
>> Um,
yeah,
>> thanks for organizing. Really,
>> thank you for organizing.
>> Yeah, thank you, Alex.
Perhaps I'll close out by just saying um
you know I have a lot of thoughts about
that last question you asked uh and I
think uh obviously I don't quite have
time to say uh them all or even say some
non-trivial portion of them uh but I
think a fruitful thing to do uh would be
to look into the world of stoastic
thermodynamics where a lot of work is
currently trying to bridge information
and physics uh in order to describe
uh complex non-equilibrium systems. Uh
and and probably uh the relation between
maximizing entropy in an information
sense and maximizing entropy in a
physical sense uh will fall out of
something adjacent to that. Uh hopefully
we as a as a community as a field uh get
closer and closer to that. Uh hopefully
you and I get to talk more about it as
well. I know I've I've promised to do so
and we've both just been a bit busy.
>> Oh no, I'd love to. Thanks. Yeah, I'm
looking forward to all these
continuations.
>> Yeah, but thank you again uh for the
panel. It was really wonderful
discussion. Um I'm sad it was so short.
I feel like it could have been much much
longer, but uh
>> yeah,
>> what can you
>> We'll do a retreat. We'll do a retreat.
>> Thank you.
>> Great.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Thank you. You all have a lot
of I know excellent writings on the
topic. So it is fun to see that kind of
come out just a little bit tip of the
iceberg. So all right, farewell. Oh,
All right, welcome back. We're with
William Gabert who will be presenting on
NGCLARN V3. You may remember a previous
symposia where William presented as
well. So this will be great to catch up
and hear about this toolkit and some of
the cool things that people can do to
apply and do modeling in it. So thank
you William to you.
>> Yeah. Hi. So my name is William Gart. Um
I am representing the neuro adaptive
computing laboratory from the Rochester
Institute of Technology in New York. Um
I'm here today to talk to you about
NGCLearn specifically the V3 which is
our upcoming release of NGCLearn. Um it
is a fast and modular computational
neuroscience library. Uh and with the
acquisition of V3 it just gives you a
bunch of new tools to work with. So
first off I just want to give a very
brief overview on what computational
neuroscience actually is. So
computational neuroscience at a glance
is basically just the study and
investigation of functions of the brain
uh brain functions using mathematical
computational tools and theories. Uh and
what this means is that uh instead of
going uh to math first and then trying
to claim that we are you know using
things like the brain uh we go to the
brain first and then try and model the
processes that happen in the brain with
math. Um your brain is not actively
doing a bunch of matrix multiplication
but if you look at it from a high enough
level and squint properly it does look
like it's doing matrix multiplication
and so we can approximate things that
way. Um, and we are very focused on the
bioplausibility of all of this. Um, and
it's all grounded very much in the
physical studies of living organisms.
Um, so there are studies that look at
how neuropathways work. There are
studies that work at how synaptic
plasticity works. There are studies that
look at memory. Uh, and these are all
just the various things that we look at
in computational neuroscience.
Uh now what this kind of means is that
we need tools to work on this. Um
because the brain is complex. Uh for
example, if when our brain is
interpreting the world, uh it is
receiving lots of data um like gigabytes
and gigabytes and gigabytes of data
coming in constantly. And what this
means is that if we have a model, we
need to uh obviously we're just going to
be looking at a small paired down
version of the amount of data that comes
into our brain. So we're always working
with a slightly suboptimal picture. But
on top of that, your brain isn't ever
idle. So in traditional deep neural like
deep learning, uh you take an image, you
feed it into your model, and then you
get an output. Um, sometimes we do
things what's known as recurrent neural
networks where you give it an input, it
goes and it processes and then you give
it another input and it uses the output
of the previous one and the new input
and it processes. That's closer to what
your brain does. But the problem there
is all of the little internal parts of
that network don't have values. Um, and
so like we want to make sure that we're
representing things with biology. Sorry,
was there somebody speaking?
Okay, sorry. Um, and so then the this
biological interpretation also lends
itself to how we get inputs into our
models. Uh, so for instance, the focal
point of your human eye can only really
process things at roughly 60 frames a
second. Uh, your periphery processes
things a lot faster than that, but the
focal point doesn't process much faster
than that. Um, but even in between those
frames, it doesn't sit idle. Um and then
obviously different sensors in our
bodies uh impact uh sense things at
different time. For instance, the
periphery, the uh rods in our eyes
process things a lot faster than the
cones in our eyes.
Um, and so then we work inside of this
biological framing that I was alluding
to earlier where when we model our
neurons in our when our when we model
our neurons uh we want to make sure that
they are stateful and that we are
working in a more uh time aare system.
Um, and we do this because your brain is
a time system. And so we still use a lot
of the similar words that you're going
to hear in traditional deep learning.
But for us when we say we are talking
about a syninnapse, we are talking about
the actual modeled connection of the
syninnapse. Uh when we're talking about
a neuron, we are talking about voltages,
currents, membrane potentials. We are
talking about the physical biological
aspects of a neuron. And what this also
means in our biological framing is that
the way that information is transmitted
from uh point A in our network to point
B in our network. Um it can't just send
a floating point number because your
brain doesn't send floatingoint numbers.
The way neurons communicate in our
brains is with uh pulses. Uh for we call
them spikes. And so this in and of
itself makes things a lot more
complicated when it comes to modeling
because if we're sending discrete pulses
over time, we have to do a full forward
pass over our model to figure out where
pulses happen, send pulses, and then we
have to do that again and again and
again and again. And basically what it
looks like at the end of all of this is
we have about a 200 layer recurrent
network where it's just going down for
like 200 time steps. But really it's not
a recurrent network. It's just
constantly processing new information
and constantly giving you some output,
but that output might just be null. So
all of this comes together to basically
say that everything works better as just
one giant state machine. So we have our
model, we're calling it S. And then when
we take a step in time, we move to
another state. And depending then on
what we do and in time, either we can
move down, left, right, whatever. And
these states are constantly evolving.
And most active inference models, a lot
of just computational neuroscience
models in general, they all have this
stateful uh framework that they work in
of where if you just pause the entire
model's processing of data, there's
always something going like there's
always values that exist.
Um and the main thing to keep in mind
with all of this is that these different
initial conditions and state initial
starting state uh vastly change the
model's output even if it's shown the
same information.
So that's kind of the overview of
computational neuroscience state for
modeling and kind of setting up our
problem space. Now this is not a like
this isn't a field that came about 2
years ago. This is a field that people
have been working and tinkering around
in for a little bit of time now. Um, so
that might be the question of well,
somebody probably has built a built
something before and they have. Um, I'm
going but the thing about building uh
previously built models is that they
kind of generally operate as black
boxes. Um, so because building these
large stateful systems incur incurs a
lot of overhead, most libraries that
exist today hide a lot of what's going
on. and you have some very specific
tools that you can use to uh modify the
internals of your system, but you don't
necessarily have all the tools that you
want. If you want to come up with a new
learning rule, maybe you don't have all
of the values that you need for that
learning rule, and there's no good way
of modifying the system internally.
And so testing new components and
everything is not easy. It's not
trivial. It's something that takes a
fair amount of time. And if we're
testing models that take a long time to
run,
it means that if we're it can you can
just lose days, weeks to just trying to
get a model to see if it'll do anything
and you don't know whether or not it'll
work. Um, and so what the, and just as a
reference point here, many some of these
alternative models take up to like 8
hours to do an epoch over emnest for a
moderatelysized spiking neural network,
which is a lot. Um, and so this is kind
of why we went to like our lab uh went
to building our own computational
neuroscience library. And so that is
called ngcarn. That is what I'm here to
talk about today. And basically this is
the little highlights reel and then
we'll get into exactly how it's working.
But it is a public pip package. You
today right now could go and type in pip
install ngcarn um and you will get a
version of ngcarn. I will tell you right
now you're going to get 2.0 which is a
perfectly functional version but it will
not look exactly like what I'm talking
about today. Um, ngcarn at its core
though is a state machine that sits next
to uh Jax which is a it's effectively
the linear algebra library for numpy uh
that was the backbone of TensorFlow
before it split. Um, and Jax allows us
to do things that are known as just in
time compilation. uh which allows us to
take a bunch of Python code that we know
is has fixed sizes and fixed types and
just produce effectively a C code
snippet that we can run on GPUs, TPUs,
CPUs, whatever. Um and in doing this our
models in some preliminary results you
can get from something that takes about
eight hours written in TensorFlow to
something that takes about 15 minutes on
the same hardware written in ngcarn.
Um and then the advantage of this is
that you can also make it also allows
for the creation of new methods, new
models, new components, whatever
incredibly easily because as long as you
follow a very simple coding paradigm,
everything will interface with it
perfectly.
So let's get into what some of that
looks like at a high level. So if we're
going to build a model in ngcarn, we do
have to slightly change how we are
thinking about modeling a network
specifically. It's for us it is just one
giant state machine. But if we just
treat it as one giant state machine, it
gets very hard to keep everything
organized and not end up putting values
where they're not supposed to be or
just, you know, moving all the data
around. So we use components inside of
our state machine which here we're
calling a context. We use components to
kind of hold
parts of the state uh together and
modify only a sub part of our state and
then be able to communicate with other
components which just also encompass a
different part of our state.
And this whole compartment uh sorry
component model uh just allows for us to
keep easy track and it's basically
bookkeeping that allows the end user to
say I'm going to take these same values
and do something new with them.
Similarly inside of a component we have
a compartment model and this is where
data is stored and is moved around. Um
and this is what allows us to very
easily move data from one component into
another component uh without a lot of
overhead.
So more specifically uh com looking at
components here here we have one for
what is known as the leaky integrate and
fire neuron. Now specifically the math
that happens inside of this isn't
particularly relevant. Uh but know that
this is one of the most common neurons
used in computational neuroscience for
modeling. Um what it is is it is
effectively a uh it's effectively a
capacitor where it slowly builds up
current uh passes a threshold discharges
emits a spike. Now what this means is
that there are some fixed parameters. If
we look here the number of unit the
number of neurons in our like layer of
uh leaky integrate and fire neurons is
fixed. We're not growing new neurons
magically as this is going. uh the that
voltage threshold that it's slowly
building up to that's also fixed. Uh we
have some time constants, we have a
resistance value and we have some
voltage rest and reset values. These are
all fixed parameters. These don't change
in time. You set them up once at the
beginning of your model and then you
just call run. Now they can vary um from
component to component but as far as
time is concerned they are fixed. Then
we get to the compartments which are the
variable parts in time of our component.
So here we have current as an input into
our component. At a various time we will
have a current. Similarly if we pause at
a different time we will have a voltage
and at that same voltage maybe we have
an output spike and we also have the
last time that we spiked. So we keep a
track of all of these values that change
in time. And this allows us to think
about our components in two steps. We
have here's every we have here's all of
the math and the logic and the fixed
parameters. And then here we have a
couple of values that we need to make
sure are updated at the end of every
time we are called. So that way we keep
up to date with our state.
Finally, how do we connect these
together? So if we have component A and
we have its parameters which are our
fixed values and we have our
compartments which are our variable
values and then we have component B
which has different parameters and
different compartment values but we want
to take the output of component A and we
want to make sure that it gets put as
the input to component B. Oh, sorry. Uh
that just means that you're just going
to take the value here and it just gets
passed along and it's done and it go and
it's traverses along what is known as a
cable. And so inside your model, you can
take any compartment value and you can
wire it with a cable into any other
compartment value. And what that means
is that when component B looks for the
value inside this compartment, it will
just know that it actually should be
looking at the value inside this
compartment. And so this is how that we
can keep things nice and fast is there's
no duplicates of values
but effectively it traverses along it.
Now with component X Y and Z down here
we're doing something a little special.
We have a summation. So now it's
entirely reasonable to assume that the
inputs into our component uh need like
we could have a variable number of
inputs. Uh, one of the best examples of
this is if you have a recurrent
connection inside of your model um that
are both feeding into say the current
value of your LIF neuron. What that
means is that you would have going down
your model, you would have the current
coming in and then you have current from
somewhere up in your model also looping
around. And basically there we might
want to add these together. We might
want to subtract them together. We might
want to have them multiplied and have
some basic arithmetic operation done to
them. And so we allow you to do that
along these cables is you can basically
bundle these cables together and then
just say hey add all of these together
and you can do that and this compartment
here knows how to do all of that. So
when you go and try and see the value of
this compartment it will automatically
collect these values add them together
and use it. And you as the end user
don't have to make sure that that
happens. And if for instance we unplug
component Y from the model, it just
runs. If we add in a component alpha to
our model that we want to add to this
summation, we just add it into we just
wire it into the uh we just wire it into
the compo compartment like anything
else. It all just works together.
Now,
this shows us how to set up our model,
but we're a state machine, so we
actually have to be able to transform
through states. So, transitioning our
model through time. So, here we have our
state transitions across a component.
We're going to look at these at a
specifically a component level and then
we'll look at them as as a whole system
as our model. Uh here we have component
A. uh it has our fixed parameters like
before and here we have two different
state transitions that we want to
account for. We have our reset
transition and we have our advanced
transition. Now there's this little
helpful key up here where anything
that's a solid line means that that
depends on those values. And if it's a
dashed line that means it updates those
values. So we'll notice here inside of
our reset function it depends on this
fixed parameter and this fixed
parameter. And then what it does is it
just updates every compartment value
inside the component.
Now in component in the advanced state
of our state transition, we'll notice
that it takes this compartment value,
this compartment value, this compartment
value in as well as these two fixed
parameters and then it updates this
compartment and this compartment over
here. And you can set these up in as
many as complex of methods as you want
here. any amount of math can happen. The
only thing that we have to keep in mind
is that these values are fixed and these
values change in time. That is the only
thing that we need to keep in mind with
this.
So if we want to do this across multiple
components or what we call a process on
our model, basically what would happen
is we have some overarching process
here. We just have it called advance.
And what it's going to do is it's going
to
call advance here on compartment on
component A. It's going to compute all
of its outputs. Then since these are
wired together, the when this when when
we call advance over here on component
B, it'll actually look at the output of
component A and use it for component B.
And then it will compute its output and
put it inside its output compartment.
And if we were to keep chaining and have
a component C over here that was wired
out, it would just the D it would just
keep going. And so this allows you to
chain as many of these components
together inside like a forward pass as
you want. It's also important to note
that these do not have to be the same
type of component. They do not have to
be the same type of transition. So here
there it's all named advanced, but as
we'll see later, it doesn't always have
to be named. It doesn't all have to be
named advanced.
Yeah. And so then um yeah, and it's
always uh deterministic the order that
all of this uh data gets transmitted in.
Um it will always go in the order you
define the components in. So you don't
have to worry about race conditions and
anything like that.
So finally in order to actually get
speed up from this because right now
we've just written basic Python code uh
we actually have to do go through what
is known as a compiling step of our
process. Uh and this makes use of
Python's abstract syntax trees. uh which
I am not going to get into uh the
complications behind getting syntax
trees to work but basically we look at
your code that you have written in the
generic Python classes uh and we tweak
it just a little bit and we'll see how
it tweaks it just a little bit uh to
produce code that is fast and efficient
for Jax's just in time compilation. uh
this is the true source of ngcarn's uh
speed up is that it is uh it can take
code that is written in a very easy to
read uh effectively format and then
convert it into what is needed to be
efficient for uh Jax's just in time
compilations format. Um and so basically
we just take that whole process and we
send it through our compiler. Now the
compiler as an end user is not something
that you need to ever actually worry
about. But there are advant but with V3
and this is what we're getting into here
with V3. There are some things that you
gain from that you gain that allow you
to look and really inspect at what is
our model doing? What is our process
actually doing? Uh which is very helpful
for things like debugging.
So what does this actually look like in
code? So starting at the top, if we want
to define a compartment on our class,
right? So these these all have self. So
these are all inside of a class. Uh we
can have inputs and it's just
compartment with some initial value.
Outputs compartment with different
value. Weights compartment with a third
value. This is how you make a
compartment. Now there are a couple
extra parameters that you can pass to
compartments that are useful for things
like plotting and whatnot, including
like compartment names, units, all of
that. Uh then we have fixed parameters
which are just exactly like you're used
to defining values in Python classes
just self.shape equals shape self.trc
scale equals resist scale whatever you
want to call it. You could just define
them like regular values. Then when we
want to define our advanced state for
our transition here uh we have our
outputs which is our compartment up
here. We're setting it to a matrix
multiplication of our inputs and weights
multiplying it by some resistance scale
value and adding biases to it. uh which
is not displayed here, but there's a
bias compartment as well. And what
you'll notice is this is just the
weight. This is just a weight matrix.
This is just inputs, weight matrix,
outputs. And we'll notice that this
looks pretty similar. This outputs set
might look a little weird, but just it
if you think about this as just an equal
sign, this looks incredibly similar to
regular Python code that you're used to
writing. The only thing that's a little
bit new is that it has this little
compilable flag above it. Now, you might
think that there's a lot of work that
goes into that at compilable decorator
wrapping around this, and I'm going to
give you a secret. There's not. All that
is doing is just adding a singular flag
to the method. It is doing nothing
beyond that.
So, then we get to Okay, so now we have
our component. We have our state
transition as an advanced state. How do
we how do we use these? Right?
Obviously, that's where the
complications got to come in. So, not
really. Uh, so we have contexts, which
if you remember are just our global
state. Basically, everything has to be
inside of a context. So, we have with
the context your context name as some
variable and then you just define them
like you would regularly define Python
objects. So, here we have our static
synapse, which is a weight matrix from
our inhibitory neurons to our excitatory
neurons. It has a shape. It has uh a
weight initializer which uh for we
provide the ability to just get
distributions uh generated for you. Uh
so here we can use our distribution
generator. We can get a constant
distribution and we can say that we want
it to be hollow. Uh which is the main
diagonal is all zeros. Uh and then when
we go back we can say nope this one we
actually want it to be an identity
matrix. Um, and there's uniform g like
there's all the different we have most
of the various distributions that you're
probably looking for uh supported in
this. Um, and all this is actually doing
is just returning a method. So these all
get added to your model automatically,
right? And if you're looking at this,
you might go, well, we still don't see
where all of the compiling happens.
Where is this big step that gives you
all of the speed up? Um and I will tell
you it is just whenever you leave this
width statement you have to add no extra
lines of code to your project it will
automatically compile all of the all of
the methods. So we will compile this
advanced state method as soon as you
leave this width block. Uh so you it
becomes incredibly easy to read. You
don't have to remember to call compile.
You don't have to do any of that. It
just happens automatically when you
leave the width block.
Um, another thing that can be useful if
you're building really large models and
uh have wanting to have nested
functionality or repeated functionality,
uh, you can make sub compon uh,
subcontexts or subm models uh, inside of
your main model.
So here we have our components.
Previously we talked about cables and
how we would connect the two things
together. Uh, this is the incredibly
complicated syntax to do that. So
basically here we have our Z1 excitatory
neurons and we have their spike output
or just S. Uh and then we wire it into
the inputs of our weight matrix.
That is it. There is nothing more that
needs to be done with this. It just is
basically shifting it just directly into
there. Similarly, we can take the
outputs of Z uh Z our weight matrix here
and we can shift it into Z1
inhibiitories current matrix our current
uh compartment and it just goes and if
we want to do that fancy summation
operation that we were talking about it
is just summation with your compartment
values and you can just keep tacking
them on here. It's not two, it is as
many of them as you want. Uh we also
support products, we support negation,
we support a lot of other um values here
and you can also define your own mer you
can define your own bundling mechanisms
too.
So now we've got wires, we've got
components. Uh now the last thing that
we talked about was a process. So here's
how we make a process. This has a little
bit more looking Python code, but it's
incredibly uh repetitive. So here, so
there's two different types of processes
that we have. we have what are known as
method processes which are basically a
process whereas we are going to go over
components and we are going to be
calling transitions on them. So here we
are going through all of the components
of our model and we are calling their
advanced state method. Now theoretically
if we wanted to call something like
let's just say we were using somebody
else's component and they didn't name it
advanced state they just named it ADV
because they you know wanted to
shorthand it you could just type ADV it
will work these do not have to be the
same name similarly the name of the
component of the me of the process does
not actually mean anything relative to
these values here then uh what we might
want to do is we have this advanced
process which go does a forward pass
over our model. And then let's just say
we want to add that we have an evolve
process which basically would be the
equivalent of our update step over our
model for all of our weights and so on.
And we call that evolve down here. And
then we want to join these together. So
we only have to call one method to do
both of them. Uh and that is what a
joint process is. Is these are joining
other processes together. And you can
nest these as deep as you want. You can
make multiple joint processes all in
one. You can make you can call an
advanced process multiple times in one
of these if you wanted to do advance
advance evolve advance advance evolve it
will all work and it'll just keep going.
So this is the processes setup and these
also compile right we talked about that
these also compile and similarly to the
width block of our model as soon as we
leave that width block. These are
defined inside the width block. As soon
as we leave that width block these also
automatically compile. You don't have to
worry about getting things to compile in
the correct order. All of that is taken
for care of it automatically for you. So
what does this compiling actually look
like under the hood? So here again we
have our weight matrix for our forward
for our forward step our advanced state
and we're going to compile W uh W1 EI
here. Now, it's important that we
remember that the spike output of Z1E is
being wired with a cable into W1EI's
inputs. So, if we look up here, we have
advanced state. The name changed a
little bit. It's now circuit_W1i
advanced state. That is because this is
the name of our model. This is the name
of our component. And this is the name
of the method that is being compiled.
And notice that the input has changed.
The input is now ctx or it stands for
context. Um so this is the global state
being passed into this method.
Then what happens is this self.outputs
outputs gets changed to circuit W1EI's
outputs is equal to and we just it's
just this directly mapped over with
we'll notice that the fixed value here
becomes a global fixed value here and
that self.inputs inputs because circuit
Z1E.S
because it's wired here. And so this
just all goes through and so you give it
a context. It mutates the context where
it needs to and then it gives you back
the context.
So this is how we compile a method. Now
for convenience sake of the
presentation, this is uh I've got syntax
highlighting on for this. Practically
speaking, you will never actually see
what is down here. This is all done
dynamically. and store it entirely in
memory unless you get it to print it out
yourself and then if you want syntax
highlighting you got to copy paste it
into a Python file and get your ID to
syntax highlight it. But practically
speaking you never need to actually do
anything with this. Um but it is however
useful when you're debugging to look at
this and go oh if this doesn't if this
isn't updated if this is still just W1
EI's inputs we know that it's not wired
to anything. And so then we could
actually debug what's going on in our
model by just looking at what it's
compiling to which is incredibly useful
um because if you just like forget to
add a step uh you can see it because the
output just doesn't have the step in it.
Similarly if we have an evolve process
so I did this one because it's got
slightly less components in it where we
have just W1 right so this is just a
heavy in syninnapse that's doing an
update. What we'll notice here is that
here is our con our compiled process
where we have a context and loop
arguments. Now we're not using loop
arguments but this is where you would
actually give it uh parameters that you
are passing into the forward step of
your model. So this is things like dt.
This is things like the current time.
This is things like the image you're
looking at and whatnot.
And so then it goes through and then I
don't have the original code here, but
you'll have to take my word for it that
this is compiles and looks correct. But
importantly, we'll notice here we have
this W1_MP compute update, right? What
this here is this is another method that
exists on the heavy and synapse for
doing its update. Well, we also we we
successfully capture all of those too.
Uh you can make as many sub methods as
you want as long as they all are just
take you know they take in self they
take in values it doesn't matter and you
can call them and it all just builds
together perfectly.
So how does this actually look when you
want to like use the process loop
through the process what are you doing?
So uh for convenience you can call your
model uh dot you can call your forward
process get keywords. So for us, for
this that'll give us t and that gives us
delta t, right? Uh you don't have to do
this u but this this will tell you all
of the keywords that it is looking for
to actually run your component uh run
your process. Um and if you're missing
any of them, it will complain at you. Uh
and then we can pack all the inputs
together, right? Because you know we're
going to be looping through all of
these. We need to actually make all of
the inputs that we're going to call.
Well, luckily um that's really easy cuz
you just call pack the rows of all of it
and you tell it the number of iterations
and then you can do one of two things.
You can give it a lambda function or
just any function really uh that takes
in x which is your iteration number and
produces some value. The next thing you
can do is you can also just give it
constants. So dt equals 1. And so what
this will do if we say iterations is 10,
this will give us an this will give us
basically a matrix that has t is equal
to 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9. And it'll have
dt is equal to 1 at every single time
step because it's a constant for the
pass.
And then what we can do is okay so we
have all of our inputs now. Uh now we
want to actually loop through all of
those inputs. Well you can just call
scan which is very similar to Jax's
scan. if you've used it um if you've
used any scan method I believe
TensorFlow still has a scan method on in
it um where basically it'll just loop
through all of the inputs that you give
it in effectively a for loop but it is
doing this all compiled in C uh so we
don't actually want to write our own for
loop this is dramatically faster um and
the output of that will give you hey
this is our spike output which is
something that we set when we compiled
all our method together and our final
state of our model that we can do
something with because as it runs
through it doesn't necessarily actually
change your model. It just tells you
this is how your model would change and
then you can choose what you want to do
with that.
So there are some current papers being
written with this some current
applications that have been written with
this. Um so we have a neural coding
frameworks for learning generative
models uh done by Auroria and Kefir. Um
this one uh makes use of NGCLearn. uh we
have an uh we have uh reproduced uh Dan
Cook's model of unsupervised learning of
digit reconstruction using spike timing
dependent plasticity
uh we have my own personal paper with my
adviser called time integrated spike
timing dependent plasticity uh that is
also made in this model uh and then we
have a contrastive signal dependent
plasticity self-supervised learning and
spiking neural circuits also done by my
adviser Dr. in Arabia. Um, and you can
find all of these models and more
actually in a sister library uh known as
the NGC Museum. Uh, so this is a library
that our lab works very hard to keep up
to date for at least our projects uh for
the latest version of uh NGCLearn and it
houses all of the biomimetic and brand
inspired computing. And if you write a
paper in NGCLARN and you want to add it
to the museum, we are happy to add it to
the museum. Um, the whole point of it is
to be a public place to share code
because there's nothing more annoying
than reading a paper, looking at the
coefficients that they claim to have
used, reproducing their work, and it not
doing what it's supposed to. So, this is
a place where we can store all of that.
It's also a place where we have some
historical works. Uh so that way if you
want to get a baseline from some
historical paper uh but don't want to
implement it all yourself we can do that
as well. And so with that V3 should be
releasing later this month. Uh I will
say with Thanksgiving it might get
pushed back to early December but we are
making great strides and it should be up
soon. And with that I will open the
floor to questions.
>> Very cool. So people in live chat can
ask questions. Um I wrote some down as
well. So just to stay close with the
theme of the talk, what would you
summarize are the major differences
between NGCLER 2 and 3.
Uh so the main difference between NGC
learn sorry it's going to flash for a
moment is this right here. So in ngcarn
2, there was an very specific setup that
you had to do when defining this
advanced state method, and you couldn't
use self, which meant that you had to do
a bunch of pattern matching yourself to
make sure that all of the names were the
same and that all of the inputs were
correct. Now, because we're making use
of abstract syntax trees, you don't have
to do any of that. So you can just throw
compilable on a class method that has
self all over it. Um, and we just
extract that all away and turn it into
the global context that you actually
want to be referencing.
>> Yeah. Awesome. That's a that's a big
>> It's also faster. I don't know if I
mentioned that. V uh V2 is roughly 10 to
20% faster. I'm sorry. V3 is roughly 10
to 20% faster than V2. um which on the
grand scale of things isn't that much
faster but it is faster.
>> Yes.
Very cool. So maybe just to to kind of
ground that um in terms of of expert
time or the size of models or networks
that you could reliably render and
execute.
Where does this move the frontier? like
what was is that was that a limiting
step or was that preventing large
systems from compiling or what?
>> So I think one of the things that it
really stops is I think the time element
stops people from getting into the
field. Um, pretty much everybody who has
been working in the field for a while,
um, has their own little custom whatever
that took them 5 10 years to get, you
know, to work and iterate on that gets
them to something that's fast, right?
Because they've taken the time to figure
out how to speed it all up and optimize
it. But if we have new students, if we
have new like new PhD students, if we
have students in a class, they don't
have five years to optimize their
codebase in order to do preliminary
tests. Uh what we allow for that is we
just allow you to kind of be a little
hands-off when it comes to how this is
optimizing and becoming quick. Um I will
also note that this does not require
fancy GPUs to actually run quickly. Uh
that 8 hour and 15 minute benchmark is
done on my laptop with no GPU. That is
the CPU speed up. Um the GPU speedups
are equally as fast. Um but you don't
need it uh until you run out of CPU
memory which is always a constraint.
>> Thanks. Okay, continuing with the
questions. So does NGCL learn allow a
different scheme or ontology other than
the neuronal like you had the block
diagram with the voltage current spike
variables. So can you specify arbitrary
stateful models in in that block?
>> Yeah. So here where we're defining this
this is just a class. So this right here
is a weight matrix right. This is our
dense weight matrix where we have we
it's just class weight matrix and then
you do have to inherit from Jack's
component but like that's that just
gives you all of the backbone that you
need um but doesn't actually require you
to do anything. Um you can define as
many compartments as you want as few
compartments as you want. You can define
any number of fixed parameters that you
want and you can define as many state
transitions as you want with as many
different names as you want. It will
just all find them and work. Um the only
thing I will say is that because this is
a giant state machine. Um obviously if
you have tens of thousands of changing
values at every forward pass I it's
going to get slow but that's not a fault
of the library. Any library is going to
get slow with that because just changing
that many values in Python takes time.
So, do those internal calls or nested
calls have to remain within the NGC
semantics or where would an external API
call or another routine or program? How
would that be brought into the design of
what
>> Jax's matrix multiplication call? This
right here, it's just Jax's
multiplication matrix multiplication
call. You can just call them.
>> It doesn't it doesn't care if it's not a
class method. It doesn't try and do
anything to it. So if it's not a class
method, it'll just call it. Um, now I
will say that if it calls something that
mutates things that it probably like
because this is all built on Jax, Jax
generally speaking expects things not to
be mutable. Um, now this is a copy of
what is passed out above um, just from
the way Jax works. So like we can mutate
it here, but like you don't you want you
want your methods to return values. Um
but that is a Jax specific thing. Um but
practically speaking here we have this
is Jax's numpy ver uh form uh matrix
multiplication call of these two inputs.
Um inside of ngcarn we have an entire um
ordinary differential equation backend
uh that you can just reference like it's
just ngcarn. OD whatever OD you want and
it'll just work. And like that's not
something that's like written
specifically to work with the compiler.
It just allows it to function like you
it just doesn't care if it's not a class
method. It's just it just works.
>> Interesting. But it might hang for a
while if there was call local llm method
inside. Would it spawn a whole Python
thread?
>> Uh so it's not necessarily going to
spawn threads in that sense. But yeah,
if so, for example, if I have uh if I'm
doing a matrix multiplication of two
gigantic matrices that is going to take
like 30 seconds to do without any of NGC
learn around it, just using Jax's
optimized matrix multiplication with JIT
compiling on a 30 by 30 m on like a a
matrix that takes 30 seconds, it's still
going to take 30 seconds. We are not
speeding up the linear algebra. uh we
are purely speeding up all of the Python
that sits on top of the linear algebra
because it's really slow. Writing values
is really slow and so we are trying to
make it as fast as possible without
rewriting uh the accelerated linear
algebra library or LAX uh which is what
Jax is built on top of. It's the NumPy
bindings for all of LAX which is what
everything uses. If you come up with a
linear algebra method that is faster
than LAX, I highly recommend you tell
them because they're entire mission is
basically making it as fast as possible
to do linear algebra on a computer.
>> Cool. Interesting. Okay, a note in the
chat and then you could add a comment or
I'll ask another question. Note to
audience members, NGCLearn does also
support convolution, deconvolution,
sparse synaptic transforms. etc. In
addition to a bunch of historical
spiking and ratecoded neuronal cell
models, NGCLearn also supports generic
iterative differential equation
integration, i.e. Oiler midpoint RK4.
>> Yeah. So I I assume that's coming from
my adviser in the chat. Yes.
>> Um
>> yeah. So yeah, I don't I did not have
space in this presentation to include
all of the historical like all of the
components that we support. But if you
are used to using generic founded uh
computational neuroscience components,
there is a very very good chance that we
already have them in the library and you
don't have to write them yourself. So
pretty all of the all of the and that
includes both rate coding and spiking
like you can do rate coded with this. Um
I will say that it might be overkill for
some rate coded models but it would
work. Um, also technically speaking, you
can do back propagation through this.
Uh, Jax does do back propagation like
like gradients and whatnot. Um, spiking
neural nets themselves though are not
differentiable. So, I'm not going to get
into covering it here and we don't truly
have a tutorial on it because it's not
something that we're trying to do. Um,
but it is possible to do it and I have
gotten it to work fairly easily.
>> Okay, I just have a few more questions.
So often in in modeling whether sort of
a monolithic
>> mono composite type model or more of a
synthetic intelligence approach like
nodes that have different kinds of
programs running there's this continuum
between taking a bit of a more problem
agnostic architectural approach like
off-the-shelf neural network
architectures or domain specific
architectures and then just kind of
throwing in the training data going from
there. So in that situation the the
semantics of your model and what it does
are being shaped kind of from a flat
prior with the training data set. And
then on the other hand, sometimes
there's there's very situationdriven
modeling even into the toy modeling
space where people are looking to encode
the semantics of like anxiety level as a
parameter itself that might be
undergoing some kind of basian updates
but on the interpretable parameter
itself as opposed to to that more
machine learning driven approach without
>> looking to constrain the how how the
topology ology of the initial network
relates to the data set and the
function. So when you're designing these
kinds of systems, where does it exist
between like a super nuance way to
specify a neural network that's agnostic
and trained sort of like a convolutional
neural net or do you encode in more
direct fewer parameters of interest?
>> So uh I'm going to say that you can do
both. So we are specifically a library.
We're not we're not gunning for a
specific method here, right? I'm not
here to tell you that method A is better
than method B. Um so with this sort of
thing with like my personal research and
my use with this um a lot of the time is
driven by I am looking at the so I've
done a fair amount of work with
reinforcement learning and similar
spaces like that um in the context of
computational neuroscience. Um and what
that kind of leans to is very much
thinking about well this is what my
sensor data looks like. So, let's make
sure that like the encoding scheme that
we're using actually matches up with
that cuz like sure I could go take some
generically large LLM and just throw
data at it and hope that it works. Um,
but that's not necessarily going to be
efficient. Uh, computational
neuroscience as a field of research also
has a sister field of hardware research
called neuromorphic computing. uh which
generally speaking uh imposes a lot more
constraints on things. Uh so when I'm
building models, I tend to work with a
lot more constraints of physical
constraints uh for like value types and
you know magnitudes and the way
information gets moved around. Um so you
can definitely do it all the different
ways here. I would say one of the nice
things about ngcarn
uh though from the standpoint of trying
to come up with a new component for
instance is the fact that you are just
coming up with a new component. So, if
let's just say I wanted to go out there
and I wanted to make a new neuron,
right? Because what I was looking at
advocates for me making a new neuron.
Um, you don't have to do a bunch of
extra steps to get it to interface with
everything else. Um, you just have to
define the logic basically and wire it
up correctly and it will just integrate
into your model. I'm not going to tell
you that it's going to work as far as
like practical side goes, but as far as
coding side goes, that's all you would
have to do. I hope that answers your
question.
>> Yes. And then here's my last question.
Um or semipen ultimate and then I'll see
if there's any in the chat. But how do
you see or go from the forward design
phase and generating synthetic data and
outputs from a priori specification?
How do you also work with the empirical
parameter estimation? Whether you were
looking to design a sort of model level
property like learning or or are you
fitting this to spike train data and
looking to fit it at a more micro
component level?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So some of that so it's I'm
going to use the the hallmark frame of
it depends. Um so if we are in
computational neuroscience, if we are
looking at a toy problem that was not
originally designed to be working with
spiking nets, the biggest example of
this is emnest, right? Emnest is a bunch
of static images uh that have floating
point values. Uh we don't have a bunch
of we don't have like like we're not
static models. Our outputs aren't
static. Our outputs are just a bunch of
spike trains. So we do have to represent
that somehow. Um and so we uh it is
something that in ngcarn we do try and
offer some uh support for doing things
like that uh for helping converting
collecting whatnot um in the models that
we've built in the museum uh that can
show like yeah here is one way to do
like clustering with this. This is one
way to assign labels to output neurons.
So we do that sort of thing is where
it's like okay like we have to make the
synthetic data effectively work to
something. Um but the or I guess it's
not quite synthetic but like we have to
basically make our own labels um that
mean something to us. Um and then on the
follow-up side of that when it comes
from like do we work forwards or
backwards from either the real world and
synthetic data or synthetic data towards
the real world. Um I would say that good
science does both. Um sometimes finding
a real world problem that an idea fits
to is challenging. Um and other times
you have a real world problem that
you're trying to solve. Um and therefore
you definitely should be working
backwards from it.
Very cool. So now the actual last
question any first you can add anything
you'd like and just where are you at in
your overall research journey? What are
you looking to have done by the end of
this phase or just what's next for
NGCLearn and and how you want to develop
and do that and other things.
>> Yeah. So I am in my fifth year of my
PhD. Uh so I am slated to defend my
dissertation fall of next year. Um I
really like working in the space of
research tools. Uh it is something that
I have a huge passion for doing. Um and
so research tools and more recently
specifically research tools for hardware
applications. So I mentioned a little
bit earlier uh there's the whole sister
field of putting spiking neural networks
onto physical hardware. Um I have done
some research in that recently and it is
a lot of fun and I enjoy doing it. Um as
far as more immediate plans of stuff um
there's a survey paper that we are
currently working on that should be
coming out soon uh in relation to
spiking neural networks and
computational neuroscience. Um, in
addition to that, uh, coming out either
December this year or January next year,
uh, there should be a white paper
actually out for NGCLearn on its
development, the thought process that
went behind it and everything as long as
well as that. Um, beyond that, um, I
have writing my dissertation on the
to-do list and probably one more one or
two more research projects in there
somewhere that we have not figured out
yet.
>> Cool.
Great. Yeah. lot of exciting reasons to
explore NGCLERN. I have just cloned into
it on another computer. So I look
forward to uh learning more about it.
>> If you clone into it right now, if you
are using it through pip, it will be v2.
If you clone it from the GitHub repo, if
you just check out the v3 branch, uh you
will get all of what we're currently
working on. That is the dev branch for
version 3. Um but the release branch
should be updated within the month.
>> All right. Okay. Thank you, William.
Good luck with finishing your PhD.
>> Thanks for having me.
>> All right. Bye.
>> Bye.
Okay, that was all of the live streamed
presenters for the day. Now, there will
be several pre-recorded videos.
First pre-recorded video is Steven
Wineer. Interceptive posture pictures
for active inference informed
neuromuscular skeletal NMS therapy.
43 minutes long. Here it is.
Intraceptive posture pictures are a tool
and a methodology
for practical
active inference informed neuromuscular
skeletal therapy as well as for people
who want to move well as they age.
Intraceptive posture pictures IPs are a
tool and a methodology for active
inference informed neuromuscular
skeleletal therapy. Muscle, bones,
joints being able to move well. which is
why it's also an amazing tool for anyone
who wants to move well as they age. I'm
a neuromuscular clinician and educator
and to me active inference is a
framework to connect and shape people's
mindsets towards healthy behaviors in
both body and mind. Now I understand
that AIF is part of a broader
understanding for PhD scientists,
researchers and others looking at how to
model from a computer AI point of view
as well as understand from a personal
point of view how humans work in a whole
new light. I believe that for
clinicians, patients and the public,
active inference can play a role in
preventing the progression of I hurt my
back back pain. and I overdid it. Neck
pain, common stress,
going from acute to chronic and
especially when chronic low back pain is
the leading cause of disability globally
and neck pain and tech neck and normal
daily stress is part of a sematic pain
that a lot of people live with in their
lives. Active inference can help
clinicians and people help themselves.
In addition, it's also a way to mitigate
full risk for aging boomers, as well as
to address mild concussions, things
called MTBI or PPCS, persistent
postconussive syndromes after accidents
or sports injuries, as well as helping
everyone including you to connect with
your intraceptive sense and your sense
of balance,
your sense of your overall body
alignment to have the zones of postural
mass balance. balance and have those
zones of postural mass, those posture
zones move in everything you do.
Balance, align, and move. We call that
BAM. My name is Dr. Steven Winger. I'm a
doctor of chiropractic. I practice for
26 years. For the past 20 years, I've
been lecturing around the world about
teaching people to move well. I'm a
diplomat of the International Academy of
Neuromuscular Medicine. And I'm very
proud. Last year 2024, I published my
first peer-reviewed paper in Frontiers
of Neuroscience. It really was a very
cool thing because I had wanted to but
never went into research and I had
gotten a whole new understanding of what
it takes to be a PhD level researcher.
I've written books. I've lectured
literally around the world. And when I
saw the word cloud for this conference,
the first thing that popped out to me
was energy principle and clinical and
the clinical application of this is
something that I think it's tremendous
and it's not yet been realized
especially in NMS care. So the title of
our paper,
introsceptive posture awareness and
accuracy, a novel photographic strategy
towards making posture actionable came
from my work teaching which works with
well this is some of the disclosures
that I do need to talk about.
Bodyzone.com which is public health
awareness and ideas largely focused on
posture and posturemonth.org or which is
a public health awareness campaign and
strongposture.com
which is a self-care campaign and tools
for professionals mostly to give to
patients to work along with those
patients. My main interest now is
ceup.com which is online continuing
education for professionals. We teach
doctors, therapists to incorporate the
ideas of using a grid, the posture's own
grid, which is a tool to objectify a
simple posture picture. And we certify
people with this in with posture
practice. Disclosure, these are things
that I do have an economic interest in.
What you have an interest in is your
posture. And everyone does. Posture
isn't good or bad. That framing is
wrong. It's old. Posture is functional
which means it's strong or weak.
And the overlay with active inference is
that maximizing the symmetry means
reducing the prediction error which
saves energy. Energy is the thing that
life is all about. Efficient movement
that generates a fluid flow is not
wasting energy. And every unique body
selects their movement strategies that
match their internal models expectation
of what's going to occur next moment by
moment. And that's why
good static posture and dynamic motion
are not the same for everybody because
not only is your body different from
mine, but our experiences are different
in life and what we've done and who we
are. I'd like to start to get you
thinking about your body and how your
body is basically working in what you
do. So my question for you is as I stand
here right now on an overall
biomechanical basis and biomechanic
means muscles and joints how they're
working together
right now is my body balanced.
I've asked this question around the
world to many audiences and people
invariably say no he's not balanced. No.
And you're probably saying that right
now, but remember the question on an
overall biomechanical basis, is this
body balanced? And the answer is of
course it is because I'm not falling
down. Which brings me to the point, your
posture is how you balance your body.
It's what you're doing to maintain
verticality.
Humans are the only oblate biped on the
planet that is a mammal.
birds also obligate bipeds some other
creatures in different places but humans
are the only mammals and mammals are
unique because we've learned to do a
number of things one of which is
maintain our internal energy at the same
temperature
uniqueness of human bipeedal momentto-
moment balance requires inference to
stay vertical maintaining that takes a
huge amount of the free energy that we
have and conserving energy is a priority
for anything that's alive. This is a law
of nature. If there's an inferred
prediction that has a higher energetic
cost or a greater inefficiency,
the organism is going to have a negative
perception of that action and tend to
shy away from it. When that persists for
a while, it can be felt as stress,
fatigue, pain, or just feeling bad.
Human activities require accurate
balance control. From simple standing to
complex sports movement, falling down is
something that we don't want to do. When
you watch children learning how to walk,
they fall down and they bounce back up
because they're made differently. But as
we develop, we become less resilient to
falling down because we've learned how
to stand tall. And our bodies develop in
that direction. which is also why
losing your balance in daily life is a
early warning signal for problems
breaking down your health. And you may
say, "Well, I'm not old enough to have
that problem yet." But if your balance
is weakening, you're getting a big
flashing yellow light to do something
differently.
And balance assessment of how your body
is standing both statically and
dynamically is a sensitive indicator of
neurologic health.
In 2012, maybe 2013, I saw a TED talk by
Bud Craig and it got me interested in
introsception. I picked up his book,
read it, How Do You Feel? And it sounds
like an emotional touchy feely book, but
the subtitle really got me. It's an
intraceptive moment with your
neurobiological
self. The premise of this based on a
neuroanatomist that spent his time
literally tracing where nerves in the
body go is that the insulin deep part of
the brain is where your sematic feelings
of your body emerge from. And there's a
sense that drives this called
intraception. And the next question
becomes well what is intraception?
I mentioned before that mammals are
warm-blooded. Mammals have to control
their internal temperature. And that
began a process of controlling what's
happening inside our body to different
degrees for different mammals in
different ways.
Humans do it differently. And we've
developed cognition in ways that have
allowed us to socialize and to project
our feelings from ourself onto other
people and to have abstract thoughts
about those in cognition. In our hope
progression over this past six or seven
million years, we've developed a very
unique cognition and very unique body
and very unique abilities to connect
with our body.
and focusing on intraception
is what the NIH the actually the NCC
division of NIH in the 5-year plan from
2021 to 2025 said we need more research
about intraception because it is a huge
and unexplored factor in promoting
effective health and in addressing many
syndromes and diseases of modern life.
the stress and the many problems
developing from the incursion of
technology into the activities of daily
living. You probably know what I'm
talking about. The definition of
intraception from NIH is the
representation of the internal world of
an organism which includes the processes
by which the organism senses,
interprets,
integrates, and regulates signals from
within itself.
Now, if you're on the biologic side of
this, this is basic. If not, I'm going
to do some really fast anatomy to give
you a sense of why this is so important
from a processing point of view. The
insula develops in humans from the
silven fissure, which is an infolding
that's on the side of the brain. That
line that you've seen going left to
right is the sylvvian fissure. When you
were developing from an embryo, you went
from one cell to a ball of cells to a
tube of cells. And at the top, there was
an explosion of cells that started to
fold in. That stuff on the outside, the
cells on the outside are the cortex. And
that cortical infolding went down and
got buried and became an anatomic
structure called the insula.
And because it's been so deeply buried,
it's been hard to study. So anatomists
have not really looked at it as we began
mapping things. Well, some of the newer
technology has let amazing insights
occur about this over the past 20 25
years. And it's these insights are
exploding. There's a ton of research
going on about intraception because when
you look at again you'll notice that
above that horizontal line there's a
groove going up and down called the
central sulcus. That is the line between
the blue and the red. And that line
between the blue and the red is the line
between the sensory cortex and the motor
cortex. And the sensory cortex is where
information coming in from. And the
motor cortex is where information going
out. On the coming in and the going out,
there's what called a homunculus.
Basically, it's a sematotopic
representation of neural connections.
You may have seen pictures of a big nose
and a big big lips, big eyes and small
arms which represent the pointto-point
correlation of the nerves in that part
of the body. They're different for the
information coming in and the motor
control going out. That is why there's a
different sensory homoculus and a
different motor homoculus.
roughly the same eyes, two eyes, one
nose, but the proportions of the neural
density is not the same. When you look
underneath, when you open up that
sylvvian fissure and look down between
the parietal lobe of the brain on top
and the temporal lobe of the brain on
the bottom, you look at what's
underneath it. That's where you see the
insula. And the insula has a front and a
back, an anterior and a posterior
portion that controls things in the
body. It is the most uniquely complex
part of the human brain according to
some people. And it's a really good
argument because it ties things
together. There's three different
emunculi. It's not just only the sensory
cortex. It's not just the motor cortex
that has a representation or a
pointtooint. It's also the insula. And
that insulin has homeostatic as well as
autonomic as well as allostatic input
into the brain. If you know what
allostatic is, it's another big thread
in what's occurring in life sciences.
And one way to look at it, which is
conversation for different day, but if
you know what homeostasis is, the
ability to keep things level within the
body, allostasis is to homeostasis
as prediction is to reaction.
Alistasis is predicting forward, which
is one reason why active inference in my
mind is destined to reshape a lot of
life sciences. The lowhanging fruit
almost is the biomechanical side of
because when you start getting into some
of the the hormonal issues, it becomes
far more complicated.
Oh, one more rather important thing from
Bud Craig's book, emotional feelings
emerge in the insula. Craig writes that
the insula optimizes homeostatic sensory
motor integration and homeostatic
behaviors. Masio and Carvalo wrote a
paper about intraception and the origin
of feelings and they talk about how the
intraceptive nervous system maps the
homeostatic state of the body and that
intraception
is structurally and functionally
different from extraception. Different
pathways, different processing,
everything's different. It's a different
aspect of your sensing
your body. It's a different way of
reacting
because of that different sensation
coming in. Which is why a 2024 paper,
what is the role of intraception in the
symptom experience of people with
chronic pain? A lot of words really well
put together, but the bottom line is in
common sense. People who are more
accurately connected to their body's
inner feelings have less pain less
often. People who are inaccurately
connected to their body's inner feelings
tend to have more pain. This is why
accuracy of sematic bodily prediction is
so relevant from a pain point of view as
well as from a addressing the causes of
the pain and empowering the person to
work with and connect with their body
more effectively and to feel better
about it. And that emotional side of it
is one reason why intraception has seen
far more attention in the psychological
sciences working with emotions than in
the physiologic sciences. One of the
directions within muscle and joint back
pain care has been what's called
biocschosocial
to work with the biological and the
psychology and the social because these
things affect how people deal with their
pain on a simplistic level of I'm under
stress because of bad home life to a far
more complex level that ties directly
into active inference of incorrect
predictions because of priors, things
that have happened before that then make
me look at how the world is going to act
towards me, which then shapes how I act
in the world. And these things are not
conscious. They might be, but they don't
have to be.
In fact, it is a really strong argument
to be made that active inference is how
we feel. Emotions are inferences about
causes of your bodily state, which is
your body's best guess about, well, why
you feel the way you do. It's okay for
me to feel this way. And feelings in
general are intraceptive predictions.
Your brain predicts the state of your
body. Now, pain can be predictive error
signal. If something hurts, there's a
torn tissue or a broken broken bone.
That's a prediction that if I move, it's
going to hurt. And that's true. When an
expected and an actual body state
doesn't match, you've got a prediction
error. Feelings aren't passive
reactions. They're active inferences on
a momentby-moment basis about what's
happening inside your body. I'm afraid
to do this. It's going to hurt. We'll
try it like this. I thought it's going
to hurt. It's going to hurt. Oh, it
didn't hurt.
When you feel your posture more
accurately, when you feel the muscle
tension and the mechanics of what's
occurring or the pain more accurately,
when you're experiencing your brain's
predictions about your body more
accurately, then those direct sensations
coming into the nervous system are more
accurate to reality and you tend to have
less pain and you're empowered to do
things that can then help you have even
less pain. One of the biggest issues
with muscularkeeletal problems is people
don't move because it hurts. So they
become less able to move. So they move
less. And this is a problem that plays
out over a long period of time. But
hopefully you've been living for a long
period of time. And I know many of us
hope to live for a much longer period of
time. Introsception informs active
inference. Which is why looking at how
someone's balancing their body on two
feet, their posture. I'm balancing like
this. That says something from a
biomechanical as well as a social point
of view. I mean, our language says it.
He's kind of shifty. He looks crooked.
He's a standup guy. That two lit balance
symmetry and accuracy of prediction
has a dramatic effect. In fact, it's a
proxy
in my mind for how your one leg balance
is expressed. If I'm balancing like this
on one side or like this or like this,
whatever it happens to be,
those motor patterns
will be
directly
reflective of how I move in everything I
do. And this is one of the profound
implications of active inference.
Biomechanics is more than the physics.
It's also the predictions and processing
that's occurring within my body about
how I'm going to move. The old view is
that muscles respond to muscle loads and
the nerves tell the muscles what to do
and that's all there is to it. The
active inference point of view is that
muscles activate based upon the
predicted load and they also preload in
that prediction which means that well
I'm just tight like this because your
body is preloading based upon actions
that have occurred between your
predictions and what's happened and the
predictions may be stress maybe threat.
The fact is that people that live with
anticipatory muscle bracing, have a
protective guarding based upon reactions
are moving in patterns that initially
will compensate would move differently
which is one of the concepts we talk
about that are functional. You can
change it if you focus on it. But
ultimately it adapts.
This structure changes. When I use this
muscle more and that muscle less, this
muscle gets stronger, that muscle gets
weaker.
Your brain distributes the load based
upon the capacity of your body. Is it
the predicted capacity or the actual
capacity? It's the predicted capacity,
not what's actually possible. It's what
you think you can do. Even after the
injury, the heel tissues may keep on
being protected because you've learned
that pattern that outdated prediction is
carrying forward in the express pattern
of how you're moving your body. And
that's why you end up with chronic load
syndromes going on where you're putting
more load on something. It I'm just like
that way. That's the way I move. I don't
know. I just that's just me.
that asymmetry of function accelerates
breakdown and asymmetrical development
creating a negative spiral. That's the
model that we look at and I believe that
this is very much the active inference
model that is creating a more accurate
way of looking at the world. George box
is a noted British statistician has a
great quote all models are wrong but
some are useful. We came out with the
idea of standardizing how to take a
picture of posture that many clinicians
have used but adding something to it
that one leg balance concept as a
clinical framework that applies active
inference principle to motor control
assessment and exercise to enhance
outcomes in neuromuscular skeletal rehab
as well as chronic pain management. All
you need is a camera. Take a picture in
four standardized views. Looking at
somebody from the front, from the side,
and then from the front, again,
balancing on one foot, standing tall,
and that's important, and standing on
the other foot. These ideas align very
much with the word cloud that active
inference is something that ties into
the energy principle and it is practical
from a clinical point of view. In
addition, it's something that the public
can do and that can be researched. And
this is why I'm talking here right now
because if you're doing any kind of
research in the biologic sciences and
you're working with subjects, adding a
posture picture to what you're doing is
potential window into their body's
prediction from an intraceptive sense
because that's where a lot of this
information coming from. The senses for
your body for introsception are not the
same sensors as the senses for
propreception. How your body is moving.
The goi tendon and the muscle spindles
are dependent upon load and motion. But
just feeling something is a different
kind of a feeling inside. Intraception
is thirst, hunger. It's one of the
internal body feeling. Your body's sense
of state is an internal body feeling and
the nerves for that go on different
pathways up the spinal cord and it's
processed in the insulin which
integrates this information with other
parts of the body before going out to
the motor cortex to guide the motions on
a more gross level. And the whole one
leg balance idea is so important because
your walking begins with balancing on
one foot. Every step you take you're
balancing on one foot and alternating.
Which is why if you're doing that
asymmetrically when you're standing
statically you've burned in that pattern
every step you take. That's why in my
book stand taller live longer our second
posture principle was balance. The first
posture principle motion your body's
designed to move. Active inference
drives those movement patterns. Movement
is about the whole body. Motion is about
one arc of motion within the body. prior
beliefs about how your body should move
within a global movement unfolds from
all the little motions of the joints in
that kinetic chain of your body. And the
predictions about the sensory
consequences of the action drive what
you do and the effort to
avoid pain trumps minimizing prediction
errors, minimizes energy use. Well, it's
harder to walk like this, but it doesn't
hurt when I walk like this. You'd be
amazed to see how some people walk into
the office when they're in an acute pain
and what they manage to do to work out
to have an affordance of some kind of a
cane or a crutch in different
directions.
Oh, as a sidebar, I don't like canes. I
don't like crutches used
indiscriminately. I'd much prefer a
staff to keep the body vertical than a
cane to let the body fold forward
because that tends to lead very much
into now you have a scooter to go around
and now you have a wheelchair to go
around it.
Effort keeps the body moving.
Compensatory patterns about how your
body tends to move is your body's best
inference about how not to have pain and
how to move given your body's current
biomechanical constraints about the
muscles what they've learned and the
nerves how they've learned. In other
words, functional compensation
drives structural adaptation and then
structural adaptation constrains further
changes in patterns of motion that
change functional compensation that
change structural adaptation in how you
move and how you balance in an ongoing
spiral of those five concept. Taking a
posture picture, seeing how somebody is
standing with the instruction of stand
tall, show me your best posture, take a
step or two in place, just stand tall.
And then taking a picture of that can be
powerful to engage them in making a
change in the body. At the end of this
class, I'm going to show you two basic
and simple exercises you can do to
strengthen your balance and your body's
alignment. The protocol is to first have
someone stand tall with best posture.
Take a step or two in place.
Look at them from the front. Take a
picture. Face to the left. Take a
picture. Face back to the front. Have
them stand tall. Lift the left foot up
in the air and lift the right foot up in
the air. It's really easy. One step at a
time. And what you're looking at is
where their head is, where their torso,
where their pelvis, and where their feet
are. And we get into this in detail with
clinicians. This is not the place for
that. This is from the paper. And
looking at those four zones of postural
mass, how they're balancing and the
symmetry, especially on this, the front
view of left and right leg coming up
look something like this.
A simple set of pictures. This comes
from a paper about changes in
interception in mindbody therapies for
chronic pain. This is a systematic
review and meta analysis. Intraception
is the perception of physical sensations
from inside the body. When they're
incorrect, there tends to be more pain.
Correcting them reduces the pain. And if
when you're looking at an intraceptive
posture picture, if someone's always
leaning to the left, if they're lifting
their left foot and their right foot,
and they're always leaning to the left,
that's saying that their perception of
where their body is in space isn't
correct.
Especially if they're not hurting. If
they're hurting and it's compensatory,
that's your turn. But when they shift
the way that I am, that's saying that I
have changed my body so that I am
incorrect at where my body is in space.
And that's why systematically focusing
attention to strengthen that weak link,
which is what we'll do at the end of
this class for just a minute with two
exercises can make such a big difference
not just in how your body looks, but in
how your body feel.
Some examples. Young lady standing tall.
Left and right leg coming up. She looks
pretty good. Here's a young lady that's
also standing tall. You'll notice the
pattern of how she's bouncing her body
on the left leg coming up and on the
right leg coming up. She's going way off
to her left side with her body with her
right knee is going out when she's
raising her right leg. Left side she's
keeping much more vertical. The ability
to maintain that verticality
says something about how her body has
learned to move at a very young age. She
may have had an injury. This came from a
clinician. Hopefully, the patients
followed through and she's done well.
But the fact that a child this young was
brought to a doctor says something. By
the way, look at that first picture.
Look at the child's feet. How they're
rotated off to one side when she's
trying to stand tall. That gives you a
hint that there's been some asymmetry
trained in that body.
And it's something that especially at a
young age can be improved. Here's a
young man told to stand tall. You'll
notice he's internally rotating his
hands so his palms are facing backwards.
That's not standing tall. That's not
attention. That's a child that's
probably been using a whole lot of tech.
A clinical posture picture is an
experiential perception of that
expressed verticality of I'm standing
tall. And this is why it's an expression
of information coming in from the
outside and the inside. and your
perceptions and predictions. The
predictions part of this is so
important. Correcting posture is not
about telling someone to stand taller.
It's about making the body feel the
predictions differently and
reprogramming that step by step. This is
why active inference is such a powerful
concept. Those compensatory patterns,
the things that can be changed are
inferences about what's going to happen
in the body. A lot of times this is
called dysfunction. The simple way of
looking at it, if someone's hurting, the
waiting of the inputs coming into the
body are shifted. You're not thinking
about it. Your body just reflexively is
changes. Your brain is such an amazing
tool because it can adapt to different
situations. Humans have a great
adaptation potential. And there's an old
saying, your greatest strength is your
greatest weakness. Our flexibility means
that we can be trained unintentionally
into moving in ways that we don't want
to be doing when we think about it
rationally because that's what our body
has been trained to do. Our attention
focusing on one link at a time, one
piece of the puzzle at a time can
modulate biomechanic efficiency. It's
not a one shot I fixed. It's one thing
that can be changed. Which is why we
talk about incorporating biobehavioral
strategies, the NMS pros to help people
live well in a tech world. Don't want to
let technology ruin your brain or your
body cuz they're connected. Before we go
on to showing you exercises that I'd
like you to do, I'd like to strongly
encourage you have someone take your
posture picture because the emotional
impact of I thought I was standing tall
from the front, from the side, and on
one leg balance is powerful. Clinicians
know it. I know it from working with
thousands of people. And what I'd like
to ask you to consider once you've done
this for yourself, because if you are a
scientist, you're looking at this from a
scientific point of view, as we all
should be. If there's any part of your
research that you're using human
subjects, I'd love to talk to you about
helping you incorporate more systematic
implementations of an interceptive
posture picture as another way to get a
window into how that body and individual
is predicting actions for their body and
how simple actions can change that by
working with that person and engaging
that person, by educating them about
their body and how it moves. This is
what we talk about in stand tall of
longer. Your body is designed to move.
That's the first posture principle,
motion. The second is balance. Posture
is how you're balancing your body and
it's also how you're balancing your
mind. A lot of the implications of the
word posture is not physical. It's your
view on the world. How you're looking at
things. Where do you stand? And how you
balance your body in space and over time
is what we're retraining when we're
focusing attention moment by moment on a
portion of the body and how it relates
and links to other parts of the body in
order to balance. Because your body
moves in patterns of motion that follow
the path of least resistance of how you
balance and align to move in patterns.
If it hurts to move this way, if it's
mechanically constrained, if that's the
habit that's caused muscles to get
tighter and weaker in one direction and
stronger in another direction, that's
going to be the way that your body
learns to move. Initially compensating
you learn to move in the pattern that
you teach it. But then over time where
this becomes locked in things become
stiffer. It doesn't move as well.
Ultimately you can't move in that
direction. I just move like this where
changes in posture and changes in motion
cause your body to physically change. It
becomes a spiral. It keeps on building
on itself over life. My firm experience
and belief and hope and efforts drive
towards the knowledge that active
inference informed education linked with
individualized self-care is an approach
that builds both cognitive understanding
that ties together things like pain
science and cognitive behavior therapy
on a base level. Not therapy from a
point of view of your childhood and
things like that, but being able to
control your body in an iterative
ongoing way, arc by arc to strengthen
predictive accuracy to improve sensory
perception to have more accurate
processing and therefore prediction
of the motor expression of how your body
moves and then creating a way to track
that just by taking an interceptive
posture picture. We have a new course
that I literally just finished.
Integrating intraception and biomechanic
prediction of where your body is is part
of what we're creating as a
biiobehavioral approach to working with
neuromuscular skeleal professional. It's
also a way for psychological
professionals that are working with
chronic back pain to help and to be
working with people who work with
chronic back pain from a neuromuscular
skeletal point of view. That's the big
focus as well as neck pain and
concussion issues. I'd like to show you
two attentional focus exercises you can
do yourself once you've taken a posture
picture to see how your body is to try
to connect your perception of how your
whole body is balancing with the outcome
of if you can balance better. You feel
your body is balancing better and you
can stand on one foot and stay there for
more than 5 seconds, more than 10
seconds. And as quantified by an
interceptive posture picture of
observing the deviations of your body
connecting that balance one with two
parts of your body alignment where your
head is and where your torso is. We call
it forward head posture.
You may call it tech neck. But if you
spend a lot of time in front of your
computer, which most scientists and
researchers do, you'll probably find
that your head is more forward of your
body than your parents' head was when
they were your age. in terms of some of
the issues going on. If you take a
picture of your kids, how they're
standing and how their resting posture
is as opposed to
yours is now, and if your kid's posture
is worse than your posture is, it'll
give you some insight on where the world
is going.
This young lady is a model. She had no
back pain, no neck pain, college
student. We did a event taking posture
pictures. I told her to stand tall, show
me your best posture, and just relax.
Stand tall. And this is what she did.
Any way you measure where the head is
versus the torso, from the back margin,
from the center of mass, her head is
translating forward. And you'll notice
it's also going up. It's translating up.
And that translation up is what happens
because the muscles in the back part of
the head become shorter. they compensate
shorter ultimately adapting shorter to
restrain and constrain how the head is
balanced on the torso. So looking at
those four zones of postural mass, those
four posture zones of head, torso,
pelvis, lower extremity, the very first
alignment exercise is wall lean. And
it's really, really easy because all
you're doing is having somebody lean
against the wall with their feet a foot
away from the wall so that their pelvis,
their torso, and their head align with
that vertical wall. You can do this at
home with any vertical wall. But you
want to take your feet away because you
want to reduce the confounding variables
of feeling where your head is over your
torso. So, first aligning the pelvis and
the torso against the wall and keeping
the head level. Look straight ahead.
What you're dialing into is your
perception of is your head truly level
in space. Have someone take a clear
picture of your body from the side. It's
a way to discern functional compensation
from structural adaptation. So looking
at her over here, you'll notice this.
She was standing looking straight ahead,
thinking that her head is level. If you
looked at it from the back of her body,
the margin from the back of her torso to
the back of her head is quite a bit
forward of it. And if you look at the
face, it's looking up in the air.
When I looked at her like this and I
said, "Levelle your head and push it
back towards the wall." That's what she
did
when I went up to her and said, "Pull
your head more forward. Level your head
and externally put her head to level and
let her push it back to the wall." And I
made her stop at the limit to explore
the limit of that functionality, what
the Marco blanket is, of that prediction
and stopping there. This is where this
body truly is. Then told her to take
five breaths.
She was able to do it with a lot of
focus. And that focus on keeping it
level at the limit is what it takes to
change bodies. Having her do that for
five slow breaths three times a day will
make a difference if she's being good
about it, if she's being correct about
it. And that's why working with someone
to help you, could be a family member,
to keep your head level as you're
pressing back gently, not hard. Don't
force it. Because you want to remold
tissue that's sensitive in the body,
fascia. Don't push it. You want to be
gentle. Gentle works far better than
hard in this instance. You want to feel
the tension. And when you breathe into
it, it'll give a little bit. The
imperative, what we call the must or the
must's try, is to keep the head level.
If you're looking at a side view, if
your forehead is behind your chin,
you're probably tilting up. If you're
away from the wall, putting something
behind your head, a pillow, an
inflatable ball to get a feeling of
where the wall is and pushing back
against that very gently to build the
awareness to retrain that control.
Awareness and control of your body in
your environment is the center of the
posturemonth.org or ACE campaign which
is what we're behind to improve people's
ability to connect with their body
beginning with the awareness of the body
and then strengthening the balance your
posture just how you balance your body.
This is what we're looking at with an
intraceptive posture picture just
looking at how someone's balancing. How
do you strengthen that? Holding that for
those same five breaths when you're
balancing with your body aligned to your
body's perception. So, finding a wall,
standing tall, and dialing into what
that feels like, and then locking in
your knees, standing tall, engaging your
core, open your chest up, look straight
ahead, standing tall. Kind of feel how
that feels. Touch the wall. And keeping
your outside leg locked, standing tall.
Simply lift the leg that's between you
and the wall. And you don't want to lean
into the wall. You don't want to lean
away from the wall. You want to focus on
standing tall, but you do want to barely
touch the wall. You're going to want to
say, "Okay, I can do it without it. I
can do it without it." And the moment
you do it without it, you've lost that
feeling of inside your body. The moment
you go from, I'm maintaining my balance,
you're coming away from the feeling of
standing tall, standing tall, touching
the wall, lifting the leg, and barely
touch the wall. How light can you touch
the wall and standing tall? and focus on
the standing tall because the
information coming in to your body from
that little bit of touch is the link to
reality that lets you strengthen how
you're standing that will then help you
strengthen your balance. Tying those two
links together. Simply tying those two
links together is a huge first step in
strengthening balance and alignment of
your posture. And it's also an indicator
that you can use when you take a posture
picture, an intraceptive posture picture
to validate the alignment of that
objectively externally. Doing that along
with people's bodies internally is a way
to create changes in how people use
their body in everything that they do.
A lot of times people don't want to do
this because I don't want to see it.
It's too too scary.
Herbert Spencer was a noted British
philosopher and sociologist. The
profoundest of all infidelities is the
fear that the truth will be bad.
I hope to hear from you. I hope to work
with you. If you have any questions,
drop me an email. My name is Dr. Steven
Weineer. Thank you for having me here.
And I look forward to working with the
active inference community with a
clinical perspective to help people
stand taller and move well. Have a great
day.
All right, we're back. Next is Observer
Theory by Sam Sanchol. This is a 31
minute pre-recorded video. Here it goes.
Hi, big thank you to the Active
Inference Institute for having me
today. I'll be talking about observer
theory in the context of books really.
I'll start by outlining the history of
these ideas then explain how this
extension provides a first stab at a
general model for any observer sampling
of computational universe.
This framework proposes a resolution to
discrete versus continuous dilemma.
It handles cross domain causation i.e
mind body problem and begins to quantify
the novelty of surprise observers see.
It also formalizes a terminal object
that stops infinite regress in this
model and enables sampling utilizing the
category theoretic formulas developed by
Gard and Riwala.
This extension of observed theory is
built on the foundational work of Steven
War from Jonathan Goris
and
start with a big brief explanation of
the ruler's
physics project posits the underlying
fabric of reality is a vast screen space
of all possible computations.
Observers like us sample reality from
normal structure.
Recent formalizations
have frameless in category theoretic
terms.
A key insight is that observers are not
godsight views i.e. there is no view
from nowhere and there is no true
objectivity.
Wolram has pointed out that observers
leverage something called computational
reducibility which basically means they
pick out regular lumps in bru and
equivalence relations between them to
compress information.
Essentially, we only see what our brain
can simplify.
Wolf from also emphasized that we act as
if we're stable.
We assume we persist through time and
stay roughly in the same place, which
let us treat space and time as coherent
backdrops for anything we say about
observation.
These subconscious assumptions are
exactly what we capture by positing this
background object
and by formalizing the observer in this
framework.
From this model to get reality as we
experience it, you need an observer to
sample the brad.
Here they formalized second order
cybernetic systems within the structure.
The rouad updates state to state
and observers sample between state
updates creating a single thread of
experience.
They coarse grain a wondering amount of
computational complexity to something
manageable which outputs everything you
see around you.
Furthermore, observers hold an internal
model that they update through their
cycling which helps them predict things
within the real or in other words find
pockets of computation reducibility.
Notion of a background object is a bit
vague so I'll clarify. We can use a
simple example of an observer looking at
the sky.
That person will use fixed references
like the horizon to interpret what they
see.
In physics, it's usually background
independent.
But here we introduce this object to
capture what an observer takes as given.
This could be their internal world
model. It could be what they already
produced from the ruby.
Wer emphasizes that observers make
strong assumptions.
For instance, we assume we persist
through time and observe roughly the
same things every moment.
This is akin to having some background
reference that doesn't disappear.
By explicitly modeling a background
object, we codify the idea that
observers always compare new inputs
against unassumed stable context.
Historically, Wolf's writings on
observer theory note that observers
correspond to patches of regularity in
reality.
In other words, observers live on stable
maps in the grand computational universe
cond
before introducing new ideas I'll
summarize minimal observant.
Think of it like a very basic robot or a
thermostat. It has three jobs. One, set
something from the outside. two, store
and update an internal record of what it
says. And three, act on the world based
on that.
The authors led by RCA stress the
simplest observer must have a B in
distinguishing itself from the Safari.
For example, the thermostat senses
temperature,
compares it to a set point in its
memory, and turns a heater off.
This act of observation is reduced to a
feedback loop.
In their words, a minimum observer
perceives external states, updates
internal configurations, and generates
an action for a closed feedback loop.
This simple model captures the
functional essence of observation
without any assumptions of consciousness
or scale. It serves as a foundation for
our larger model for generalized obser.
Now embed this minimal observer into the
full rub. In the extension we define an
observer as a function
s
takes r to r.
But what does that mean?
Well, we know that Rudiad is the full
category of every possible computational
universe.
But observers have limitations.
They can only sample some parts of this
universe.
The fun XO captures this starting.
It takes each state or transition in R
and maps it to what the observer
actually perceives.
In effect, it forgets or forces details
the observer lacks the capacity to
distinguish between
the result is row the rat for the
observer and that's a function that and
that takes the fun so and applies it to
the full rad. It implies the limit of
the accessible rulad for that observer.
Different observers can have different
functions and thus experience different
worlds.
In plain language, the fun encodes the
observer's hardware and bikes reality.
This makes explicit Wim's idea that our
physics is a slice of the determined by
us as observers.
Next, we'll spell out the constraints to
define the observer.
Any observer has finite computational
resources which we call boundedness. So
it can only process phenomena of limited
complexity.
Formally, we sensate sample only if the
bandness exceeds a threshold which could
relate to a processing limit or an
observer's memory.
Likewise, instantaneous or two brief
events vanish, we include a persistence
threshold,
meaning that the state must last long
enough to register for the observer.
Finally, an observer doesn't care about
absolutely everything. It only notes
relevant features.
We encode this via a boolean.
Only if the relevance is true is the
information from that state integrated
into the observer's internal model.
For a human,
we can take the example of a bright
flash. It might be relevant to them in
the dark, but random noise might not.
Together
Bandon's persistence and relevance
filter the ruler and the observable rat
to a much smaller set of possible states
that the observer can act can actually
experience at a given time.
Field of observation is simply what the
observer actually perceives the time.
It's a subset of the observable really
that passes all three filters.
In other words, this field contains
exactly those states that are small
enough, stable enough, and meaningful
enough for the observer to see them. You
can think of this field as the data in
your current sensory bite.
For a human, this field might consist of
objects and colors you can see in your
immediate field of view. It's not
everything in the world. That would be
the observer's total accessible reading.
It's what you're effectively attending
to. Now, this field is the basis for
everything else in box. We define
information content and information
integration over this field.
The diagram on the page shows that in
the context of the RUDI ad.
The pink lines show the field and the
red dotted lines show the full Ruby ad
that the observer could access.
I as a subset and it's the bit they're
focusing on right now. Now we quantify
novelty or here surprise of each piece
of observed data.
We define the information content as the
total entropy of a state X less whatever
the observer can already predict or has
compressed.
You can also say made computationally
reducible from prior observations.
So the information content is
essentially the net new information the
sampling X offers.
If it's zero, the observer gains no new
information. If it's large, then it is
novel or surprising.
I this directly mirrors FEP but
generalizes it to any observer.
In other words, our observer is trying
to minimize the information content on
average. We tend to seek environments
where surprise is limited. Why is that?
It saves some of our bounded
computational power.
We'll use this information content to
build a measure of the overall
information the observer sites.
Get a big picture of sense of the
observer's experience. We define
integrated information as the sum of the
information content over everything the
observer's view.
The formula tells us how much new
information the observer has coherently
integrated at this moment and the moment
being the state update time within the
frame model.
It's analogist to integrated information
in consciousness studies but again
applies to any class of observer.
If integrated information is high the
observer is experiencing a highly
structured interrelated set of inputs.
If it's low, the inputs appear to be
more random or distributed.
Integrated information aims for a
concrete observer centered measure of
how complex and unified the observed
information content is.
In practice, maximizing integrated
information in this formalism is seen as
an observer's general telos akin
anthropomorphically to having a rich and
meaningful experience of the world.
One of the biggest puzzles is how
discrete computation can give rise to
the continuous space and time we
experience dayto-day. Our answer is that
the continuity is an observer con is
observer constructed to save the
computational boundedness of a given
observer.
We formalize this by giving each
observer a measure indicated by by U0
over its field. Intuitively, this weighs
different samples according to the
observer's sensitivity to them.
For example, humans weigh central vision
more heavily than peripheral.
Consequently, the observer's perceived
continuum is given by integrating the
discrete information content against the
measure.
In simple terms, the brakes filling in
the gaps.
This aims to resolve the discrete
continuous gaping of the model. The
underlying rouad is all frames and the
observer's mind interpolates to get a
smooth movie.
Wolf noted that when done properly
there's no conflict.
Space time could be a construct of
observers called spring.
So with this we can comfortably use
continuous math in the observer's
perspective
knowing it emerges from underlying
discrete expiry measure function.
making the scoop of continuous idea
more. Let's look at a few anchorages.
Imagine watching a movie
and
the film is a sequence of static frames,
but because they're shown rapidly, you
the watcher in the cinema perceive few
fluid motion. Similarly, the riad
provides discrete frames of reality in
its hypograph and the observer's mind
generates motion between them. Another
example is the blind screen vision. Each
eye has a spot with no photo receptors
where the optic nerve leaves directly.
If you position an object there, it
disappears.
You instead just see the back if nothing
missing. Your brain literally fills in
the gaps.
That's the observer theory extension in
action. We don't perceive raw data. We
perceive an inter interpreted scene.
You could also vote Newton's bucket. We
see water's surface fall under rotation
because our perception assumes a fixed
background.
These examples illustrate the continuity
and cohes
in the formalism. This is captured by
the measure integrating the discrete
samples. The theory posits that
continuous reality is an observe
construction to save Q.
Let's move up from the mechanics of
observing constructing continuity to
what that continuity produces
the layer domains of reality as
experienced by our observers.
The paper proposes the observer's
operationalized continuity not in a
single domain but across four nested
layers each expanding in degrees of
representational freedom and coherence.
In short in simple language this means
that higher domains are more
informationally dense and back by less
rules than lower domains.
It should be noted at this point that
this decomposition can be done in any
way a researcher chooses even within the
domains that I posit or for entirely
different sets of domains suitable for
other classes of service.
The following decomposition utilizes
humans cognitive layers
i.e. it's an morphing but others could
work.
I'll walk through the layers one by one.
The layer with the most rules is the
physical dome.
Here computation appears tightly coupled
with causality and energy conservation.
Think of classical mechanics field
theory and graphs. Everything is closed
and coherent and information of
evolution aligns with notions like
closure. This is where standard physical
computation lives. where off physics
lives at least until you get back to the
point.
Next, we'll move to what we might call
proto subjective space.
The valuation or domain into these
systems with observerdriven sailings
such as attention, prioritization or
inference.
This is where concepts like active
inference emerge.
Here the observer doesn't just track
physical states but values complexity
creating meaning from a computational
structure.
The third layer is the symbolic and it's
the world of form abstraction. The
symbolic domain allows for rule-based
transformations independent of their
instantiation.
Things like language, formal logic, and
mathematics.
Observers in this domain don't just
respond to inputs but create
representational continuity chaining
symbols into expressions, proofs and
meaning structures that can be detached
from any one physical or emotional such
valuational context.
For observers like us, this domain
enables coherence across the physical
valuation documents. It can describe
physical systems or encode structures.
is the seed of meta theoretic insight.
Lastly, we reach the edge,
a space of maximal modeling freedom that
we've that we've turned the minimally
constrained domain.
This is a domain where the usual
coherence rules of symbolic logic break
down. It's a place where we can talk
about paradoxes, infinite regress,
nonwellment sets, things that we can
imagine but that we can't really
instantiate or can't hopefully describe
in words.
It approaches the boundary of what we
can access.
From a categorical standpoint, this is
the domain that that gets closest to
topological closure.
Observers are capable of traversing all
paths and equival equivalences subject
to identity even those incompatible in
lower domains.
This is also where our categorical
terminal object true affinity enters.
It's a poetic limit object that closes
the space of coherent interpretation.
The hierarchical layering is crucial for
modeling cross domain observers.
one to for example infer value from
physics
or deploy symbolic logic to manage
valuation hierarchies.
It also allows us to rigorously define
how continuity and therefore computation
means something different depending on
the specific obser focus.
Why do we talk about the hierarchies?
It's because one of the central aims of
the extension is to show that multimatic
causation is natural in an observer in
the general obser framework.
There's no magic
because all levels observers like us
have access to are embedded in a single
structure. We really have a single
causal chain and thread through all of
those domains.
We attempt a formalization across domain
causation
for a state D in domain I and a state P
in domain J. There is a causal
relationship if we can find a path of
transitions in the observable area
connecting state T to state P. The path
is a sequence of states across domains.
In categorical language, we have a
process category where objects are
states and morphisms are processes.
A morphism from state P to state P
spanning different domains is a cross
influence.
So as an example, a decision you make in
the mental domain either with valuation
or symbolic logic can abomorphically
lead to a muscle muscular contraction in
the physical domain via the composition
of funus between those domains.
Think about it as a map connecting to
another map within one giant.
There's nothing a causal about it. is
just one connected multi-step morphism
in the whole of observer constructed
reality.
In the observer theory extension,
causation has two main flavors.
Formal causation corresponds to a higher
level pattern from a less constrained
domain imposing constraints on a lower
level. For instance, the blueprint of an
intention shaping fiscal act. You could
use the example of an architect's plans
for a building that don't instantiate
specific materials, which is the shape
of the structure. That limits what those
builders in the physical domain can do
to put it together, but it doesn't
determine every piece of that puzzle.
Efficient causation is the usual physics
style cause effect like you're expiring.
Mathematically we saw causor morphisms
by how their constraint levels compare
i.e. how many rules
are required to output said morphism.
If a state has less constraint and goes
to one with more we'll call it formal
course. If it's the other way around
it's efficient.
This picture shows clearly that there
are just two directions of the of one
unified structure. Crucially,
mind body effects are simply morphisms
in the observable ruler involving
different domains. We don't need new
laws. We don't need any magic. For
example, deciding to pick up a cup.
A mental domain morphism gets met by
functions through the symbolic and then
the physical domains eventually.
The laws of physics are untouched. We're
just following morphisms in the rulad
under a particular observer's mapping.
Recently Eric V has formalized a
mathematical model of the interactions
of micro macros scale causation that we
feel supports this view.
Let me tie these ideas together.
The core new quantity we have is the
information content an observer gains
with state X. This is explicitly tied to
how an observer reduces uncertainty.
It generalizes for instance and others
ideas and minim.
An observer will naturally prefer
observations that minimize a new
information because they are cheaper
computationally and enable more of their
bounded resources
to have availability to search more
potentially increasing global and local
integrated information.
The sum of integrated information tells
us how rich the experience is. This
makes observer dependent novelty precise
for any class of observer. What is new
to one observer may be old to another
because each has a different sampling
function even if they share the same
observable rad.
For in through intuition you can think
of identical twins.
They have the same observer really add
and exactly the same bodies but their
divergent cause histories mean their
sampling in front of them works
differently. Thus this framework lets us
begin to quantify novelty and surprise
in a way that depends on the individual
observer filters.
Finally we tackle the question of
closure.
Is there an infinite hall of mirrors of
observers observing observers?
We answer by introducing a special
object called true infinity which plays
the role of a terminal object in our
textbook. Concrete TI has the property
that every observer
maps uniquely to it. In everyday
language, you can think of this as the
ultimate perspective.
Our mind of God is not reachable or
observable by any finite observer.
But here it's the source of all rules
that generate the ruby. It provides a
big end of the line. So we're not stuck
with an endless hierarchy that's
computationally intractable.
I at some point everything just makes
sense.
As we summarize in the paper, TI acts
like an undershirt viewpoint or a
unification or integration of all
underlying information.
This ensures the framework is
mathematically complete. Every diagram
has a limit
and there's no paradox of what observes
the observe.
True infinity is essentially the
background frame or ground truth that
all observers implicitly assume but
can't prove or fully attain.
Does it feel like conceptually?
Here it's a placeholder for ultimate
computational completion.
Imagine that every computational process
and every observer is eventually seen
from some advantage. True infinity is
the vantage where everything comes
together.
You could call it the first mover or
even a godlike viewpoint. But in this
formalism is strictly a mathematical
object.
Because of it, our model doesn't have
two sense.
There is an absolute frame hidden in the
background, an unachievable fixed ground
against which everything else is
defined. It shuts down the infinite
regress problem. Nothing is left angly
and philosophy.
There's an ultimate to the observed
matter. So it serves as both poetic
closure and a precise mathematical
capstone of a framework that aligns with
the Garden RC formalism on the
construction of the Rubad. Simply put,
closure in the formal model enables the
Rubad to generate geometry and then
through a long chain generate physics.
Without it, we don't have a structure we
can do things on. It is no longer an
infinite group. is an
surprise the observ
author's view
treated as stere
by formalizing observers of a broad
computational universe and by
introducing observer dependent measures
and information metrics we can start to
reconcile subject and object
In our view, it doesn't introduce any
contradictions with known physics.
Instead, explains why
macros world looks from our point.
I believe this new tool to think about
how consciousness and business complain
sandbox
move forward. This framework and guided
segments in neuroscience or in the
design of AI about how build reality.
As just one example, if you increase
observers computational boundedness
or increase it,
you could use say height speed, we could
expand it observable.
We might see phenomenology
without particles.
The key takeaway is that is that
observation is fundamental computation.
By modeling themselves formally we can
better understand physics, cognition and
their intersection.
It still blows my mind 100 years after Q
there is still no general formal
observable
shortly I'm publishing a new paper that
extends the extends the ideas of this
paper of this model to theology ethics
telos and human superructures
met
through
Last I want to thank James Steven
for all that help
enjoy the All
right. Sorry about the audio issues on
that last one. Thank you for that very
interesting talk. All right. One second
before the next one.
My name is
All right, next up is exterceptive bias
belief updating in the global model Jim
Freda. This is a 51minute pre-recorded
video.
My name is Jim Freda and I am very very
pleased to be here for the 2025 applied
active inference symposium. I want to
thank the organizers
and for being so open in their
acceptance policy and letting someone
like me present.
I am a deep tissue structural body
worker, a manual therapist, an
embodiment teacher and a somatic
historian and social theorist. My
interest is not in uh computation,
computational neuroscience, mathematics,
um computer science
and um physics.
But I have a deep interest in a model of
life and especially in the perceptual
mechanics of a model of life from a
somatic perspective.
My interest in active inference derives
from my focus on what is called the deep
core myofascial
synergy which is the anatomy the
synergistic and very uh new anatomy of
our axial line our postural core.
Sherington describes this system as
propriception or self-awareness. And
when I came across Sharington's
u marvelous text, the integrative action
of the nervous system and his neural
architecture of the animal as a whole.
It really blew me away. It really
changed everything about how I was
working with people, working with
myself, and understanding my own
self-image and the world. When I came
across Carl Friston's version, updated
version of the model, I was really blown
away, very excited, and I just love the
work that the active inference community
is doing. I do not have computational,
neuroscientific,
uh, computer scientific kinds of
critiques and suggestions to offer. But
my field is anatomy and from the
perspective of anatomy and especially
the self-organizing, selfaware,
selfbalancing,
self organizing and self-directed
generative anatomy of the human body. I
do have a lot to say.
This is a new kind of anatomy. Um,
for the purposes of today's talk, I'm
calling it cybernetic anatomy in the
cybernetic tradition or we can call it
synergistic myofascial anatomy. And this
is really the key to understanding the
motoric element of the deep field in the
model. The motoric element of the
physical homeostatic function of active
inference itself.
We're going to talk about a few major
points here. I'm going to go over in
addition to some guided body meditations
that I hope that you will find novel and
um enlightening.
We're going to spend some time reviewing
Sherington's original model, the neural
architecture of the animal as a whole. I
have a big section on that. There's an
awful lot of text. I'm going to
summarize it, but I put all the text
there so that you can go back and do
your research because a lot of the
belief updating that we're going to be
doing in this talk today involves the
major contours the global outline of the
superordinate model which is three
receptor fields exterception,
interosception and proprioception.
Now the core node proprioception I argue
has been under theorized and
propriception is the least well
understood of the three different
perceptual systems. The model we
understand contains two blankets. But I
want to give the inner blanket the outer
surface of the inner self in the
nucleus. What would be the very
importantly mechanuctive
nuclear membrane? The lamina membrane of
the outer surface of the inner component
of the cell as an intuitive
uh intuitive example of of a model of
the model. uh that is uh by analogy uh
we can also find in our cells in our
body. This motoric element
has been under theorized and it's
actually missing from the model.
Proprioception
lacks a motoric element. The deep field
lacks motoric anatomy.
Um
what
we're going to find is exterceptive
bias. And we're going to talk about that
in terms of the blanket politics in the
model that if these two perceptual
fields have agency and um self have
identity which it's clear that they do
and theoretically which they must then
we can talk about their relationship in
terms of blanket politics. And I'm going
to call up call forth both Carl
Friston's disconnection hypothesis and
Gregory Bateson's double bind as a way
to discuss that.
I'd like to invite you into
a guided meditation on
on the grip on how to get a grip on the
reach. The reach, the arm, the forlim of
any animal is something that we study to
understand its unique adaptive uh
potential in its environment. The human
upper extremity, the human form, the arm
and the hand of course are are very very
special and allow us a tremendous amount
of control and sensitivity
uh within our environment.
And this has been studied hundreds and
thousands of times by motor control
theorists and neurologists and and uh
biomechanists
and it's something that we should really
be very familiar with. Out here in the
hand is the exterceptive grip. What I
want us to focus on today
is the proprioceptive prior which is
located in the armpit.
Now that armpit is formed by a single
large
bone called a scapula.
Now this scapula you'll notice is shaped
exactly like a grip. And your hand fits
around it perfectly.
And indeed there are five intrinsic
muscles arrayed over this that literally
grab onto it above and below with their
tendonous insertions wrapping around the
the the shoulder joint the ro forming
the rotator cuff. And this is the system
that anchors the arm to the body, but
also that manages that originary kind of
joint, the shoulder joint that manages
it and maintains centration and balance
and stability in that very insecure
joint. So, we're going to reach out with
our hand and if there's someone there,
grasp their hand gently. If there isn't
someone there that if you have a cell
phone or a coffee cup, grasp that and
feel how your little finger is like a
hook that secures that object in your
hand. How the thumb coming over the top
is a kind of a clamp and how you get a
grip in the exterepive
system reaching out into the world. But
even though this is the applied active
inference conference, I'm going to
suggest that we come back,
not reach outward, but reach inward into
the armpit, not the shoulder. Now, this
is again an extraceptive knuckle, a
superficial structure. Um, and a rather
insignificant
motorically speaking and perceptually
speaking structure that is not well
innervated. We're going to come into
this very sensitive armpit. The armpit
is a product of
the scapula's attachment on the back of
the ribs.
And
those propricoceptive movements,
postural movements are long, slow,
continuous and mild.
They really are the expression of active
inference in the mortal substrate.
So we have this grip in the hand with a
parallel or a mirror synergy an inverse
homology in the scapula in the armpit
and see if you can feel that and just as
an exercise let's organize our arm with
our shoulder. Let's use the neck and the
shoulder to lift the arm which is very
common and results in all kinds of
pathologies like impingement syndrome
and frozen shoulder. Instead, let's come
down deep within the armpit and bring
that elbow in contact with the ribs and
come up into the concavity,
the sensitive pit of
the the gradient of the armpit.
and feel a hand. Literally imagine that
as you have a hand out in the world, you
have a hand reaching inward in the body.
A literal hand grasping that scapula.
Now
that hand, that sense of a grip
wraps around the bony scapula with its
fingertips, the tendonous fingertips of
those muscles wrapping around the
shoulder joint like fingertips around a
doorork knob forming the rotator cuff
and giving it giving that insecured
glenoumeral joint the stability and
centration that it needs for this
amazing range of motion. that we have
that comes from deep within the
proprioceptive prior of the armpit of
the concavity. And indeed the body has a
system of major concavities on the axial
line all with this kind of a function.
And those five intrinsic muscles really
create a a synergy, a mirror synergy, an
inverse homology that the brain finds
very easy to work with. Now the last
thing that I want to say is to come out
of that meditation and to look here at
this theory. These are some recent very
interesting motor control studies of the
reach and the grasp. And you'll see here
outlined in green, I've highlighted a
graphic from each study. Now, this is
universal. Every single motor control
study originates in the shoulder, the
knuckle of the shoulder on the one hand
and on the other hand in the in the grip
and attempts to calculate proprioception
from this very false
structure.
Instead, if we reach deeper within and
understand the motoric anatomy
of the proprioceptive of the deep field
of proprioception, I wonder how that
would change our studies and our
research, our thinking about
proprioceptive prior.
We're going to take a a few minutes here
to do a deep dive and I have a number of
slides coming up with a lot of content.
We're going to do a deep dive into the
model and we're going to go back to the
origin, the 1906 origin, Charles
Sharington's neural architecture of the
animal as a whole.
And it's Charles Sharington. Charles
Sharington was a great scholar, a
tremendous scientist and a man of
letters. And when he named something, he
really thought about it and he his names
have weight. And we've gone and really
sh renamed or reinterpreted redefined
the neural architecture of the animal as
a whole without considering
the original model itself. So, we're
going to spend some time going into
that. Exterosception,
interosception, and proprioception were
all words that Sharington created with a
great deal of intentionality and
rationale.
Now it's a perceptual model but it's a
spatial model which is great for somatic
u thinkers like myself because
kinesthesia the muscle sense somatics is
a spatial form of awareness where we're
not looking to ask why or how but we're
asking where where do we go in our
experience with our perceptual faculties
in order to encounter those affordances
in the environment and within ourselves
that possess the information theoretic
content that we need. This is the nature
of of living systems and working with
complex self uh organizing and
self-aware living systems.
Now the
model has two great separate fields.
There's an outside and an inside. The
debate really is what's the inside.
And what modern scholarship has done is
taken interosception,
exterception, interosception and and
made the very simplistic and naive
assumption that well that's the outside
and the inside tarot must mean inside.
And this isn't really true. Sharington
referred to the deep field repeatedly
and proprioception is the deep field or
the core in the model.
Now, um
I'm going to go ahead and read this
third paragraph. Multisellular animals
regarded broadly throughout a vast range
of animal forms are cellular masses
which present to the environment a
surface sheet of cells and underneath
that surface sheet a bulk made up of
cells more or less screened from the
environment by the surface sheet
overlying them.
Many of the agencies which the
environment by which the environment
acts on the organism do not penetrate to
the mass of cells forming the
organisms's deeper part.
The various stimuli expend themselves as
stimuli
at the surface sheet and do not
penetrate into the depth of the
organism. So Sharington is really trying
to talk about a part of the body that is
insulated most fully from the outside
world, the deep field, the core
proprioception. And he identified that
as a mechanical system, a muscular
system, the postural system,
compressions and strains produced by
muscles. Not only that, but
um
not only that, but this inner
receptor field perceptual system is not
other aware. It is most selfaware.
Let's take a look at
Sharington's arguments around
interosception
and the surface field again. The surface
field is broadly subdivisible. Its
subdivisions are too.
So the external field is cutaneous.
But the inner surface then would be
elementary. Anything that passes through
the boundary sheet of an organism has to
be processed for example by the
cytoplasm in the cell by the elementary
canal by the visca by the gut what
sharington called the kitchen. This is
not the deep field. This is still
something that although shielded from
the outside still is basically working
with processing sensing stimuli that
come from the outside.
Now,
it's important to recognize, I think,
and to take a moment with this bottom
paragraph to just go ahead and look that
external is special and important in a
way in that, and these words I think are
really, really nice. It's facing outward
on the general environment and it
receives freely and it receives and has
received for countless ages the full
stream I love this language the full
stream of all the varied agencies
forever pouring on it freely from the
outside world so there's a bit of a
basis with exterceptive bias in terms of
the perceptual fields exterception has
to always be operative from the moment
moment of birth onward. And this is one
good explanation for bias in the system.
But the real bias that we're facing is
an accentuation of of prop
interosception and a diminishment of
propriception. So let's look at
Sherington. The stimuli effective on the
receptors of the deep field differ
fundamentally from those on either
subdivision of the surface field.
they are adapted for excitation by
changes going forward in the or organism
itself. Now in interosception in the gut
the excitations are coming from um the
the red pepper and the garlic that you
might have had with your spaghetti. But
in the deep field it really is the
contractions and relaxations of muscles
of the postural system hugging the core,
hugging the spine itself. which are the
basis the priors the postural
basis
for the rest of the actions of the body.
Since in the deep field the stimuli to
the receptors are delivered by the
organism itself the deep receptors may
be termed proprioceptors
meaning selfawareness and the deep field
of field of proprioception.
Now this is a postural and a tonic
system and we've discussed that but it's
tightly interwoven not with
interosception but with exterception
and
maintains tonic reactions in the
skeletal musculature. Sharington
describes these wonderfully steady,
long, continued, untiring and for the
most part mild contractions
and this is known as their tone. Tone.
Sherington spends a long time talking
about tone. The muscle sense was a major
topic of 19th century um explorations
into perception but also into the
physics of life.
And I love what Sharington uh says and
he says that
um tone serves as an adgivant to
so-called to the muscle sense.
Now
in the literature
since Sharington
these terms have gotten twisted around
quite a bit and there's a real consensus
in the literature. Um these are a number
of quotes here from different serious
studies and scholars
making the point for example that
proprioception predominates as the most
misused term within the sensory motor
system. Uh jumping down um propriception
is one of the least understood senses
yet fundamental for control of movement
and foot to the bottom. Some major
textbooks claiming to cover neuroscience
barely mention it or mention it only in
passing. But the truth is that if you do
a search online, you're not going to get
the proprioception that Sharington just
described, you're going to get a
definition of it as positional
awareness. Typically, say in the elbow
or in the extremities. That's a very
different creature. Positional awareness
is a very different creature than
self awareness
and then what of interosception? Now
interosception has been redefined as
comprehensive of all inner sense which
then includes proprioception or
proprioception as positional awareness
and
proprioceptives might be considered
interosceptors. Sarius says in a in a
major study um interosception then
refers to the perception of the
physiological condition. Now what's
happened is a very simple
reinterpretation
and none of these studies engage sharing
more than for a few lines or a few
paragraphs at the most. But
interosception has simply been redefined
to mean inner sensation. And we now
understand from Sharington that was not
his intent. That does not make sense.
The cyto cytoplasm is not constitutive
of the inner self of the cell. That
would be the nucleus.
So
interosception is not a source of
self-awareness.
It's not realistic to expect from it a
selfidentity.
Exterosception however is. Of course,
our sense of our outer sense of identity
is quite rich and complete.
But that inner sense of identity that
comes from the functional unity, the
bodywide axial core
also functions at the level of of of a
self identity
and has the neural
the neural mass to support that kind of
a hypothesis in the cerebellum, the
brain stem and the spinal cord.
Now, I just want to take a moment here
and and I'm sorry if that was rough,
but I want to take a little bit of a
moment, a few minutes of your time to
explore this in the body. And we're just
going to look at those three fields. And
let's start on the outside just to
rehearse the the marov blanket, the
outer surface of the surface sheet.
with the five senses, with the
extremities, with the skin, with our
distance receptors. And we can look
around and we can hear
the cars far off in the distance or
children playing. We can touch the
things in our environment and touch
ourselves on the outside. We have so
many ways of relating to the outer world
that it can be overwhelming and and
allconsuming.
The importance of going deep within is
so important. So we're going to start
that process at the inner surface of the
outer boundary. Naturally, we're going
to start that process.
We can start in the mouth and in the
nose.
Inhaling, embibing,
coming down the esophagus,
feeling the blood, feeling the heart,
feeling the lungs,
and all of the awareness that exists in
the gut. That's interosception.
Now that doesn't go all the way to the
core, but it does go all the way to the
other end of our tubular vertebrae tors
torso with its cordate body plant to the
excoratory system. What comes in and
comes out is a matter of interosception
but is part of the surface field.
Next, we're going to start again here in
the tongue. And we're going to identify
that muscular system of the tongue
running back in the back of the throat,
in the back of the chest,
behind the heart, in the front of the
spine, behind the lungs, then expanding
suddenly here into the whole diaphragm
and coming down through the gut. Not in
the viscera, behind the viscera, in the
motoric core, the postural core, the
soaz muscles running down through the
pelvic basin
and the groin through the medial thighs
and the adductors down the legs
around the medial ankle and the medial
arch to the big toe and the surface of
the feet. a bodywide myofascial
motoric muscular continuity.
This deep inner field proprioception,
the postural system, the deep core
doesn't contain
these distance receptors. It doesn't
have visual and verbal and auditory
awareness.
It has haptic and muscular awareness
which nevertheless is tremendously rich.
And this is something that we're going
to encounter all day every day. It is a
daily part of our life. But if you go
into a yoga studio, then that's that's
what you're going to experience is that
system as you move in those long slow
continuous tonic movements.
I have been I have been arguing that the
core node has been under theorized in
the model and that the most important
aspect of that core node is the motoric
anatomy of the deep field in the body.
Um the deep field is the postural system
and is the source of physical
homeostasis. And if we do not have a
clear anatomical understanding of that
system, then I I think it's reasonable
to say it's under theorized.
So
it's only a recent discovery that the
nucleus has a nucleiokeleton
and the importance of the mechanuctive
elements in the nuclear envelope.
Now
it's also a recent discovery of the the
the the discovery of the myofascial
synergistic nature of the body is a
recent discovery and we can see in these
other pictures here the core
we can see this one circular this
cutaway diagram of the abdomen. Now we
can see the outer blanket of the
abdominal muscles of the core. The
traditional core that we think of on the
outside of the body is complemented by
an inner core that I surrounds and
supports and protects and expresses its
neural content. The spinal cord this
inner core system is the myofascial
synergy that I've been describing.
Now,
so I want to talk about two blankets, a
double blanket theory. I want to propose
that there are two blankets in the model
and that they have a relationship
that is problematic. We can call it
blanket politics. We can think about
that problematic relationship between
these two systems in the body in terms
of for instance disconnection hypothesis
because
poor integration between these two major
perceptual systems is going to have
effects in terms of neurom modulation
and sensory integration. Now I'm not
going to discuss that but I am going to
suggest that Bateson's notion of a
double bind is relevant here. Now let's
look at a double bind. A double bind is
a situation in which there's a victim
who is exposed to multiple contradictory
injunctions
within a kind of a power dynamic
a power differential where escape is
barred. there's a dependency.
Now the result of that is silence and
immobilization and and we can see that
in the body. Now I think it's going to
take a lot of work to really flesh that
out so to speak but the double mind we
can think of that as a relationship say
within a family between a parent and a
child and let's say there's a
problematic relationship. Now the child
is sick
and is has recovered, is getting better
and the parent visits in the hospital
and the child gets out of bed and wants
to embrace their parent and share their
their happiness and their their
gratitude, but the parent
backs away and signals, "No, we're not
going to hug. We don't touch." And the
child is immediately despondent and
perhaps a little bit ashamed.
And then the parent having given one
contradictory signal gives the next and
chides the child saying something like
it's perfectly what's wrong with you?
It's perfectly natural to love your
parent. It's perfectly natural to want
to express your joy. Why are you ashamed
of yourself? And so then it puts the
child this dependent being who can't
escape in a situation where they they
can't do and they can't not do they
can't speak but they can't not speak a
double bind and this the result then
would be immobilization and silence and
I think that's an interesting metaphor
for this outer blanket the extercept
system with all of its power and it's
enveloping presence
and this more dependent inner very
sensitive
um perceptual system
which nevertheless has its own impulses
and needs and
which can be at odds. They can be at
odds with each other and so a lack of
integration then we would call that the
double bind. Not sure really how to work
with that, but I find that to be
productive in terms of my own working
out my own inner blanket politics, so to
speak. The solution, what's the
solution? Well, first to identify that
dynamic to be able to step outside of
it, at least conceptually,
but also empowerment
to give that victim agency. And
one of the uh
problems about under theorization of the
core node is that we don't have that we
don't have that empowerment and agency
at the level that we really need it for
belief updating in the global model.
Belief updating in the global model then
just to be really simple about it.
There's a lot of text here, but the
global model is going to be the
superordinate level of the model, which
would be the model itself, as we've
already discussed, and its three fields
rather than some subsystem within it.
It's going to be the the level of the
individual organism, the person, the
self, and their own different ways,
their their own uh three different
fields within the individual organism.
but also the world model that we're
working with. And
we certainly can in terms of thinking
about surprisal, we certainly at the
level of global phenomenon and the
anthroposine and collapse and
technological overshoot and uh political
um uh strife
that we're experiencing. We certainly
can identify a great deal of surprisal
which should be telling us to look at to
revisit the global model and I think
that this interpretation is a salient
one and a relevant one. Now a little bit
more about exterceptive bias.
Exterosceptive bias is going to be uh an
innate tendency within the system. There
simply are more receptors. There simply
is a lot more going on exterceptively
than in any other field. Certainly in
the proprio than in the proprioceptive
field and the animal when it's born
immediately has to look
into the world around it to to find uh
warmth, shelter, food, kin and that need
doesn't stop that continues. So there is
an exterceptive bias that is an innate
tendency within the system although it
is not meant
to be overwhelming, not meant to be in
an imbalance and repressive
instead. Um
and so what that what happens then is
that a control bias emerges when the
balancing proprioceptive priors are not
present in the system. Then there's a an
a feedback loop, a positive feedback
loop, a vicious cycle that occurs, a
control bias in which exacerbates that
imbalance.
Now we can see that in right hemispheric
dominance and hyperintellectualization
of our culture which is increasing
exponentially with the exponential
changes in technology and the built
environment.
Self-evidencing then is one way of
looking at how the body calibrates.
Precision tracking and self-evidencing.
Now self-evidencing,
what is self-evidencing? I think that's
a great question
from an exterceptive perspective.
Self-evidencing
is a little bit obstruuse because
exterception is other evidencing. Um,
the five senses provide the basis, the
evidence required by science and reason.
This is conventional. There's really
nothing wrong with it. But
self-evidencing
is a property of a selfaware a self
directed system and that would be the
core that would be propriception. That
would be the core node in the model.
self-evidencing then is a natural
property of the functioning of the
propriioceptive core in its relationship
the body's deep deeper inner hidden
relationship with itself.
Now there's a lot of ways to look at
that, but
um
we're going to talk about
uh precision tracking and we're first
we're going to talk a little bit about
fascia and we're going to talk about
precision tracking in the model. Now the
rediscovery of fascia is a big deal. I'm
a body worker so I work with fascia.
That is a recent phenomenon and I would
argue one of the most important fifths
in anatomical science since Vicelius
in 1543 that the restoration of the
connective tissue matrix to the image of
the body
is a powerful powerful form of belief
updating. Now we had removed the fascia
because it was in the way. We thought,
we believed it was simply a kind of
white wrapping tissue that needed to be
discarded so that we could see what was
underneath the individual muscles with
their tendonous connections to the
bones. A bunch of mechanistic little
parts was revealed through the process
not of peeling away a wrapping paper,
but of cutting away powerful chunks of
flesh. Because the muscles, this image
that the muscle is connected to the bone
and the bone is connected to another
bone and to other muscles is artificial.
The bones and muscles are invested
within a connective tissue matrix
that provides 30 to 70% of the force
production of the system
and which is itself an inner skin a
layered complex inner skin. It's a it's
an elastic source of force production.
That's very important. But it's also a
layered inner skin so that the
interuscular
the intramuscular septa in the system
the interstitial
um tissues the interstatial space is
very very sensitive. we now know. So
we by restoring
that more integrative
and holistic self-image
anatomical
image of the body then that in itself is
very empowering. It certainly is
empowering for me as a therapist because
I understand it. But also in terms of my
movements, it gives me a lot of insight
into the feel that I have for these
deeper more subtle movements that we say
experience in the yoga studio or in
meditation in Taichi or rehabilitation
etc.
Myofascial synergies then are and this
is the one that I've been talking about
are
the basis
for
um a kind of biomechanical belief
updating in the model and my work at
least comes from this wonderful text by
Tom Meyers and where he has posited 12
different longitudinal myofascial
continuities. This is not the only
example. It is the preeminent example,
but there are others in history and
others available today. And an
interesting hypothesis, a paper was
published in the international journal
of molecular um science
arguing that the myofascial unit, not
the individual muscle,
is the physiological basic element for
peripheral motor control. that the the
basic unit of motor control is
myofascial synergy.
Now again, some different pictures of
the deep core and then getting a little
bit more deeply into my system. What
I've tried to do is to unpack this axial
skeleton in terms of that axial line.
And what we see here are how that axial
line is intersected at each major
juncture. At the one end of the spine
where the head meets the neck. At the
other end of the spine where the legs
meet where the hips meet the spine and
in the feet where the the ground
connects with where the in the feet
where where the body connects with the
ground. And each one of those junctures
is represented by a circle because those
are highly sensitive arrays,
concavities,
gradients if you will, pits
in the body full of sensitive organs and
tissues full complex junctures that come
together with at the center
a a bony
prominent central bony servo. mechanism.
Now,
um
I want to apply that
these ideas
to movement and we're going to talk
about kinesiology. So, conventional
kinesiology of the exterceptive system
is adequately represented by the very
very primal primordial simple stick
figure that we see on cave walls. And
that with just a few simple lines can
represent the expressions and the
movements of the body on the outside,
the extremities.
But it's interesting to note that that
stick figure has nothing to say
about what is obviously what is clearly
the most important part of the body, its
most sensitive contents.
the the axial line, the core.
Now,
there isn't a stick. We even a even the
transmission of a car has linkages and
articulations.
So, getting back to that stick figure in
conventional kinesiology,
the the kinesiology, the movements are
oppositional.
flexion coming together, extension
coming apart, adduction bringing the
limbs to the body, abduction taking the
limbs away from the body. They're
oppositional.
And then internal rotation, external
rotation, oppositional movements. Now on
the other side of the fence in
proprioception in the axial line in the
core, in the synergistic system, these
kinesi, this kinesiology is not
oppositional. It's complimementaryary.
It's interdependent
and the movements of the axial structure
are also um uh diverse and significant
but we can describe them as as the grip.
We talked a little bit about the grip
that we can get in the armpit. The
scapula doesn't just grab the arm. It
reaches around the ribs in in a in a
grip-like structure. and contributes to
centration and pressurization
in the torso.
Centration coming together,
pressurization, a little bit of
expansion work together to create
balance and stability in the body on a
longitudinal level. We push down through
the posterior line and experience lift
coming up through the front. This is
something that's uh experienced in yoga
all the time. Gravity in fact translated
through the tensegrity structure of the
body
does not pull living organisms down but
in fact lifts them up. It provides a
vertical kind of a gradient that my
physics is getting way ahead of me but
provides lift. And this is something
that we can see commonly in life and
that we can experience in ourselves as
we bring our posture together. That
poise is a form of lift. And then the
third set I think of of complimentary uh
cooperative sort of movements is some
sort of a spiral or helical pattern in
the body. Now
we talked a little bit about homologies
and how
the in the exterceptive system in the in
the body in general there are there is
segmental homologies and that helps us
to organize the body the body's
movements but when we shift from between
perceptual fields
from an exterceptive to a proprioceptive
field then we also experience what I
think is an inverse homology
and that helps the brain to sort of get
a grip from within.
I won't say any more about that. We
talked a lot about the bony servo
mechanisms here. Um we'll go into them a
little bit more deeply. The different
bony servo mechanisms on the axial line.
Um there are no other alternatives, no
other options. It's very clear uh what
they are.
we can come into each one of these
sensitive areas and each one of these
major bones
in order to organize that area. Now here
they are laid out in the skeleton
and uh we can see the the circles around
those bones and on the right hand side
and highlighted in a kind of a green
blue is is each one of those prominent
bony servo mechanisms. Each one is at
the center of a sensitive kind of hidden
concavity. The groin, the throat, the
armpit in the b in the soles of the
feet. Now, these are clearly areas in
the body where we're meant to know
ourselves.
But what happens when we get confused?
So this is a little diagram and I'm
going to finish with this diagram today
about how we actually what
stereosceptive bias means as a control
bias means that we wear the body
backwards and the green areas are the
axial postural areas the bony
affordances
largely in the front with the exception
of the scapula.
And
these are the areas if you think about
your body now, the most sensitive areas
of the body. But are these the areas
where we experience the most problems?
These are the areas where I think that
we experience the most repression and
sometimes even shame. And when we see
collapse, we see a collapse in these
areas with a tremendous amount of stress
and tension and compensation required in
their opposites and those are the red
areas. So when we have a head forward
position, when we have collapse in this
anterior structure, the back of the neck
is carrying this heavy imbalanced load.
We get tension in the occiput in the
neck and in the shoulders. When we um
fail to attend to the proprioceptive
prior in the armpit, we make the
shoulder do all the work. And of course,
that's the third most common site of
muscularkeeletal complaints. It is not
where we're meant to control the body.
We're meant to find coordinative
awareness in these um
concavities
and their bony servo mechanisms of the
low back
in relationship to the groin, the pubic
bone in the front. The pelvis very much
is shaped like a wheelbarrow. And those
two big bones in the back, they're like
the two big wheels or handles of a
wheelbarrow. And we try our best to
force that load and we believe that we
can control that load with brute
strength until the front wheel of the
wheelbarrow hits a pebble and the entire
thing tips. So if we don't attend to the
the little front wheel to the low front,
then we're going to have dysfunction in
the low back.
The feet. What I'm going to say about
the feet is that that big toe is very
clearly the power structure of the
entire foot. And what's the first thing
we do when we put it in modern shoes?
Hix VGUS. We collapse. We crush that
structure.
So that's my talk for today and I'm
that's an effort to unpack belief
updating and exterceptive bias in a
somatic way with reference to sharington
with reference to anatomy myofascial
anatomy it's been a real pleasure I want
to ask you if you've made it this far in
the talk that you give me some comments
give me some feedback hopefully some
positive feedback I've worked very hard
on this again I'm very excited to make
this unusual somatic anatomical
contribution to the field of active
inference thank you very All
right, the next talk is by Sid,
10 minutes long.
Greetings everyone. My name is Siddhant
and I'll walk you through our recent
work on enhancing bisantine tolerant
formation control for maritime buoy
swarms using you guessed it right active
inference. What are maritime buoy
swarms? As you can see on my screen
maritime buoy swarms are a swarm of
buoys like deployed in the ocean in
order to achieve certain tasks. For
example, if there is an oil spill or um
like um an incident in the ocean, these
buoys help in monitoring that. They also
help support missions like surveillance,
search and rescue and other kinds of
environmental monitoring in hostile or
contested waters. The threats that we
focus on in this particular work rely on
the configuration that you see in front
of you. All of these buoys can be
imagined as decentralized robots
floating in the ocean with minimal motor
control and they can communicate among
each other and a centralized hub. But
because of this they are also prone to
cyber physical attacks. So we will focus
on three kinds of attacks which can
impact their operation and mission
success. So for example, if the task is
area coverage
like taking down one or more of these
buoys is equivalent to a bisonantine
problem where we cannot trust certain
buoys anymore and now we have to measure
how to measure the mission success in
this particular uh scenario so that the
rest of the buoys can reorganize around
this and in order to do do that they
need to detect the cyberphysical attack
at play. So the threats that we will
focus on are GPS poofing, communication
jamming and actuator hijacking.
Why these three? Because these three
push the resilience limits of existing
control architectures which may not use
artificial intelligence or any active
inference approach. Our goal in this
work is to maintain formation integrity
and task coverage while detecting and
mitigating malicious agents. I'll start
with our baseline approach and then
explain how we integrated active
inference, where it shines, where it
still struggles, what alternatives we
considered, and how we plan to push the
results further. The original meth
methodology without active inference
uses a decentralized neighborto-
neighbor approach
in order to facilitate communication.
Each buoy assessed trust using
hand-crafted manual heruristics, rules
that downweighted agents exhibiting
inconsistent trajectories, communication
dropouts or mission throughput
anomalies. We combined that
multi-dimensional trust score with an
attack aware formation controller
which essentially helped reate the
neighbor influence based on trust
estimates while enforcing formation
geometry and coverage. This approach was
practical and interpretable and it
handled many different kinds of
anomalies well as you can see in the
graph in front of you. However, it
lacked formal uncertainty quantification
which is very important for this kind of
a task. Strugg it struggled with subtle
or staged attacks that we uh inflicted
upon the system and sometimes even over
penalized honest agents during
complicated maneuvers. In our improved
methodology
like we see we see that we introduced an
active inference-based trust assessor.
The core idea here is to move from
uristic rules to a probabilistic
generative model and variational basian
inference. Each buoy in this new model
maintains an internal state predicting
neighbor trajectories position, velocity
and acceleration and even jerk to
measure change in momentum. While taking
into account estimated formation forces
when reality deviates from predictions,
we compute a mahalenobis distance across
those dimensions. High prediction errors
uh will suggest potential tampering. We
then update our trust beliefs using
basian filtering explicitly tracking
both the mean trust score and its
uncertainty. The formation controller
uses those uncertainty aware trust
estimates to moderate neighbor
influence. Agent communication stays
decentralized. The key change is that
the trust updates now come from
predictive modeling rather than fixed
thresholds.
And this as you can see improves the
detection accuracy a bit across all
three metrics. Where active inference is
useful can be highlighted in the
following ways.
Like the graphs are pretty clear that
active inference over a period of time
can help in improving the results that
we are seeking. But to do that it helps
mostly in three areas. First is early
detection. Predictive errors surface
anomalies before they manifest as gross
deviation. We see this particularly with
GPS spoofing position when they diverge
sharply from expected trajectories.
Secondly, uncertainty quantification
helps us in carrying variances along
with the trust means so that we can pro
protect the honest agents when the model
is unsure. This reduces false positives
during tight maneuvers. Thirdly, it
helps with attack specificity. Different
attack modes produce distinct error
signatures which are important for us to
quantify and measure. GPS poofing
elevates the position residues.
Communication jamming shows up in
missing observations. Actuator hijacking
disrupts velocity and jerk. We calibrate
these responses accordingly. In our V2
results, this translated into an 8.4%
average improvement in detection
accuracy, a 1.6% boost in resilience,
and 6.6 6% gain in task coverage with
actuator hijacking coverage jumping
nearly 20%. And the results are pretty
clear. We do not claim that active
inference is always the better approach.
We can see here that active inference
does a lot better at task coverage and
resilience score whereas it is nearly um
as performant in other metrics or
sometimes less performant in average
trust score over time. Where active
inference still falters is that the
generative model still simplifies the
hydrodnamics and control inputs. When
cooperative agents execute aggressive
maneuvers, prediction error spike and
the system can result in false alarms.
Moreover, communication jamming creates
data gaps that challenge the inference
updates. Even with tempered thresholds,
detection improvements for actuator
hijacking um like are minuscule. So what
do we do? Um we see that um detection
improvements are modest with only 3.5%
because actuation dynamics are hard to
model at the granularity we need. So
active inference is computationally
heavier for these decentralized forms
with lesser processing budgets. So we
need reliable processing power in order
to ensure real-time updates which may
not always be a solution in a maritime
environment. The alternative approaches
that we have considered was a
reinforcement learning based trust
estimation where agents learn policies
from simulated attacks. It offers
adaptability but lacks the
interpretability and uncertainty
guarantees that we wanted. Another was a
consensus based filtering with fall
tolerant observers. Classic control
theory techniques. These have strong
stability proofs but require centralized
coordination or strict communication
assumptions. Another thing that we could
look at is an hybrid approach which
combines calman filters with heristic
gating which shows um which has the
potential to show some promise yet um
like it also has the potential to lack
explicit uncertainty handling. What
active inference gives us is a balance
between theory interpretability and
decentralized operation. The key finding
for us is that active inference can
outperform huristic baselines across
detection resilience and coverage while
providing principled uncertainty
estimates. GPS poofing detection jumped
over 15%. Uh our communication jamming
detection um improved by 7%.
And actuator hijacking coverage improved
almost 20%. These are not
basic numbers. These are quite
significant. So how do we go about it in
a practical setting? We confirm that
these protective floors and attack
specific calibrations are essential.
Without them, active inference
overreacts. Finally, the predictive
modeling gives the commanders richer
diagnostic signals. Not just what went
wrong, but how confident the system is
in that assessment. This is where active
inference really shines. We can improve
upon a few things as next steps. Our
next steps focus on richer generative
models incorporating better hydrodnamic
parameters for this environment,
external disturbance introduction and
learned control inputs. We plan to fuse
communication reliability signals more
tightly with behavioral predictions to
handle jamming gaps. We also want to
explore hierarchical active inference
where local agents share compressed
summaries of their beliefs to enhance
collective awareness without breaking
decentralization. Finally, we plan to
benchmark against adaptive consensus and
reinforcement learning hybrids to ensure
that we are harnessing the best aspects
of each approach. In summary, active
inference has pushed our maritime swarm
resilience forward in a simulation
environment, giving us predictive
confidence and measurable improvements
against bisonantine threats. The work is
not done. We need to do a lot more to
move this from a Python-based simulation
environment to the real world. But the
path is clearer. We need to sharpen the
models, strengthen the communication
inference loop, and validate under more
diverse operational profiles. Thank you.
Please feel free to reach out and I'm
happy to dive deeper into any section.
And it has been an honor presenting here
at the symposium and I wish you luck.
All right, next talk is by Nicholas
Hinrix. Hypers scanning under active
inference for mental health. This is
going to be an 11 minute recorded video.
>> Hi, my name is Dr. Nicholas Henri. I'm a
neuroscientist working at the Max Bank
Institute for Cognitive and Brain
Sciences. And hi, my name is Dr.
Nicholas Henri. I'm a neuroscientist
working at the Max Frank Institute for
Human Cognitive and Brain Sciences and
at the Okinawa Institute for Science and
Technology.
I study how people come to feel
together.
Today, I want to talk about a problem
that's obvious to anyone who has ever
been in a therapy room.
Mental health interventions depend on
attunement.
When therapist and client are not
aligned, therapy stalls or even fails.
Yet, we have almost no quantitative
tools for monitoring attunement in real
time.
My colleagues and I propose a way
forward. We build on active inference
models of social interaction and link
them to a geometric hypers scanning
observable that is suitable for clinical
deployment.
We will also sketch a prospective
digital twin for psychotherapy that uses
real-time monitoring of neural geometry
to mark and eventually predict when
crucial behavioral events say ruptures,
co-regulation and reatunement occur.
The common scientific approach to social
cognition is to treat one person as an
observer trying to infer the hidden
mental state of another. This third
person stance assumes social
understanding happens through detached
one-way observation.
In contrast, second person neuroscience
emphasizes that meaningful interaction
is embodied and reciprocal. When two
people engage, their brains form a
coupled generative system.
Computationally, each partner maintains
a generative model of their own as well
as of the other person's states.
predictions are continuously updated and
belief updating becomes mutual.
This dissolves the regress of I model
you modeling me modeling you into a
shared dynamic narrative
and this framework the diet not the
isolated individual is the basic unit of
inference.
A effect fits naturally into this
picture. Emotional balance can be
formalized as inference over the
coherence of a self model. Two
quantities drive it. The magnitude of
self-model prediction error. So how
surprised you are about yourself and the
self-relevance of that error. So how
much the situation touches your
identity.
We include an effective memory term to
account for emotional inertia and allow
different temporal orientations.
prospective, retrospective, fast, slow,
intense or smoother,
which we call temporal aim.
The position parameters alpha and beta,
which you'll see in our um paper, tune
the influence of surprise and memory. In
a diatic interaction, prediction errors
become entangled because each agent
recursively models the other. Positive
balance signals smooth coordination
whereas negative balance signals
breakdowns within active inference. A
effect acts as a soft prior that biases
policy selection towards trajectories
that minimize expected surprise.
Therapists sometimes use their intuition
to sense when the alliance with a client
is strong or weak.
In social neuroscience, hyperscanning
allows us to monitor brain activity
simultaneously in multiple people.
Most hyperscanning studies compute
correlation or phase locking metrics
which describe neurosynchrony but cannot
tell us when and how the network
reorganizes.
These metrics treat interbrain coupling
as somewhat static and misdynamic
topological reconfigurations associated
with rupture and repair.
Network geometry offers a more
mechanistic lens. Discrete geometric
notions like the form and Ricky
curvature quantify how information
expands or contracts across a network.
In a weighted network, positive
curvature marks edges embedded in dense
redundant clusters while negative
curvature marks bridging edges that
connect different modules.
This edge centered measure captures
local flow in ways that nodebased
synchrony can't.
Our method which we've dubbed geometric
hyperscanning computes the formal
rickety curvature on time resolved
interbrain networks derived from dual
EEG fur or fMRI recordings.
We treat each cortical region as a node
and functional connectivity as weighted
edges for each edge connecting nodes I
and J. The formal Ricky curvature is
computed
over the weight of that edge multiplied
by the sum of one divided by the weight
of node I and 1 divided by the weight of
note J. Then you subtract the correction
term which is the sum over all edges
that share a note with the edge under
consideration
of the ratio of that edg's weight to the
square root of the product of that edg's
weight and its neighbors weight. This
context the function w assigns weights
to nodes and edges.
To track how the overall geometry
evolves, we compute the entropy of the
curvature distribution within a sliding
window.
Curvature entropy at time t is
calculated by taking the negative of the
sum over all edges present at that time
of the probability of each edge
multiplied by the natural log of that
probability.
Here the probability of an edge is the
curvature of that edge divided by the
sum of curvatures across all edges.
This resulting scalar curvature entropy
measures the volatility of interbrain
topology.
Abrupt peaks or discontinuities in
curvature entropy indicate topological
phase transitions in the shared
generative manifold. When the entropy
spikes, it often corresponds to
effective rupture. When it declines,
repair and reatunement are underway.
How do the how do we use these insights
in therapy?
Each partner in therapy, so the
therapist and the client is modeled as
an agent whose self model contains a
generative model of the other.
Prediction errors in this recursive
model manifest as topological changes in
their combined neural activity.
By combi by computing former Ricky
curvature on the weighted interbrain
network this third brain between
therapist and client and tracking the
entropy of its distribution. We obtain a
realtime readout of when the interaction
is stable, rupturing or repairing.
Here's where the idea of a digital twin
becomes powerful. A mental health
digital twin is a virtual representation
of an individual's mental states that is
continually updated with data collected
over the person's interaction.
Such a twin can guide professionals in
diagnosing and treating patients using
mechanistic models, machine learning
tools.
The digital twin concept extends beyond
simple simulations. It spans the
neurohysiological cycle of an individual
and updated by real world data using
physical and statistical models to
answer what if questions
in mental health. Digital twins could
forecast deterioration,
predict treatment outcomes, and
recommend tailored interventions.
Implementing this framework requires
robust data in careful modeling. Hypers
scanning signals must be pre-processed
to construct reliable time resolve
functional connectivity matrices.
The curvature calculation depends on
appropriate waiting schemes.
Positive curvature highlights redundant
local clusters while negative curvature
highlights bridges. Entropy should be
computed within windows suitable for the
modality's temporal resolution.
shorter windows for EG or longer ones
for fMRI. In real clinical settings, the
digital twin must integrate behavioral
cues, gaze, procity, gestures, and
self-report
data with the neural one. Each of these
streams can inform the posterior over
latent states, ensuring the twin is
grounded in multimodal evidence.
Ethically, digital twins raise issues of
privacy and agency.
Despite these challenges, the potential
benefits are considerable. By embedding
geometric hypers scanning within an
active inference framework, we can
develop social markers, realtime
signatures of interpersonal coordination
analogous to biomarkers.
in therapy. These could alert
practitioners to ruptures they might
otherwise miss, guide decisions about
when to pause or reframe an
intervention, and help quantify progress
over sessions. In research,
curvature-based metrics allows allow us
to test hypotheses about how belief
updating and effective revelation
unfold moment by moment.
In technology, digital twins could
inform adaptive interfaces and social
robots that adjust their behavior based
on the geometry of human interaction.
Mental health interventions thrive on
attunement. Yet quantifying attunement
has remained elusive. We propose a
unified framework that models therapist
client interactions as coupled
generative systems,
formalizes affect as inference over
selfmodel coherence and measures
interbrain dynamics using discrete
geometry. The formal ricky curvature and
its entropy reveal dynamic phase
transitions,
rupture, cogulation and reatunement
which standard synchrony measures miss.
Building on this insight, we sketch a
digital twin for psychotherapy, a
virtual entity that integrates real time
neural, behavioral, and emotional data
to timestamp and anticipate shifts in
relational state.
Such a twin has a potential to assist
therapists in guiding sessions towards
the optimal outcome, namely healing.
We invite collaborations to test this
approach on real clinical data and
further refine the models for broader
use. Thank you.
Okay, we're back. This is going to be
the session that would have been
immediately following Carl Fristen's
keynote address earlier today due to
some technical issues. The group with
Ian Tennant recorded this during the
time. So, here it is. It is a 45minute
video.
Yeah, it seems
>> great.
>> Okay, good.
Hello and welcome and thanks for
joining.
This presentation for the fifth applied
active inference symposium is titled an
applied active inference group practice
for transdisciplinary collaboration. My
name is Ian Tenant. I'm based at Anglia
Ruskin University.
So I'll start with explaining um why I'm
interested in a particular type of group
practice or communication style for
transdisciplinary work and then think
about how we're going to go about this.
Today we'll do a um a live demonstration
of this type of um group practice and
then I'll talk about the details of what
it involves before we do the live demo.
So at Angller Russ University a year or
so ago, a new planetary health group was
set up and um the idea was it brings
together a new group of peers and um
colleagues who are interested in
planetary health with different
backgrounds. So some from engineering,
some from economics, health, different
types of health and um law. So we're in
the stage now where we're still kind of
storming, forming and norming. So
understanding each other's interests and
trying to figure out a shared way of
looking at global planetary health
issues
and the idea of a transdicciplinary
mindset um appealed to me but I wasn't
sure exactly what it means. So I looked
at the literature for some definitions
and found a nice paper in 1998 titled
complexity and human hast uh human
health the case for a transdisciplinary
paradigm. And this table sets out a a
spectrum of ways in which we can look at
um big problems.
So in this case health problems we can
draw different boundaries around the
problems. So um if we considered
something like a
um
uh a health problem like kidney disease,
a single discipline might be a kidney
specialist thinking about the best
medical uh medicine or therapeutic to um
treat the disease. A multiddisciplinary
uh approach
might be um uh a kidney specialist
teaming up with a engineer to develop a
new device. uh transdisciplinary
um according to this definition goes a
step further and they widen the scope of
the problem to look at the um situation
of kidney disease from multiple levels a
kind of look at health as a dynamic
system operating um even beyond the
individual.
So um staying with the example of kidney
disease here we have a picture of uh Dr.
William Kul who was the first um person
to develop an artificial kidney. These
days we call it diialysis and he teamed
up with engineers to build the first um
uh kidney diialysis machine.
These days we have um transdisiplinary
projects looking at things related to um
uh the issue of something like endstage
kidney disease. So with kidney disease
um some people can develop it after
having diabetes for a long time which
damages the kidney. So if we were going
to go to the root cause of uh draw
expand the boundary of our problem and
say why for example are there so many
people in Europe or in or the UK
developing diabetes which then reaches
this stage of endstage kidney disease.
we might take a transdisciplinary
mindset and this project here called
cities changing diabetes from 2014. It
um brought together people from lots of
different disciplines including urban
planners and uh um maybe environmental
toxicologists to look at what is it in
the environment that might be um
causally related to people developing
diabetes and the problems that they may
um come up with maybe involve
redesigning cities to make them
healthier places for to be in. So often
these are um it's a blending of
disciplines for a long-term
collaboration and it may end up in
resulting with new frameworks or
theories to work with.
However, um when new people with special
um interests and working models come
together, there's often some challenges
during the early stages. And I'm going
to use the Jiari window model here to um
explain what I mean by this. So with the
Jiari window model um it's it's it's
called a window because it looks like
four planes panes of glass. And we have
in the top left corner things that are
known to um the self one group of people
but they're not known to other groups of
people. So we could say with people with
some uh specialism or one discipline,
let's say a uh kidney specialist,
they're things that are known to the
specialist in kidneys but not known to
an engineer.
Then the other corner we've got um
things that are not known to the self
but are known to the other group. And
then we've got in the bottom right
corner things that are not known to
either of the two groups. And the aim
really um of transdisciplinary research
or teams will work better if we we um
expand the window where things are known
to self and the other. And hopefully
people familiar with um the active
inference framework will recognize this
as a form of reducing uncertainty or
reducing surprise or or minimizing
error.
So um
the free uh active inference um involves
reducing the discrepancy between what we
um our internal model and what we sense
from the world and we can do this either
through updating our model of the world
or trying to change the world change
what we sense from the world.
um a slide here from one of Carl
Fristen's papers where he um uses uh an
example of song birds singing and turn
taking. So the birds generate a shared
model or or a shared generative model of
their song by taking turns to listen and
to sing.
And this is referred to as precision
engineer engineered message passing. And
we all kind of do this sort of thing.
Um, every day we take turns to listen
and speak. But there are different um
styles or ways we can do this. The
archetypal way of um thinking of people
coming together to share stories is
around a campfire. um but we do it uh in
lots of different ways. The last month
there was the sixth international
workshop on active inference. So a
conference is a style of um sharing
generative models and um it may involve
people presenting for long periods of
time and then questions and answers. and
we're seeking to kind of understand each
other and reduce our uncertainty about
each other's models.
In the therapeutic world, there's lots
of um approaches to this. On the right,
a picture of uh a counseling session.
So, in some forms of counseling, the
counselor will not um necessarily
uh try to
um coach or guide the person in
counseling. they'll literally listen and
reflect um and allow the person to
share.
But it's a very um structured approach.
Uh another style of group chat maybe
around uh less structured is around uh a
social event around a table where people
will take turns but there um there's no
structure to say who has to speak first
or who gets to speak or um um who should
be listening.
So um it's a big spectrum of styles for
sharing, listening and
um speaking and listening. And they
range from having a lot of structure to
little structure. The approach we're
going to use today, the how we're going
to go about this is um inspired some by
some therapeutic traditions. And one of
these is um has been developed by John
Vavi who's appeared on the inference uh
institutes u several several times and
he um calls this style dialogos and he
says that it encourages a reciprocal
flow state which is similar to um jazz
or sparring.
So um this type of style has been
developed by um the circling institute
and for those of you who wish to find
out more uh can visit the circling
institute website
but um it shares similarities to lots of
therapeutic styles of communication or
nonviolent communication and um my
partner has um um trained in this style
of communication and has encouraged me
to um adopt it and I'll just share a
very brief example of how it's helped in
our relationship. So the idea is that um
if someone is speaking to you and um you
rather than if it if something arises
that maybe you disagree with or there's
some uncertainty about you seek to
understand the other person before you
add your own opinion. So, this simple
example was a day when we'd had a lovely
day out and at the end of the day, my
partner said she wasn't feeling very
loved. And the part of me that might
have been sensitive or um wanting to
defend myself might have said um of
course you're loved. We've done all
these lovely things today. And so on.
But because she had um helped me
understand the ideas of reflective
practice, um I sought to understand what
she meant. So I said, "Okay, um
uh in what way are you not feeling
loved? Um please help me understand what
you're feeling." And this led to a
really interesting conversation and our
relationship deepened as a result of it.
So today we're going to use um a
structured form of communication and
we're joined by Susan, Andrew, and
Leonardo to demonstrate this. And there
are um certain stages to it, but the
general principles are that when you're
listening to someone speaking, then you
um
uh seek to understand what they're
sharing through reflecting what you've
heard back to them. And if there's an
error, it gives the person who spoke a
chance to clarify or they may want to
add further detail.
So the mindset we have to approach is to
be comfort to be comfortable with the
error and um if you are sharing then be
um open to revealing your whole
experience. So um that could be more the
effective side of the experience. So uh
your emotional veilance as well as just
the facts.
So um I propose that this type of
approach um can help with generative
model alignment in transis
transdisciplinary research. So um
through this turn taking in small groups
we can continually update our beliefs
about others intentions and
perspectives. It can help with precision
calibration. So uh the practice can
highlight which signals deserve more
attention and which need revisiting. It
can help with epistemic action and
shared anticipations over time. So
hopefully the transdisciplinary group
will develop a um kind of shared
um expectations or uh beliefs about how
they can approach the transdisciplinary
problem.
So a quick um
bit of detail about what is involved. So
we imagine we're sitting in a virtual
circle. If this was face to face, you
could sit in a circle and it's turn
taking between listening speaking. So
the first two people um person A and B.
Person A will speak to the topic and
person B will listen and then aim to
reflect back what they've heard.
And then um when person A has finished
and um yeah person P person B reflects
and then when they've reached the
position where person A feels understood
person B turns to the third person and
they share what they feel was surprising
um or confusing or jarring about what
they heard.
And then after then they add their own
opinion about the topic. So their
fresh opinion about the topic. It
doesn't have to be related to what the
previous person said.
Then this continues around the circle.
So person the third person then takes
the role of the seeker. So seeking to
understand and they reflect what person
two has said and that continues. So,
we're going to demonstrate this live
now. And um the topic we're going to
look at is
um about misinformation.
So,
a recent um piece of research says that
of all the kind of um potential threats
around the world that people are worried
about such as natural disasters, war um
um and so on. disinformation is amongst
the top. So people are worried about um
false information and the threats of
that. So what um I'd like the group to
have in mind is how might our
understanding of active inference
help us notice and respond differently
to the types of unhelpful information in
society. That could be AI generated or
it could be through social media or it
could just be everyday life. So, I'm
going to stop sharing the screen
and we'll return back to our small
circle and
um welcome back Susan, Andrew, and
Leonardo.
So, you're welcome to unmute now.
And maybe before we start the group
practice, could you just introduce
yourselves and say a few words about
your um interest in active inference?
So we'll start with Andrew.
That sounds good. So um can you hear me?
Okay.
>> Mhm.
>> Yes.
>> Great. Thanks. Um so yeah, thanks Ian
for for inviting me to this session. Um
I have been involved with the realm of
active inference for roughly three or so
years. Um sort of my background has been
a a very broad combination of the social
sciences, economics, but actually kind
of a move towards complexity science, uh
neuroiming, data analysis. Uh I work
full-time as a data analyst. So I'm just
I'm a very curious person. I'm very
interested in many things and uh so I I
interned and then uh became a member of
the scientific advisory board with the
the institute and some people recognized
me for teaching uh the the proverbial
2022 textbook uh by uh par and pulo and
frist. So thanks
>> thank you Andrew uh Susan. Hi. Yeah, I'm
not a neuroscientist or a data
analysist. Uh I teach uh biology at uh
University of California and I'm
interested in active inference for the
roles that it can help um us find better
ways to help students learn and for the
difference between how they perceive
they're doing in a class and what
actions they're taking and how they
actually are doing. And I'm very curious
about ways to break through that sort of
cycle when people seem to have a large
gap between where they think they want
to be and the things that they're doing
to get there. And so um I'm very curious
about ways to get through that um log
jam.
>> Thank you Susan and Leonardo.
So my name is Leonardo. I'm a PhD
student
in therapy research. My focus is on seat
music uh for dementia carers and my
interest in active inference um
initially came came through my uh
studies in neuroscience
and then it I find it as an interesting
framework for understanding social
dynamics and social neuroscience like
musical interactions.
>> Thank you. Wonderful. So we have um
people in the background of social
science, biology and music.
So um we're going to begin the group
practice now. And um the topic is
unhelpful information that people might
be presented with in various different
forms. and we're speaking to how our
personal understanding of active
inference may help
deal with misinformation or unhelpful
information.
So, is there someone who'd like to speak
to that first?
Andrew. Yeah, I don't mind popping in.
Sure.
Thank you. So, yeah. Shall I just kind
of go for it or
>> you go first and then I'll um take the
role of reflecting you afterwards and
then we'll then I'll pass it on to the
next person.
>> Sounds great. Um
so, it's interesting how you introduce
the word unhelpful information
uh in addition to misinformation.
And I think um you know if I'm thinking
of whether it be active inference or
even some sort of more colloquial sense
of understanding this like unhelpful
information to me um because active
inference in one sense is very much
related to sort of the standpoint of the
observer and we heard some of that
during Kristen's talk. Um, so there
might be information uh that is told to
me that I might perceive as unhelpful uh
if I'm doing some particular project or
something uh that that at least
seemingly has nothing to do with music.
Uh then if I'm told a lot about music in
this moment, I will perceive it as more,
you know, distracting. It's not
particularly helpful despite that
information about the music perhaps
being well evidenced and researched and
maybe kind of comes out of some clinical
study or otherwise. So in which case so
it's it's not misinformation but it is
unhelpful information and I think that
that kind of distinction uh in the the
broader context of thinking about um
global issues or or uh disasters or or
you know kind of um political uh
contention um I think that that
distinction is very relevant right
because someone
who
if active inference entails the idea of
us being self-eviding, right? Then if
I'm told repeated uh incidents
incidences of misinformation
that at least reconfirm my model. So say
I'm listening to a particular
politician, they're proposing some grand
scheme for how to resolve all of our
issues. Um I put in caricature and that
uh policy proposal doesn't necessarily
bear out in policy research. um then it
is a it it could be a kind of
misinformation, but it's very helpful to
me because it makes me feel good, right?
Reconfirms a lot of the beliefs I came
to to listen to the politicians talk
with, right? So, um it's I'll maybe
pause there, but I I just thought it was
a very interesting way to go with that.
>> Thank you. So, I'll aim to reflect and
repeat back what I've heard. So, um you
found it interesting
um the the
putting the word unhelpful and
misinformation, unhelpful information
and misinformation next to each other
and you um
say that um these two things are not
equal. So, information might not be
viewed by the observer to be helpful. So
it might be viewed as unhelpful
information but it may um actually be
true in some sense. It may actually
reflect something um accurate. So it may
not be misinformation in the sense of
false information.
Um and you use the example of um maybe
something a repeated message by a um
politician for example that may confirm
reaffirm someone's belief. So even if
it's misinformation, it may be used as
it may be viewed by the receiver as
helpful
even though um it's not necessarily
accurate.
So you were um aiming to kind of show
some examples of when
information might be viewed as helpful
or unhelpful or accurate or unaccurate.
Um and that those two things don't
always they're not always equivalent to
each other.
Anything else you'd like to add or
correct about
my summary?
I I think you did a a pretty good job of
the summary. Uh yeah, I think I think
that um I think it's useful to include
the idea of what does it mean for
information to be helpful or unhelpful
and then kind of juxtapose that with
what misinformation is cuz I think that
kind of um by understanding the idea of
information being helpful or not to
someone, it actually can kind of help us
potentially better understand the
dynamics of the spread of
misinformation, right? that to kind of
it's just reiterating what you said uh
regarding re reiterating what I said uh
that is uh in our in our turn taking
style here that uh yeah to for for
information to to make me feel good for
me to self-evidence for me to oh I don't
have to change my model of the world
very much because these people are
telling me what I think I already knew
right uh it's quite comfortable it's
very low cognitive cost for me to
process that information and update my
model. Um, and perhaps benown to us,
unbeknownst to us, it nonetheless can be
misinformation. So,
>> thank you. So, um, you were um, saying
that you think it can be useful to
include the notion of helpfulness or
unhelpfulness
um, when talking about misinformation.
Anything else to add before we move
around the circle?
>> I I think we should keep turn taking
>> and taking. Okay. So, I'm going to turn
to Susan next.
>> And what I do now is briefly summarize
what I found interesting about Andrew's
um sharing before I share myself. So,
yeah. Um what I really liked about
Andrew, what Andrew shared is that um he
gave an example of when something can be
um viewed as unhelpful
but actually be accurate and then he
gave a an example of the opposite case.
So um for me that opened up
uh
something around transdisciplinary work
when new teams come together and they
um you may have
uh
an expert who's got a um special
interest and they are hearing lots of
information from someone else. So it
could be they're hearing some
information from a finance team for
example um or a engineer but they don't
view that information as helpful. Their
interest might be on um let's say the
psychology of the issue.
So they may discard it as not helpful
information but actually for the project
as a whole it may be useful. So for me
that presents a real challenge. How do
you help each member of a
transdisciplinary group see the value of
information if it has got value?
That's all I want to share.
Okay. Um, so reflecting back, I think
Ian was thinking about I think Ian, you
were thinking about situations where you
hear or one hears information and one
isn't necessarily sure in a group why
that information is being presented. Is
is that correct?
>> Yes. Yep.
>> And then you have to try to figure out
what to do about that presentation.
And um did you come up with any have you
thought of ideas for what ways to manage
a situation where information is coming
up and you're not sure how to how to use
it?
>> I guess um what's coming to mind is
there's a proactive and a reactive way.
So the proactive way might be a group
member might sort of put their hand up
and say, "Excuse me, I'm not um sure
about the significance of that
information." um or I'm not sure about a
terminology, maybe I just don't
understand the vocabulary being used.
That requires the person to feel
confident about their uncertainty. Um
another way
I can imagine is to um maybe the
facilitator or the organizer supporting
or scaffolding that uncertainty in some
way. So being prepared that people will
not know the significance of each
other's information and putting in place
some kind of process either background
information or some kind of um glossery
or translation tool to help members to
um realize the significance
for new groups.
So you're saying basically that if in a
group where information is presented uh
someone's struggling to understand
whether it's useful or not, they could
ask the person themselves and say, "I'm
not sure why you're saying that or or
maybe I just don't understand it." Or um
which puts pressure on them in a sort of
social context to say that they don't
understand which may be uncomfortable.
And then on the other side, it could be
the role of the facilitator to realize
that there are gaps in communication and
step in and try to fill them. Is that
sort of what you're suggesting?
>> That's it. Yes. Yeah. Thank you.
>> Yeah.
So,
>> so I I don't think I um I don't think I
have any of anything else to add at this
point. So, um, Susan, you're welcome to
turn virtually towards Leonardo and
share your thoughts on this topic.
Yeah, I think this topic is really
interesting because what it it it seems
often in transdisciplinary groups, it's
very hard to understand
whether you don't understand what
they're saying or you don't understand
why what they're saying is relevant or
they're what they're saying isn't
relevant. And so you're always in this
sort of internal quandry and trying to
think how do I present this in some way
that you know yes I may have to show my
ignorance but on the in the goal of
moving the discussion forward how do I
react to this and so I think that that
people um I think facilitators are often
hired for reasons that they can try to
bridge those gaps and help people
understand them. But I think sometimes
facilitators either don't know the
topics well enough to be facilitating
those topics and that can create more
trouble. So um I found some of these
discussions to be kind of difficult for
the reasons that uh both Andrew and Ian
have mentioned. And I wonder Leonardo um
what are your thoughts on this? And is
anything I've said resonating?
>> Um thank you Susan. This is a very
interesting topic. I'll just start by uh
making sure I understand what you've uh
explained to me. So you're saying that
um you can see the importance of the of
understanding unhelpful information in
transdisiplinary groups. Um because we
as a listener we might uh develop
internal troubles uh because we might be
afraid of looking ignorant if we don't
understand something.
We have to balance it with the uh desire
to progress the conversation.
And so um am I understanding? Is this
relevant? Well, maybe a facilitator can
help to understand to make sure that the
language is a bit more uh commonly
understood. But the problem here is that
uh they might not be an expert and might
actually make the discussion uh even
muddier.
Is that's um the main topic or is there
something else you you'd like to
mention?
>> No, I I think that's the main topic. I
think the other piece is trying to
figure out whether the what the person
said really was uh on par for the
discussion or was sort of something that
was leading the whole group off in the
wrong direction. And I really don't know
how you deal with that.
>> I see. So that is a interesting problem
to tackle.
in in problem solving situations. Yeah.
So now do I
turn to someone or
>> Yes, Leonardo. So
>> So um Susan, do you have anything else
to add before?
>> I do not.
>> So now we would at the bare minimum we
would close the circle. So, Leonardo,
you would turn towards Andrew
and share a bit of a summary of what
you've heard before and then add your
own
new insight.
>> Fantastic.
So the discussion Andrew so far um has
been about around
uh really unhelpful
information whether we can uh in
transdisciplinary groups um able to see
what is really significant to the
overall topic conversation with the
group or what can we ignore and how can
we address this problem of whether
something is unhelpful given even that
we're not an expert in what the speaker
is saying or even the facilitator
is not an expert on what's being
discussed. Um I found the role of the
facilitator actually very important in
the what I've been hearing in this
discussion. It seems like it's a good
solution could be sending some
premeating readings that aren't too
long. Maybe all individual all the
individuals should send out at least um
a few bullet points relating to the
discussion before.
Um then
so
in the situation of misinformation and
unhelpful
um the difference in that I mean that I
feel like if if you're saying something
as an expert
um it's maybe important to say that this
is a true thing this is evidence backed
and maybe coming back in your
explanations that um well this relates
in this way to the overall topic and I
mentioned on the the fact of saying that
what the statement you've expressed is
true um to emphasize the truthfulness of
your statement because if if it's
unhelpful
um and false it it won't bring to the
conversation. So it's just saying well
I'm not trying to invent something. So
yes, I think that was um to emphasize
the truthfulness of Usain and the
relevance to the overall topic every
time we express a statement
and
our premeating readings.
So what do you think of that Andrew?
>> Sure. Thanks Leonardo. Um so to kind of
recap my understanding of everything
um so we have we're looking at the
notion of unhelpful information in the
context of transdisciplinary work. Um
how do we kind of see the overall
significance of particular pieces of
information to the whole group? What can
we ignore or perhaps what should we
realize we shouldn't ignore? Um and you
laid emphasis upon the role of the
facilitator. Uh seems to be very
important and they could perhaps help
with organizing a bed through uh sending
out premeating readings or or bullet
points in advance of the discussion uh
to maybe establish some kind of initial
common ground between everyone and maybe
what they're thinking about. But then
that said, um, being able to relate
different pieces of information to
various topics or in the context of
transdisciplinary research, uh, relating
like the same topic to potentially
different disciplines, I could also see
coming in there and, um, so being able
to keep those connections. Um, have I
done a fair enough job in kind of kind
of recapping there a bit?
>> Definitely. Definitely. Um, and there
was just one point I wasn't too sure how
to address it in the but it would be
that to emphasize the truthfulness of
the statements. So I guess as an expert
you you want to you suppose you're
saying something truthful but you know I
don't know if that's um it's just an
idea. I'm not sure if it's um practical
but um in the in the um definitely the
relevance to the overall topic is the
most important as you've uh repeated
Andrew.
I say
Ian, do I should I continue?
>> So you can you can maybe um
so Leonardo wanted to add an extra
detail. So if you're able to can you
reflect that back to him?
>> Yeah. Uh
I mean
to to emphasize the truthfulness of the
information you're sharing. I mean, I
find that quite significant as far as I
understand bringing that up because if
you know, if you're working with a team
of people and you introduce, you know,
say a new concept that's otherwise
foreign to them, um, then if they're not
able to sort of relate it back to their
own uh, discipline and, you know, you
could sort of inject the the active
inference framework here a little bit
and say like if you say something that
simply does not sort of correspond
respond in some meaningful way at least
at a baseline at a micro scale as a
starting point with their their prior
beliefs about you know whether it be the
world at large or at least like how
their discipline works or their general
topics and and and folky that they focus
on then yeah I think I think well in
that case you'll really want to like
bridge that gap for them uh in a way
that you can you can justify by saying
that there's some truthfulness here. So,
um, so like social science, uh, music
and clinical research,
um, you know, if you and I could
establish some kind of gap or even if I
was sort of like proverbally selling
active inference to you, saying like,
oh, you should use active inference,
here's why. Here are various, you know,
papers that have been published on like
dynamics and clinical therapy that
relate back to the active inference
framework and how it can be useful. So
being able to just kind of provide that
sort of additional information that can
help establish that connection
potentially in a way that exceeds just
me saying it to you, right? It's like
no, it's, you know, not to appeal to
authority here, but here are some
published papers, you know, that that
have much more detail if you want to
pursue that further if it piques your
interest. So that's one way to deal with
that.
>> Great. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Referring to
the published evidence, it's a great
way. Thank you.
Okay, thank you. So, I think we'll close
the the demonstration and close the
circle there. What can be done with this
type of um process is that you can keep
going round the circle again. So, you
can see what else evolves with another
another round. But given the the time
constraints today, um we'll draw towards
the end. I would like to hear
um any views that you have and it can be
kind of popcorn style so any any person
can speak first um about how you found
this process. So you all kindly gave up
some time before this session to have a
practice with me and we practiced with
the simple question of please tell me
about your name and we went through some
uh a round of reflection there. So you
you've experienced it twice now. Do you
have any thoughts about um how this
process of turn taking and reflection
um could be useful or not or where it
could not be useful?
>> I can go first. Yeah, I I think it is I
think it is helpful because you uh get a
chance to sort of hear how other people
perceived what you said which helps you
clarify your own thinking. Uh you think
oh is that how I put that? Okay. And you
get so so you have that role of
self-reflection on your own thought but
then you also hear how the um how the
thoughts of others dovetail and
interact. And I felt like we were moving
towards a conclusion. If we had another
couple of rounds, we might have come up
with a sort of, you know, tiny version
of how you should start organizing a
certain kind of discussion. So, I
thought it was helpful.
>> Thank you. Anything else to add, Andrew
or Leonardo?
I don't know why I saying I agree with
Susan that it is helpful and we were
getting closer to a a conclusion for
sure. It still feels a bit uncomfortable
to make sure you're Oh, am I fully
understanding? Am I having am I
repeating well, but um I think it's a
good process. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I uh I mean I think I think it's
great and uh just so that I can add a
little bit more. Hopefully not too much.
I'm trying not to go into like teaching
mode, but you brought up the the bird
song example in your introductory slides
to this. And what I love about that
example is through the turnt taking
between the the song birds, it's not
just that they're kind of mutually uh
reducing prediction error, but if you
actually look, and this is where it gets
a little mathy, I don't want to get too
abstract, but if you actually look at
sort of the state space that they
collaboratively explore, um it starts to
expand. So they start to synchronize but
explore new places in the state space
that neither one of them have
individually explored before. So through
this kind of collective emergent
behavior they traverse new territory.
And so if you bring that back to us
talking, it's kind of like, well, we all
sort of have our own mutive
explored spaces around these topics, you
know, our own degree of interest, but by
going around the circle, I I agree with
with Leonardo and Susan that it did seem
like we're kind of reaching a new sort
of conclusion about these things. And in
some way it's kind of like where it's
through this turnt taking that we can
kind of reach new places and
conversation and our thinking that
wasn't may or may not uh I won't be
overly optimistic but may or may not
have been immediately available to us
before doing this. So basically
collaborative exploration leads to new
insights that weren't available before
potentially. So yeah I think it's great.
>> Very nice.
>> Thank you. Yeah, that was really um
useful to hear that view from an expert
in the maths behind active inference.
So thank you three for helping uh to
rescue this session with the technical
difficulties and I hope it will be made
available um to the symposium and I'm
also interested in um working up this
style of uh communication and group
practice and translating it into the
language of active inference for other
people to use.
So, thank you for joining.
>> You're welcome.
>> Thank you so much.
>> Thank you.
All right, next pre-recorded video is
going to be Sanjie Nam joi fundamentals
of active inference a self-guided
textbook for learning and applying
active inference from first principles.
This is going to be a 20inut video.
Hello, my name is Sanjie Namjoshi and
I'm a machine learning engineer working
at verses. If you've ever tried to learn
active inference, you probably know what
it feels like to get lost in a maze of
subdisciplines. Neuroscience,
information theory, Beijian statistics,
physics, and more. Every paper seems to
assume you already know three other
fields with different mathematical
notations. equations seem to materialize
out of nowhere with few good resources
explaining where they came from or how
they're even useful in the first place.
Today, I would like to talk to you about
my my progress toward providing greater
accessibility, visibility, and knowledge
of active inference and the free energy
principle.
I'm excited to announce that my textbook
fundamentals of active inference is
complete and will be released in March
2026 from the MIT press.
My aim for this textbook is to provide a
unified, systematic and rigorous
foundation for students and researchers
entering the field to reduce the steep
learning curve. However, an important
motivating question is why should you
learn active inference in 2025? To
answer this question, I think it is
helpful to turn the clock back 2006 and
draw a comparison between the state of
deep learning in its early days and
active inference as we understand it
today.
Prior to the mid-200s, neural networks
were just one of many possible models
rather than the dominant choice in
academia and industry. This all changed
in 2006 when Hinton and his colleagues
released the deep belief network paper
which is generally understood as the
start of deep learning as we understand
it today.
After some various hardware innovations
and the release of the well-known
imageet library,
we started to see more coverage and
success of AI in the news. But in 2012,
deep learning truly provided its value
with AlexNet. And for the first time, it
achieved better than human performance
on image detection tasks.
But this was just the start. What
followed was a proliferation of deep
learning across industry and research.
I've added some well-known milestones
just to highlight the explosion of
progress in deep learning in the last
decade. But there is so much more that
deserves mention and attention here.
And since I presented about my textbook
at the 2023 active inference symposium,
the state of AI has dramatically changed
once again. Today, large language models
dominate the AI landscape and have
managed to overshadow many other fields
and alternative approaches. New and more
powerful language models are released
every quarter, though the rate of
advancement over previous models is
beginning to slow. So what about the
state of active inference as a field?
From my perspective, active inference
lies in the same position as deep
learning did in 2006, influential and on
the brink of exploding in popularity and
relevance.
This paper here um from which this
figure comes from is from contributors
at the active inference institute and
shows the current growth of publications
in the active inference community. In
the last few years, active inference as
a field has seen a number of important
milestones. Here I show just a few that
broaden the scope and attention to the
field. We have the first international
workshop on active inference in 2020.
We have the first applied active
inference symposium and the foundation
of the active inference institute.
We have the release of the par
pizzazzulo and fristen 2022 book as well
as the pmdp library. And from 2023 to
present there are so many pieces and
changes here. Uh some of which include
new Julia packages RX infer um and many
many more papers in robotics and other
industries as the international workshop
of active inference has begun to grow
and grow and grow.
I see active inference as perfectly
poised for greater visibility and
attention, especially given the current
interest in generative AI and deep
reinforcement learning. Working
alongside the active inference institute
and other organizations, my aim here is
to provide some of the fundamental
materials to capture the attention and
notice of machine learning researchers
and students to bridge this gap to bring
active inference into its renaissance.
So why learn active inference in 2025?
Well, active inference is highly
interpretable. The very nature of
Beijian networks means that you can
follow the chain of reasoning through a
particular problem to see why a certain
um outcome was chosen over others for a
particular model, why a particular
policy was chosen. For example,
active inference comes equipped with a
principled modeling system, a way to
model any system of interest using an
elegant and all-encompassing
encompassing formalism based in
information theory.
Active inference also has a more robust
interpretation of agency than current
LLMs as we talk about agency in a lot of
industry contexts today and includes an
aspect of control of the external
environment. Active inference is
fundamentally compatible with the notion
of world models that capture the cause
effect understanding of the external
world and it's believed these world
models um are very important for pre
preventing hallucinations that we see in
large language models.
Active inference can also be used to
solve everyday practical problems in
research and in industry.
And it may also expand the field of
complex systems modeling which is
central to fields such as physics,
climate science, economics, political
theory, psychology, sociology, and more.
Active inference also provides a
convenient way to univise unify many
disperate fields that are exploring the
same ideas in different languages or
scientific conventions.
And although it's been yet to be fully
demonstrated, active inference does have
the potential to be more cost and sample
efficient at scale. And more research
needs to go into this area, which is why
we need a new generation of active
inference researchers uh coming to
contribute to the field.
Due to the current state of active
inference and its potential as a premier
AI research framework, my aim is to
expand the reach of active inference
beyond its current confines.
To this end, I've aimed to make my
textbook as accessible for the widest
audience possible with the least amount
of required prerequisites. The major
focus is writing this book for an
engineering audience. Both machine
learning engineers and traditional
engineering disciplines. Neuroscience is
largely out of scope for this book and
there are many other resources available
if you're interested in that particular
aspect of the free energy principle and
active inference.
Many of the recommended and even
optional prerequisites that you see here
are typically known by undergraduate
students in science and engineering and
certainly by graduate students in these
fields. Nevertheless, the book is also
written to be readable for those that
desire to focus on everything. The
completionist that wants to know all the
math, the concepts, and the code. It's
also suited for people who are more
interested in the theory. uh maybe just
interested in the math and concepts to
get a general sense of things so they
can dive into the literature further.
And my hope is that ultimately um those
who are intuitionists who want to skim
over the math and just get a sense of
the ideas should still be able to read
this book. And ultimately I hope to
convince you by reading this textbook
that active inference may be challenging
but it is not impossible to learn by any
means.
Part one of the book called fundamentals
will set the stage by describing the
statistical setting with an agent
interacting with its environment. We
start as simple as possible with a
single state and a single data point and
then we begin to expand from there.
Connections are made in chapter 3 to
other classical parameter estimation
techniques in statistics as well as a
complete investigation into the basics
of variational basian inference which
happens in chapter 4 where variational
free energy is also introduced. The
field of predictive coding is also
explored in part one which we can see as
a kind of precursor one of the
precursors to the modern formulation of
active inference. And this will also
allow us to introduce the notion of
prediction errors which are ubiquitous
in the active inference and also the
neuroscience literature.
Part two, the active inference core now
introduces the core active inference
methodologies. Chapters 6, seven and 8
focusing on continuous state spaces and
chapters 9 and 10 uh focusing on
discrete state spaces. Like part one, we
start simple in the simplest possible
model we can imagine and then begin to
grow and build up the model to the full
vanilla active inference agent step by
step.
Part three, applications and extensions
cover various developments that have uh
occurred in the last uh 8 to 7 8 to 10
years uh in the field which include um
modifications and extensions to base
active inference and also a number of
other topics included here like
structure learning, factor graphs,
robotic applications, different types of
free energies, hybrid discrete and
continuous models, the free energy
principle and so on.
There are also extensive appendices
covering the history of the field and
its connection to other fields, a deep
overview of all notation in the book, a
uh exhaustive summary of the different
forms of variational free energy you
might find in the literature, and a
least you need to know for all
background mathematical topics in active
inference. Um, you can see here that
there's a lot of coverage that gives you
the basic details. So even if you're not
an expert in all of these different
background topics, you have enough of a
sense of how to actually understand why
they're relevant in the context of
active inference and understand when
they show up in various papers of
interest.
So now I'd like to give you a preview of
what's contained in the textbook itself.
Type setting and style is extremely
important to successful learning. So
I've spent a lot of time attempting to
make my work clear and readable. Margins
are used for footnotes and supplemental
figures uh that can aid reading
comprehension.
There's a large focus on building
intuitive understanding of concepts. For
example, all algorithms are explained
from scratch.
And in this book we uh start from a
description of the agent environment
modeling problem. Describe the
univariate case extend the multivariate
case. Then we introduce variational
inference. Add dynamics. Add generalized
coordinates if applicable. Uh we look at
hierarchical models and we also look at
action building on it step by step and
then looking also at learning and
attention as well to see how they fit
into the broader framework.
Figures are designed to clearly walk the
reader through the text and give
detailed visualizations of important
concepts.
There are also concept maps provided for
most chapters which lay out the
fundamental vocabulary that will be
covered in the chapter and show how
they're all interrelated to one another.
And this should hopefully form a useful
guide as the different sections are also
numbered and shown in the concept map so
you can understand where that topic
comes from and how it relates to
something else that you may have read
earlier in the text.
The early part of the book focuses on
basic concepts such as hidden state
estimation that is estimating the
conditional distribution of a latent
variable given observed data. And the
aim here is to explain the modeling
paradigm in the context of an agent
attempting to infer the states of the
environment. This is an interaction
between a generative model and a
generative process. And this is a
perspective that differs from the way
that Beijian inference is normally
taught. In chapter 3 and also in the
code notebooks that I'll talk about in a
moment, we go through this perspective
taking something as simple as linear
regression and putting it into the
context of an agent environment
interaction to really make those
concepts clear and understandable.
Typically, introductory Beijian
inference books focus on parameter
estimation or what we call learning in
this book. And in part one, I introduced
the expectation maximization algorithm
to make it clear what the relationship
is between classical parameter learning
and estimation techniques that you might
see in a basian context in certain
textbooks and this notion of hidden
state inference. We deal with latent
variable models to understand how they
connect together within one algorithm
which sets the stage for the active
inference models that come later.
Variational inference is also explained
in detail. The book features a catalog
of all the different forms of
variational free energy or expected free
energy in the literature and how they
can be derived from one another and how
the different forms interrelate.
The book also covers raw and Ballard
style predictive coding terms and ideas
such as prediction error minimization
as well as a clear explanation of
fundamental concepts such as surprisal
and variational free energy.
I'm also making extensive use of Bashian
networks in this book so that all models
can be seen graphically and we also
build up starting simple to more and
more complex models throughout the book.
Factor graphs which are an alternative
way of representing Beijian networks
that have a number of other interesting
and very useful properties um are
explained in chapter 12 where I go
through all the different models we've
seen so far in the book and show how
they can be represented as a factor
graph to build that intuition and
understanding of how these kinds of
models work.
There are more than 230 custom figures
that have been created for the book,
most of which are full color. And the
figures are extremely detailed to give
the reader a deep understanding of the
content that I provide in the book.
And many of the models presented in the
book in the book are also shown in
pseudo code which would aid in
implementation. My aim for readers is to
go through these algorithms and be able
to implement them in code yourselves.
Although code will also be provided for
those who also want to learn through
reading the notebooks and running
pre-existing code.
Finally, each chapter is filled with
numerous examples and simulations. These
examples correspond to the Jupyter
notebooks that I will be talking about
in a moment and try to show the
application of a particular concept in a
simulated environment.
So now let's shift our attention to some
of the supplemental materials that are
going to be provided. A few months after
publication, um Jupyter notebooks will
be uh released on GitHub and be fully
reproducible using Docker or other
version um version handling tools. The
notebooks will recapitulate every single
figure that's shown in the book, all
simulations in the book and all
background material with explanations
for all this all these uh different
items. And it will also come with a
library of modular functions that can be
used to build custom active inference
agents in environments fit for learning
purposes. These modular pieces can
essentially be mixed and matched inside
different environments or agents. And
that's how these Jupyter notebooks often
proceed. They'll explain the basic
concept first and then use those
components or tools to build up an agent
that does a particular task. Uh that's
corresponds to whatever is being uh
presented in that particular chapter.
There's a direct correspondence between
the equations that you see in the text
and the uh notebook u Jupyter notebook
code as well. So here's an example
showing um variational free energy um in
one particular simplified form that you
can see here and I've tried to match the
kinds of style of variables on the left
here uh showing you how the matrix
multiplication and addition and these
different components fit together. So as
close as I possibly can I've tried to
match them so it's very easy to see when
you read through the notebooks exactly
what that equation is telling you.
And this is just another example here
showing that um there are detailed
walkthroughs of different kinds of
things. Here I'm showing you colored
noise and how you can smooth out a noisy
signal by passing over a Gaussian filter
and get smooth or colored noise which is
very useful in active inference
simulations and is present in a lot of
raw data uh that sensors might pick up.
There are also going to be uh full video
presentations for each chapter. Um this
is going to be a project that I'll be
working on in the uh late future after
the book is released. Um but this uh the
idea would be to eventually have an
active inference course and you can see
some of the details here of uh some
slides that I've created uh along the
route to this this goal.
A good majority of proofs had to be cut
from the book due to space concerns. um
and I will collect all of those as well
as other proofs um in a document on
archive that will um contain all proofs
for every equation in the active
inference literature. So the aim is if
you ever see an equation you don't know
where it comes from, you should be able
to look it up in this guide and be able
to find how it was derived and what
assumptions were made in that
derivation.
So finally, let's talk about a few of
the planned future resources I'd like to
work on to further support the
educational tooling around the book.
There are two potential side projects
I'm interested in working on with
collabor collaborators. The first is
providing a software suite for
continuous state space active inference
and a basian mechanics simulation suite.
Um these will both be very useful
additions to the field and um allow
people from other disciplines to begin
experimenting with active inference code
and fill the gap right now in the
software ecosystem.
I'm also very much interested in
interactive learning. The aim would be
to have concepts explained in the
textbook with various simulations um
interspersed in the forms of plots uh
plot demos and other visualizations
maybe sliders that you can move around.
You can tweak initial conditions and
parameters and and see how the resulting
plots change.
And this would support um everything
from beijian mechanics to continuous and
discrete space state space active
inference. As you can see, a lot of this
work will um be very involved and take a
lot of time. So, I'm very open to uh any
volunteers that would like to help me
with these projects. So, please contact
me. I have my contact information shown
at the end if you're interested in
contributing to these projects um as I
continue to expand this ecosystem.
I'm also working on a second book um
also to be published by MIT Press called
Fundamentals of Beijian Mechanics. If
you're not familiar with Beijian
mechanics, it's an entirely separate
field um related to active inference and
the free energy principle that talks
about the separation between different
kinds of stochastic processes uh
separated by what's called a marov
blanket rendering the two systems
conditionally independent. And this
forms the background formalism and
structure around which active inference
models can be derived. So it's kind of
looking at the bigger picture, looking
at more thermodynamics and living
systems and the mathematics of different
kinds of interacting stoastic processes.
This book which is at the intersection
of information theory and physics um is
currently under um a work in progress
and will be released probably sometime
in late 2027. Um and I'll be giving more
updates on that book as I proceed.
So just as another reminder again, my
textbook will be released in March next
year and I'm very excited and looking
forward to educating and collaborating
with a whole new generation of active
inference researchers.
I would like to thank the uh active
inference institute for hosting um
presentation and uh code during the time
when the book was being written. Um I
got a lot of very useful feedback from
everybody that joined in those sessions.
Um, and I really appreciate all of your
hard work. You've all been acknowledged
uh in my um book's preface as well for
all that for all the contributions
there. And um I'd also like to thank my
my employer versus for their continued
support of my book as well as the active
inference community in general with the
international workshops on active
inference. And this is my contact
information. Please feel free to contact
me at any time and email is the easiest
way, but I'm also sometimes on the
active inference institute discord as
well if you'd like to see me on there.
Thank you.
All right, that's the end of this
stream.
Next stream tomorrow,
part two. Bye.